On all the new features we've been working on to make getting your data out to the
community even easier for you. So
with that, I'm going to turn it over to Kevin Holston.
If I can find your presentation.
Thank you, Kevin.
Right here?
All right. So how do I start? Okay, I'm on now.
Okay. Yeah. Thank you. Thank you for the opportunity to come and speak to you
today.
And I know that the SAAS is maybe a little bit
provocative for people, but I'll explain what I mean by that.
Specify as a
Service, ephemeral repositories for collections-based research.
Let's go to this. Okay. So first of all,
well, can I switch? Yeah.
I just want to tell you about the outline for this.
I'll talk about Specify as a Service,
go to
the idea of ephemeral collections and their data repositories, and
talk about why that matters to me. Some examples of this, and of
course, some final assertions.
So,
I'm also trying to go very quickly, so if I see some eyebrows raised, I'll slow
down a little bit.
Most of you know what software as a service means.
This is something that Specify has provided, cloud service
provider for different collections to
be able to use the software
and access the software without having to install it themselves.
And for more information on that, you can go to the website and see that.
It's a service that people would need to use.
But when I'm talking about Specify as a Service, I'm really talking about at the
institution, we've taken another route, which is to have different
local installation for that, running Specify on our own
infrastructure.
And from that,
we can encourage data capture that's
compatible with our local needs.
Local researchers can become familiar with the SEC under some kind of
reduced commitment pressure. In other words, instead of just saying, "Here's
Specify, you should use it," we're trying to ease them into working with
Specify. And also, it means that for test purposes and
whatever else, we often are spinning up temporary
instances anyway of Specify, but we can leverage that and maybe use that for
people who are coming into, say, our collections as visiting researchers and
say, "Here's an instance of Specify for you. You can do your digitization.
We can help them with getting information in and out," but it's already compatible
with what we're already using at our institution.
And of course, as you know, with Specify as a Service or Specify in general, the
import/export, batch editing, all these different tools are already available for
them. And
perhaps this will get them excited about working with Specify as they go back to
their home institutions. And certainly, the data exchange will be something useful
for us
at the NRM.
So I'll talk a little bit about
this era of extending specimens. We're all very aware of this.
There have been a lot of historical precedents
for people working with voucher specimens, dissecting them, moving them out
in different parts of the collection.
But we can say that curation workflows have always included recording things like
biological observations that are referring to the voucher, not necessarily to those
derivative objects that are ultimately curated.
And that what we need to do in our collections often is to improve our coordination
of these voucher processing, so that it can serve immediate needs and also
long-term needs of our researchers and public collection staff.
So with this era of extended specimens, you also have this
proliferation of semi-persistent actual collection repositories
of this material that's taken out from these different
voucher specimens. And it's arranged at different institutions and laboratories,
and these represent semi-persistent vouchers.
They are actually looked at, especially in the biobanks, as vouchers.
But they're expected to be used up over a certain period of time, and this is why
I'm calling them semi-persistent, even though curation or examination has always
resulted in some object damage. Of course, I've been in collections myself to
work with specimens, and even if you don't want to do destructive sampling,
sometimes you do by breaking off a leg or two. So that happens.
But the best example of this kind of semi-persistent collection repository is the
biobank.
And we have an eDNA collection in our museum as well that
corresponds to this.
So to go back to ephemeral collections,
temporary and semi-persistent, I can talk about two categories.
Category one could be the research group, and category two would be the research
institution. And so with category one, the
collection itself is temporary. It's just material that has come in on
loan. Someone is using it, the lab or research group is using it.
Some of the material will be used for destructive sampling, but probably not.
Usually, it goes back to that institution.
Category two is within an institution, often,
that's managing it, like the biobank.
The material is semi-persistent, you could call it voucher material,
and is subject to material depletion.
And it's very hard for me to read this, but it's easy for me to read it here.
Historically, derivatives generated during research have been documented as
voucher attributes rather than as independent objects.
And that's important because the way that we're trying to track the information
over time, depending upon how you're modeling it within the database,
it has a
strong impact on how well you're able to talk about what's happening to objects
over time, what the attributes actually are, where the objects actually are in
space. So it's important to come back to that.
But this has been done historically, especially in vertebrate collections, for
quite some time, distributing vouchers.
As far as category one, the research
group, probably a good example is maybe you could say
a network or domain, and this is the portal for AntWeb, which is a great
website. It has everything from specimens to
taxonomic data.
But in this, you could think about that as a research group kind of context.
The material is owned by different institutions, managed by loan.
You have persistent vouchers,
and the motivation and ability for project data repository itself to say
where things are physically is quite low.
Research groups are emphasizing
a persistent data repository as opposed to a specimen repository,
which you can say there's a contrast.
The thing is, as well, when you have independent researchers, often what you have
is not necessarily a well-defined, sophisticated network
or a digital infrastructure for handling the data.
We often have things like the spreadsheets, the papers, et cetera, and then as
part of the process of research on that group, you
organize that data. And I guess I'm putting this image here just to help you to
think about this is also why I think getting Specify in a little bit early in the
process would be helpful for all of us who are involved.
The second category was the research institution, and as I was saying before,
category one maybe you could look at as projects.
Category two is maybe programs.
Semi-persistent vouchers, like I said before, but the motivation and ability for a
data repository to reflect what's in the physical collection is quite high, so it's
more like a traditional collection.
And having that persistent repository, specimen repository is actually
important. But like I said, semi-persistent voucher.
And I'm not going to go into the different networks that are
available, but just to say that I'll come back to this with an
example later.
So as an example of category one at our institution, we have Johannes Beierstein.
Raza was actually working with him, and she's worked on this part of the
presentation here, or this part of the
instances for Specify.
So in thinking about Specify as a service for him, his motivation was about
rapid data entry from inventory. His inventories of aquatic
insect fauna from Madagascar, and was looking at maybe a Specify work
solution to do some rapid entry. And so that's why he came to us and said, well,
maybe we can do something like this for him.
So this is becoming his
research database. Whereas before-- Five minutes?
I have plenty of time then.
But this became his research
database.
What I'm saying is a surprise benefit for him is that he was seeing that in this
process, there was a lot more standardization.
He's very organized, don't get me wrong, very organized. He knows what he's doing.
But there was still some standardization that came through that process of getting
the data prepared to put into or to import to Specify.
So I helped him out on that, but particularly the digital assets, thinking
about images and permits, et cetera.
And Raza helped out quite a lot with the images for the, you'll see this in a
minute, the collecting events.
And what I'm saying by push is just my desire that there's a little bit
more
unambiguous data compilation and sharing of objects that are on loan
and from other collections. So in other words, having his collection
exist the way that it does, he has collections.
He's dealing with specimens from all over, not just at our institution.
And if you did that within the home collection, it would be a little
bit more difficult to try to tease that out and figure out what should be part of
it, what should be out of it. But to facilitate the data exchange between,
say, his work and the museum's work, the NRM's work
with those specimens. So just a few examples to show.
This represents 16 years of his collecting in Madagascar, and I've
compiled this as
collecting trips.
This is 808 events, collecting events.
Again, standardization that's coming through that.
And something that we didn't think about at the very beginning, but this allowed us
to be able to organize all of his collecting event
images throughout these
16 years of trips,
as well as field data
sheets that are associated with those collecting events.
So that was something that was a little bit of a surprise for him, maybe, but it's
not just the rapid data entry that we knew was going to happen, but this was
something else that came through that work.
This is me
back in the early aughts.
Just to think about, there are some other things that we can collect, not just
collections data, but maybe observations and things like that, that are
important to a researcher. And mid-'20s, I'm just saying that in the
mid-'20s, not me in my mid-20s, but I shifted over from Specify 6 to
7.
And I just wanted to show you a couple of features there
that talk about the flexibility of Specify.
Instead of focusing on, say, the physical position of
specimens in a collection, I used Specify Storage to look at things like
provenance, which is basically loans.
And so I was able to
use that
and to, of course, deal with the observations, the images, track
them back to their original URLs, which are shown there.
But the traditional is also available, which is registering collection
objects from all these different museums.
You can see there's storage, but it's actually talking about, "This is my loan,"
basically, my loan organization units,
and of course, the specimens that are associated with it.
Now, a very quick aside.
I want us to think about what we're doing more in terms of inviting people
into our collections as a laboratory,
where there's infrastructure. You want to be able to come in with your methods,
your local infrastructure is generating data, and then you leave with a copy,
hopefully, of your data, not just the data.
But there also is-- it sets us up to look at a little bit more
alternatives here, such as
moving into a house or visiting a hotel. Do we furnish it or do we not furnish it?
And there's some different implications for each of those.
So we could spin up an instance of Specify, for example, with more or less of your
data from your collection, and it gives them a head start in
digitizing whatever collections they're working on or looking at.
In this case, collecting objects. Another case might be localities.
And very quickly, I'll talk about category two, which is just environmental
specimen bank.
Lots of different aspects of objects that they're dealing with in different
workflows. And what this is allowing us to do is to push us
into a better organization of the data,
and that's very exciting recent work.
So we want to be able to--
My time is up now, and I just wanted to say that we have initial
data standards,
data compilation that we want to think about coming in very
early in the process, strengthening our relationships with the researchers,
and then finally, and probably you've heard the first one already, but I really
want this to say that these instances can be these laboratories of
innovation. That's where a lot of the recent work or some of the work that's been
done in terms of pushing Specify to
have different capabilities has come.
And we can get, I think, a lot of that from engaging with our researchers as a
resource better. Okay. Thank you. Sorry about the time.
Do you want me to take this?
Yep, take it back there.
Oh. I'm just going to lose my mic. It's fine.
I talk loud enough. It's fine.
Thank you very much, Kevin. Next up is Robyn Drinkwater from
Royal Botanic Garden Edinburgh.
I do want to put in one quick plug,
and I'm going to put more in later. So this one is just for now.
If you have not, please come up and see Amy, raise your
hand,
or Grant.
You can come get one of our bandanas
to take home. We have a lot of stickers for everybody.
So
come and find us here later, whenever.
We're more than happy to not take these home.
So,
okay. Robyn.
Okay.
So I'm from the Royal Botanic Garden Edinburgh.
Realized I hadn't put it on my slide, but we're a herbarium collection of around
three million specimens, primarily sheets, but also
a lot of the other groups,
including our pathological. And we cover all groups that are
traditionally considered plants, so that includes things like diatoms, algae,
oomycetes. So it's quite a wide collection.
We've had some level of databasing going on in our collection since around
the mid 1970s. This has given us a really long
legacy of data that we need to deal with and attempt to
clean and standardize.
I think in that time, we've probably gone through at least four different database
systems, maybe slightly more. There's four I'm aware of.
So as
we've moved through these different databases, we've tried to improve the
standardization of our data and the cleaning within
those systems as well, and each database has allowed us to do more
of that as they have improved. And then as standards have come
in, we've had to look at ways of how we then introduce these to our
records. At this point, we're around 1.5
million database records that we're trying to work
with and get these various standards associated with.
I'm going to focus on identifiers for how we're linking and working with our data,
both
to push data out externally, but also to create relationships within the
various systems at RBGE.
So in terms of agents and agent identifiers,
our previous database didn't have a unified agents
or names, peoples table. They came from at least
four different places. If you were a collector, that was in one table.
If you
had a destructive sampling request, that was something else.
A user was another thing. At the point of migrating into Specify, we had
four or five versions of some people in our system, which is a
lovely thing to get to deal with.
Thankfully, there's the agent merging tool in Specify, which has
really helped us with this process as we've been sort of working through
trying to disambiguate our staff. Some of them are very easy.
They're well-known, very clear. So those are the quick and easy ones.
But we've had to keep going and there's still a lot of disambiguation to do
and merging to do with our agents to try and at least
clean it, and get us down to maybe one version of each person rather than
five.
We've always had geographies and specialties, and we've been able to maintain that
through in Specify as well, and this really helps with understanding our
collectors, along with a lot of the other
fields like remarks and active periods.
We've now been able to start adding
identifiers with the dedicated agent identifiers field in
Specify, which is great because it allows us to hold multiple different
identifiers for an individual agent if they exist.
And the one step that I have to do, and I still haven't, is put the link outs to
the agent to the various resources, which will help our staff when they're
working with the collections. Because whilst we do have a level of information
stored within Specify itself,
by creating those link outs, we can get enhanced data for those
individuals through ORCID or through Wikidata to
help our staff with that process as well.
We have a lot of taxa that we are dealing with from multiple
groups. So we're trying to include identifiers wherever we can.
We haven't had these in previous systems, so it's something that we're having to
bring in.
Primarily at the moment, it's IPNI IDs for the
vascular plants and MicroBank identifiers for our fungal
collections.
We are in the process of looking at getting the World Flora IDs associated as well,
and whilst there are some relationships between a World Flora ID and an IPNI
ID,
we do want to be able to record both in a record so that we can move through to
those.
Any new names that are added, we can bring these in very easily,
but we've got this legacy of existing taxa that we need to work with,
and we are also looking at how best to manage these.
At the moment,
we're using
one free text field, which isn't great.
So the top black screenshot is from our test
instance where we're looking at bringing in World Flora ID.
It's structured in such a way that we can provide the link out to that, to those
individual records, which again helps our staff when they're curating and working
with the data.
At the moment, we've been using the LSID field for both IPNI identifiers
and MicroBank IDs, which means that if we did want to bring in
link outs, we would struggle because we've got mixed data in that
field. So we're going to have to look at, one, restructuring the IPNI identifier so
that it can link out the structure of that isn't the linkable version,
and that's what we originally started using.
But also, we want to pull our MicroBank identifiers out, and at some
point, we're hoping to get identifiers on the other elements of our collection.
Vascular plants are the easiest to do this for, so those are the ones we've been
focusing on. But as more identifiers for the taxa appear, we want to work with
those more as well.
The last identifier for pushing data out that I'm going to look at
here is our record identifiers. We've been using this CTAF
stable identifier since 2012.
Roger Higham RBG was working on these, so we brought them in very
early in that process. These make our specimens
very citable. They can be cited in electronic journals very easily with links to
our herbarium catalog. It also means we can put a web link on our
barcode field and have links for our staff within
Specify to our herbarium catalog where the specimen images are.
So this means we're not necessarily having to bring images into Specify to
associate that image with a specimen.
We can get quick and easy access to those specimen images,
to work with those
if we're doing things like transcription.
We also have just started Disco,
so we're now going to be looking at what can we do with the Disco DOIs as they get
minted and created, how are we going to be associating those with our
specimen records as well, so that we have a complete
reference for what
is referencing our collections.
We have four primary large
what's classed as preserved collections, or collections, three of which are in the
preserved. We've got the herbarium, which uses Specify.
Our living collection is managed through Iris BG, our library is in
Koha, and our archives are in Atom.
So we have four different collection management systems
across the gardens, but our items often have relationships within
the individual collections. So,
the example here is a rhododendron growing in the garden that was
grown on from either seed or a cutting, a specimen that was
then taken at the same time that that seed and cutting was made in China,
and the letter from George Forrest talking about that particular specimen as he was
writing back. We may also have
field notes that are associated with that.
So how do we start to build those links between our collections?
We've had various projects, some to look at bringing agent identifiers into all of
the collections so we can start linking our agents more easily between the four
different databases.
We've also been looking at how we record artworks that are
maybe associated with a herbarium specimen.
So these are beautiful watercolors by Robert K.
Greville of the mosses he was collecting.
The specimen and the watercolor are both intrinsically linked.
We can't separate them, but we want to have a record of them both in Koha, where we
record our artworks, and in Specify, where we record the specimen.
So we've had a project to look at bringing identifiers into the two collections.
From the Specify side, we're just recording
an associated work, so the type of artwork it is or the type of work
it is, and the identifier in Koha.
But from the Koha side,
they were able to use our
URI to link out to the herbarium specimen.
So that can be on the public-facing catalog.
People can go to that link on Koha and then see the illustration
on the herbarium catalog. So it's a really nice link-
to start bringing those collections together.
Likewise, our living collection, and this is one we're really working on, and we've
still got work that we want to do to try and bring these together.
Our previous CMS had both in the same system, which had a lot of
advantages, and we're trying to look at how we rebuild the links that we
previously had.
At the moment, we can use
the accession number and qualifier to link through to the living catalog.
They use the same format as the URIs for our
herbarium specimens, so we can link the two together really easily,
and you can get a link through to
one of the living catalogs that's public-facing.
It doesn't always have a lot of information, as you can see, but it does have some
additional images of that plant growing in the garden
and giving some more information about it.
There's much more we want to do to try and bring these collections back together.
Hopefully identifiers is going to be one of the ways we can start doing that.
And then
just as a conclusion, we're looking to how we can continue developing this
within the collections.
There's a lot of work to do with the ones we've already got to make those complete,
but we've recently brought in DNA and extraction data into
our collections. So how do we start recording things like the GenBank
or the BOLD identifiers within that?
So we've got records linking back to the extractions,
allowing better access to the data.
We've also got something called Data Heap, where the actual sequencing results go
to, so we're working with the staff who do that to look at how we bring
those links into Specify so that we've got a record going back out.
We're very aware we've not got all of these identifiers in our Darwin Core
export at the moment, so we've got to start bringing
those into our exports so we can start pushing those identifiers out.
And for our internal ones, we've talked about a data lock being in Scotland
as a way of pooling all of the data from these systems to create something that's
much more searchable and accessible.
But there's going to be a lot of work there to start getting more data into all of
these things and elements that we can start linking across them.
And then how do we make these links not just a reference, but an actual
link that's more active between the different elements of the collection to
make them
as unified as they can be whilst being in four different systems,
which each have their purpose for those elements of the collection?
So there's some really interesting things going on with our internal linking that
we're hoping to keep developing over the coming years.
And thank you.
We have one minute for questions. Yep. So we have time for a few questions.
Just, I'm told, one minute. So does anybody have any questions for Robin?
Nope.
Okay. I highly encourage everyone to catch Robin and ask her questions.
They have been super users of Specify for years, so
she has great insights, and she's just fun to talk to.
Thank you.
Okay, so our next speaker is Siyabonga Zamisa from
KwaZulu-Natal Museum. I'm sorry if I didn't
say that right.
And I also wanted to make one more plug,
everyone should have received a message from the conference from
Melina to encourage everyone to pitch ideas for
the Unconference, which is a member-led session tomorrow where you can
talk about the topics that have been brought up here.
So they really encourage you to pitch your ideas of what should be discussed during
that meeting.
Zamisa?
Okay. Siyabonga, sorry.
Okay. Good morning.
Good morning.
How is everyone?
Good.
So yeah, Teresa, it is
KwaZulu-Natal.
So yes, that's where I'm from, South Africa,
south side of South Africa, KwaZulu-Natal.
Just now, a little bit of history that Teresa just reminded me now.
So today we are celebrating Heritage Day in South
Africa,
and it used to be named
Shaka Zulu's Day.
I'm sure
people know Shaka Zulu.
Anyway,
so yeah, today I am just going to take you guys through how
Specify and workflows has made our
job at the KZN Museum a lot
easier. Yeah.
So I am just going to show you guys, take you through our
scale a little bit of what I'm talking about.
So before I talk about the workflows, so let me give you a sense of our scale,
what we have at the museum. So we have 11
collections, which are managed through Specify.
As you can see there, we have over 430,000
records.
And then out of the collections,
the biggest are your Mollusca and your Insecta,
and then with Onychophora,
which makes under 150
records. So why this matters. So we're not talking about one small
homogenous database here, but 11 collections,
each with its own specimen types and its own long history
of data capture. Right. So a little bit of history
of-
The systems that the collections were before Specify.
So as you can see, the entomology from
2003,
they used Access. From Access,
they used Excel, and then Specify in 2012,
and then mollusca
around about 2009. Our database were Access, and then in
2019, Specify. Also, at one's
history of using Rapid,
they moved to Access, I'm not sure when, and then eventually Specify.
So I'm happy to say now from 2019, all of our
collections are in Specify now.
So
what was the issue then? But the problem was not simply that data
lived in different systems.
Information lived across spreadsheets, catalog cards like this
one in the image, and then
even where data had been digitized, the process around it was
not standardized. So each collection had developed its own habit
for capturing, editing, tracking, and sharing information.
And on top of that, things like your images, loans,
it means that the work was repeated.
So we tried to minimize
that.
So what was the solution then? The solution was
Specify. So this led us to a different question.
So 11
collections effectively meant 11 slightly different ways of
working. And inconsistently, historical records made
retrieval of loans, data sharing slower and more error-prone.
So we realized that digitization alone was not enough, but
putting information into a database doesn't automatically create a good
data management.
So the real challenge was organization and procedure, and not only
technological.
Okay.
Sorry about that.
And then, yeah, the solution, that's where I am now. So the solution was Specify.
We decided as a museum to use Specify
as a collections management for ourselves through the help of
an SCF, in this case, which is Natural Science Collections
Facility.
So we partnered together to develop workflows which will make
our work much easier at the museum.
So these are some of the cool things that Specify allows us to do
into the system.
Such things like specimen cataloging,
accessioning new material, georeferencing, taxonomic
management, data image, loan tracking, data cleaning.
So this was cool because as we have 11 collections, it means all
of us now can use this one system and have standards,
and make my job easier as a data technician, so that I don't need to
try and understand what's happening in the data that they give
me. So then I'm going to take you guys through some of the
examples of the workflows that I have developed in the
museum. This is a bounties of data
workflows, how to import. So workflows start and end
somewhere. So this one starts at the creator level, technician
level, anyone who may be a data capture for you guys.
So from there, how we have tried to standardize this process is that
we have this template spreadsheet.
So everyone in the department uses the same spreadsheet across
all 11 collections. So this has been standardized with Darwin Core
terms.
And then what's nice about this spreadsheet is that it
has these fields, and then it has explanation of what each
field requires and how to enter data into that
field so that it becomes easier when one
does the mapping into Specify
workbench.
So and then from there, the next step will be those datasets or
data sheets come to me as a data technician, and then I run
quality check.
I use OpenRefine for that.
From there, spreadsheet is imported to Specify workbench,
and then from there, I'm able to map the Darwin Core term
fields, and then after that, Specify further does data
quality check through the upload processes, and then one is
able to view the final stage upload in the workbench.
Here, you're still safe. If there are errors, we are able to fix those
errors within the system. But if you like, you are able to also
export
your data and import again if you're happy.
And then after that, that way, the final upload
happens and
you are safe. The next one is
the daily data capture and quality assurance
workflows. So this is where I go in into the collections
randomly. I
access a collections day. I take it into my office,
and I try to see if the data in the specimen correlate with the
data in Specify. If it doesn't, obviously necessary changes
are made
both in Specify and updated into the label, and then the
specimen is taken back into the collection.
So this is how we ensure quality in our
collections. Because we are an institution also which
publish data So this quality check is very good
for us before we give data to the rest of the
public through GBIF. So the next one will be, how do we
do that? This is another workflow for that.
So
you build a query in Specify,
and then you export that. Once that is done, open Refine
again, where I do my quality test.
From there, I remove insensitive
species or data. And then through the IPT,
that's where I
get metadata about the datasets, and from there,
I do my down-core mapping, and
one can then publish into
GBIF.
So what has that changed? So it has made
retrieval of information much quicker and faster.
So tracking as well.
We've tried to build consistency, so shared procedures and
templates reduces variation between collections.
Try to FAIR principles, scalability, and
reuse. So results, some of the tangible impact,
how that has impacted us as the KwaZulu-Natal Museum.
So before Specify and their workflows, we didn't have any collections
in GBIF. And after we made a decision to move to
Specify, out of the 11 collections, I'm happy to say
seven are
found in GBIF. And then it has made
accelerating cataloging rates much quicker.
So standardized spreadsheets and Specify workbench tools
magically increase the cataloging and sustaining rates of new incoming
materials. It's made efficient
loans, so significantly reduced loan processing time
and fulfillment turnarounds. So the
lessons from
this process, so digitization is not simply moving
information into a database. So the bigger transformation is
defining a reputable workflow
around the specimen,
the data, the people, and the standards.
So standardize the workflow, improve the data, and reuse
the collection. And that's where I end for
today. Thank you. I would like to thank the KwaZulu-Natal Museum,
my employer, and I would like also to thank the National Science
Facility
for funding me to come here. And obviously, I would like to thank
Grant and the team for always
allowing me to bother them when I need to. Yeah, thank you.
One minute. Okay, we have one minute for questions, if anybody has
questions for Siyabonga.
Oh.
Ooh.
Let's see, turn around.
We have a few.
If you have any questions.
Thank you. It was very interesting.
I was wondering if people in your
museum use Specify software, or if they just use the Excel
template that you provide. And if they use Specify, did you create a
common template of form for all
of the 11 collections, or did you create a single entry form
for each collection? And so, well, the question would be more, how do
you manage to
keep the tension between having, of course, a common template of form and
also, well, the collection of differences?
So how do you manage this
tension?
So we do have a standardized template, but obviously 11
collections means slightly different
interface that you may want and how she would want and how she would
want. So what we did was to contact each
curator,
and ask them how would they like their forms to be like, and then they will tell
us, and then one would
make it as how you want it to be. Yeah, so that it speaks to you
directly. But that's maybe 20%. The rest is
the same across the 11 collections.
Everyone uses Specify at a different level, obviously.
But yeah, ultimately, I'm the one who's there on
top of using it, usage of the system.
Yeah.
Thank you.
We have about 30 more seconds if anyone has any other questions, and there's none
online.
All right.
Thank you very much, Siyabonga.
Next up is Kim Labuschagne.
Hopefully, I did that right.
Sorry.
From the South African National Biodiversity Institute.
Thank you.
Can I change my presentation just to one slide?
I don't need the speaker notes.
Or can I-
The slides.
Hang on just let me change it here.
Presenter. Oh, sorry.
I didn't bring my glasses as well.
There we go.
Okay.
Yeah, let's see if that's...
All right. Good morning, everyone.
My name is Kim Labuschagne, as I was introduced.
I'm from the South African National Biodiversity Institute.
I manage the wildlife biobank there.
So welcome to the presentation. This morning, I'm going to speak about digitize,
standardize, mobilize wildlife biodiversity biobanking with
Specify.
Okay, no, I've done something wrong. I'm sorry.
I changed the view
because the slide was tiny.
Is it back? Okay. It worked for you.
All right. Okay.
So first of all, we've heard a lot about museum collections.
We're a little bit different. We don't keep the entire elephant.
We keep the samples of the elephants, but then we also keep eVouchers.
So those are your photographs.
We need to make sure that we've got a system in place then that can manage all of
the samples, derivatives, everything that belong to one singular animal.
So it's the multiple aliquots, and then also, where are we
storing them?
Okay, there we go. So the Wildlife Biobank, what
are our core functions? So it's to curate and preserve
biomaterials,
for the governance and custodianship of these tissue samples, for
sampling and DNA systems, and then also for
research support and advisory services.
So our workflows from specimen to impact starts on the
left-hand side here. You've got your plan and collect, so it's your sampling,
whether you're going out into the field or you're actually receiving these samples
into the collection.
Process them, preserve and store, manage and integrate the
data, enable the research, and ultimately deliver an impact
to the community.
A little bit of a history. We established in 1994, so
it's almost a 30-year collection that we've got in place.
It's over 250,000 samples from more than
110,000 individual animals, 46 countries.
We've got 14 phyla, 42 classes,
165 orders, 462 families,
1,219 genera, and then this represents almost
1,900 species. So we concentrate on
from marine
to terrestrial invertebrates. We've got
terrestrial mammals. Any wildlife species in South
Africa, we pretty much bank, and then we also receive these
collections from different countries as well once they're in South Africa.
According to the IUCN Red List of species, we have 102
vulnerable species, 72 near threatened,
63 endangered, 26 critically endangered,
three completely extinct in the wild, and then one
extinct,
and that's the western black rhino.
So the rapid expansion of biodiversity in South Africa, led by initiatives
such as the Biodiversity Biobank South Africa project, has created an
urgent need for robust, standardized digitization
and management systems. So if you think of South Africa being a mega
diverse country with over 100,000 species, something needs to be
managed in these collections. So it holds biological
collections, which are used for conservation, research, and sustainable
development.
Previously, there used to be these fragmented collections, fragmented
data. So there's an urgent need for robust,
standardized data digitization, and
management systems to be put in place.
We need the digitization process,
traceability across the full sample life cycle, and then also national
guidelines and critical elements also need to be in place.
So you've got the digitization process, which is your sample, your
taxonomy, your locality, your permits, all of that information, your
traceability. We need to be able to trace a sample as soon as it arrives in the
biobank to when it goes into the freezer to also when it gets distributed as a
sample request. All of this needs to be
captured some way. Every time we move a sample from one freezer to
another freezer, anything like that, that's a QC point because
you've altered the original sample.
That also needs to be captured somewhere.
And then the national guidelines and the critical elements, we deal with a lot of
permits and regulations within South Africa, especially within the animal
sphere because of the disease regulations and also your CITES.
We've got a lot of CITES species, which is also threatened or protected species
within the South African regulations.
So all of this is linked towards the actual specimen
originally and then where it is and all of the information.
So the extended specimen in biodiversity biobanking, so advancing
towards your fair principles always.
We've got voucher specimens information, the collection
event metadata. You can see all of these have got all the little
bullet points underneath them. This is all that we have to consider
within our collection all the time.
It's not just one sample going to a freezer.
Regulatory and ethical information, the biobank information,
the derived data that we get from all of these samples, the associated
ecological information, the linked research outputs,
and then all adhering to fair principles all the time.
So contrasting traditional and extended specimen data models in
biobanking. Gone are the times where it was a leopard tissue sample,
it went to a freezer, and it gets a catalog number.
And
if I think back to when I first started in the biobank in 2005, that's pretty
much how we were working.
Now it's an extended specimen model, so we've got the
leopard tissue sample, we've got a voucher specimen, we've got a field
metadata, we've got the permits, the storage history, the DNA extraction,
genome sequence, disease screening, publications.
All of this needs to get stored somewhere.
So the extended specimen goes even further in our collection.
Within the Sanbi Wildlife Biobank, the collections also include the diverse
taxon sample type, which are linked to permit storage records, images,
molecular data, and metadata. We have 79
different sample types within our collection.
So if we have an opportunity to sample an animal that's been immobilized,
we'll take as many samples as we can, provided the vet is allowing it.
All of these samples are then prepared and then--
Sorry.
My brain is not braining this morning.
Processed into the different derivatives, and then we store from room temperature
down to -196.
And then these include the storage records, the images, the molecular data, and the
metadata.
We had historical chaos years and years ago.
So we had very, very
disconnected systems, the inconsistent
data. So we needed something to be put in place, and this happened around
2013, where we actually implemented Specify into our collection.
So that was the calm solution. And in this way, we were able to
put everything into one system. It was very connected.
The data was clean as soon as it goes in.
We come across some of the bugs every now and again, but those are sorted out quite
quickly, and we've got someone on call all the time as well at SAIB, which is
the South African Institute for Aquatic Biodiversity.
So some of the
processes that we really find a lot of
joy out of using within Specify is, of course, your hierarchical tree
structures. So I love the way that Kevin actually used that and
altered it a little bit, and that just shows how customizable Specify is.
But the taxon tree, because we're dealing with so much biodiversity within South
Africa, we able to see where are our gaps in our collections
as well. Our storage tree is quite important
because of us storing from room temperature down to
-196. We need to know where these samples are.
And then, of course, your geography tree.
We've got nine different provinces within South Africa, so it's quite
diverse where all of these samples are being stored.
This is just an example of our storage tree.
So this is a sample going from the bank that it's
in to the freezer, the section in the freezer, the rack in the freezer,
the box in the rack, the sites in the box, and then the sample.
But this also eliminates your searching, so you're not going to go through hundreds
of boxes trying to find these little samples.
It ensures that the correct samples are always located.
We use a catalog number on the tube on a little sticker, and we've got a barcode
as well to double-check ourselves.
And then this also saves time and resources.
You're not going to multiple different
locations around the biobank trying to look for one sample.
And then also the attachment capabilities.
Because we've got so many different permits and data sheets
and photographs,
using
the attachment function in Specify, we can put all of these
samples into one database and have click on it, and we
know that everything's stored. So it's your compliance and your permits, the dates
and the photographs. It'll be like your spreadsheets.
And then also
all of the chain of custody samples.
We do a lot of chain of custody
sampling, so that means taking the photographs as well to add more value to the
actual sample that we've got in the biobank.
And then also your customizable workflows.
Is it a sample coming in just today, or is it an orphan collection that we're
receiving? So how are we going to process those?
Using the workbench or just entering a sample as it is.
So unlocking biobank potential, standardized digitization, and
Specify platform integration in South Africa.
We've got these input from biodiversity biobanks.
It's an integrated process. Specify is the
advanced data management platform that a lot of these biodiversity biobanks are
now using. And in the South African context, it's national
priorities, so your data accessibility, your
regulatory
considerations, and then also the global collaboration.
So you want to make this data available as well.
And then also the broader impacts and research that we are
contributing to.
I have a wonderful team back home,
that hopefully one day will be able to join a tad with
conference. But until then, thank you very much for the opportunity to
present.
Thank you.
We have time for a few questions if anybody has any questions.
Kevin?
Excuse me. It's not really a question.
I just wanted you to maybe talk a little bit more about your interaction with
the researchers who are coming in using the material, how
that part of the workflow, you could say, looks when it comes to
taking a request from people to use the material, and how that's
processed and possibly how that's actually stored or reflected in the system.
How is it stored in the system?
Yes. Results from results or just the idea that analysis have been made on
particular material.
So we battle, I'm sure a lot of people dealing with collections, allowing
access to samples. You battle with researchers to get the
publications, any of the data back.
There are time to time that you get a really awesome researcher, and
you get all of that information back.
Publications that relate to samples that we have given out,
we always store that information,
on the actual little preparation thing.
So we customize it. We gave a data sheet years ago and customized
the preparation table,
that it's been used or we've minused 0.2
microliters.
All of the attachments, the publications, the
sequences as well. We used to capture forward and reverse.
We've got a main collection, then we've got another collection for
all of the genetic information.
We, part of, well, a bigger foundational
biodiversity science, so there's also zoological research there that makes
use of a lot of the samples. So they also provide us with all of the information.
When it goes onto BOLD or GenBank, we get the little identifiers.
All of that goes into Specify as well.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Kim. Yeah. Thank you very much, Kim.
We appreciate it.
So next up is Niels Kluyzinga, but wait, before you do that,
you're all in a picture. Hold on.
Smile.
Okay, thank you.
Along with that, at the end of this, if the speakers could stay for just a few
minutes, we need a picture of the speakers. I would appreciate that.
Okay.
Good morning.
First I would like to acknowledge the traditional owners of the
land I live and work on. So the Wurundjeri and Boonwurrung
people of the Kulin nation. I'd like to pay my respect to the elders
past and present,
and I'd like to extend this to any traditional owners that might be with us
today.
We have been using Specify for a while, over 16 years
now.
We actually started with
Specify 6.0.1,
and we actually made a bit of a leap of faith with Specify
because we had already committed to Specify, before
Specify 6 was even there.
So I don't have a
nice migration story or what we all do with Specify
because I've forgotten most of it.
But I will be telling a bit about how we
integrate Specify in our broader
science structure
and,
yeah, how data standards are part of that, of
everything. So,
this is our broader-- I can just look here.
This is our broader science
structure. So let's start with the collections hub,
I call it collections hub, which is basically Specify.
We've got a media hub,
which is our digital asset management system, which is Canto
at the moment.
We've got VicFlora. That's our flora
hub. VicFlora is actually three different floras, or two different floras at the
moment. It's the flora of Victoria and the horticultural flora
of Southeastern Australia. And,
we hope to get a
fungi--
I'm not allowed to call it flora, I have to call it funga,
as well. And,
yeah, then we've got a documentation hub, which is
where
all our documentation of all these systems is sitting.
We've got a traits hub, which is a very grandiose name for
a handful of Lucid keys
we've got, but I hope to make something,
turn it into an actual
traits database so it can be properly integrated, because with Lucid keys, you
can't really do anything.
And then we've got Keybase
and the Keys Hub. And Keybase is an application that I made 14 years
ago,
but it's still being used by a lot of people, so I had to
upgrade it
last year. So,
that's out there. That's an application for
managing dichotomous or pathway keys, which in principle everybody
can use, but it was actually the first
version of VicFlora, or the first part of VicFlora that we did.
And then that small thing that lives in
the cloud, which is the
Atlas of Living Australia and
the Australasian Virtual Herbarium, which is part of it.
It's actually the most important thing,
for Australian herbaria,
AVH is
very important because
that's where we put
all the metadata for our collections in and how we share
all the data, make it available to the public, and, yeah, that makes the data
relevant.
And, yeah, that has a lot of effect
on
Specify as well. So we don't use Specify for any dissemination
because it goes
all through AVH.
AVH is part of the ALA Biocase.
So for this point, ALA and AVH is the same thing.
And,
yeah, so
we use Specify only
for
collection management, or for managing our collections and managing the
metadata. And
actually one of the reasons, the main drivers be-
For adopting Specify.
Oh, for EMu things. Yes, EMu comes from Melbourne.
Was that we
wanted to deliver high-quality data for
AVH, so that's why we chose Specify.
So even if we only use it for
Specify, it
doesn't do everything
that we need for
collection management or not in the way we want.
We have to realize here that
Specify 16 years ago is not the same
as Specify now.
So there was quite a lot that we had to develop around Specify,
and a lot of that we probably
might be able to put in Specify now.
But
some of it we do, and other things
we don't. And one of the things, so we have this Bystander app, which
basically connects to the database.
We've had it all the time, and
we made it initially for the labels and
reports. So we use all that
in a Bystander app,
because
we needed to have those, and I couldn't work out how
Jasper Reports worked.
So by now,
we have moved everything back into
Jasper Reports.
But some of our labels and reports,
we'll still have to
do outside Specify. And one of those is our sticky labels.
So we've got them in Specify now, but
they print on sheets of 30,
and
if you do it from within Specify, it
always starts with the first label.
So if you need six labels, then you lose
the other 24
labels. Oh, wow.
So
we actually ordered seven label printers, and it turns out
that PDF is really
low quality. So we're going to make ZPL labels, so it has to sit outside
Specify. The other thing is the duplicate labels,
because we
need multiple labels for the same
catalog number, which Specify can't do anything.
And
all the transaction paperwork, I haven't actually moved it back
yet, so I'm not sure if we're going to do it immediately.
The other thing is loan return,
especially
partially
returned loans.
So herbarium loans can be very big and be thousands of specimens.
If we return 300, it's quite difficult
to do within Specify. So I have an old system.
The other thing is
event system.
For some things we do, we need to know
what
happens in a database.
So that's in a separate system. The other thing is a
taxonomy sync. We actually use the Specify taxon tree
as
the taxonomic backbone for a lot of
other systems.
And we've got a GraphQL API, which I've actually had longer than
Specify
has had an API.
So I've never used a Specify API. And so for now,
at the moment, we don't
need a separate database.
But we are going to
move some other data sets from our living collection
database into
Specify. And one of them is
Victorian Conservation Seed Bank.
Samples are already in Specify, but I don't know what to do with the
germination
test. I can't really shoehorn that in Specify, so I'm going to have a separate
database for that. And the other thing is the Orchid Conservation
Database. They have
cultures of mycorrhizal fungi and a lot of other data, and I don't even know
what that looks like yet.
So we've got an image portal we're developing at the moment.
That's actually good, mostly for our herbarium imaging
program. So it's
IIIF
compliant, so the image API is already there.
And
so you specify
to populate the presentation API.
And that's what the GraphQL API is for.
Okay.
The data delivery is via the
IPT.
So we deliver to the Atlas of Living Australia, and then the Atlas of
Living Australia
delivers to
GBIF. So Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian GBIF node.
And so now going a bit towards the standard.
So
this is the
Darwin Core
conceptual model.
I come from ABCD too
Background. So actually,
moving to Darwin Core Tech was quite a step back.
In my mind, we had to do that because that's the only thing that they labeled
accept.
And
now being able to
have a more structured data model will be
really good and have
great
opportunity for AVI,
really.
And then as last, I
can't have a talk by me without talking about taxon concepts.
So as I said,
we use a taxon tree as the backbone for all our other
applications,
especially Image Portal and Living Collections Database.
And,
so
we need to be able to put taxon concepts
into there. So
Robin talked about, not so much taxon concept, but the identifiers
for
all the taxon identifiers.
So I've been able to put a lot of taxon concepts in
Specify using taxon
citations, but we need to be able to
do it in a way that we can actually link identifications to
taxon concepts. So,
I would like to discuss that with Specify later.
That's it. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Niels.
You're welcome.
We don't have time for questions, but Niels will be around if you want
to ask any questions.
Next up is Marion Duprette.
I can't do that.
From the Museum of Natural History, Berlin.
So,
okay.
Hello, everyone.
So I'm Marion Duprette. I would like to invite you on a journey through the museum
collection, exploring their complex and fascinating history,
the challenge of managing their associated data, and how
Specify images are the perfect tool for addressing these challenges.
The Museum für Naturkunde Berlin is one of the world's largest natural history
museum, with 30 million items.
Its collection includes specimen from recent geological
collection, paleontological collection, as well as
mineralogical collection, and a sound library.
These 30 collection and sub-collection are managed by a team of
20 scientific aides, 21 collection manager, and around
20 support staff, including volunteers, student assistant, and youth
services participants.
The Museum für Naturkunde Berlin has a unique history that make managing its
collection particularly complex.
Founded in 1810, the museum welcome its first collection,
and in 1889, the current building was constructed out
there.
In a context of a strong colonialism, the German Thünen-Gohr Expedition in German
East Africa brought back 250 ton of fossil to the museum,
and other expedition to Africa, Oceania, and Asia also enriched
the collection, particularly with bird and mammal specimen.
World War I had little direct impact on the collection, but this period marked the
beginning of a long international isolation.
In 1937, 20 years after the first fossil discovery, the
giraffe skeleton was assembled, contributing to the museum
worldwide renown.
World War II had a significant impact on the collection.
From 1943 onward, intense and frequent bombing led curators
and staff to pack up the most irreplaceable specimen and evacuate
them to an underground limestone mine in
Rüdersdorf.
On February the 3rd, 1945, the museum was bombed,
completely destroying the east wing and many specimens.
While 75% of the collection was saved, it remained
difficult to determine exactly what was lost, but digitizing
effort are now helping us to clarify this.
And at the end of the war, Soviet forces confiscated a large number of
specimen as wartime reparation and transported
them to the Soviet Union.
It was not until 1943, as part of a diplomatic gesture aimed
at strengthening ties with East Germany,
that the Soviet Union agreed to set up a large-scale
repatriation program, enable the collection to be returned to the
place of origin.
During the Cold War, the Berlin Wall geographically and ideologically
isolated institution, and exchange with Western scientists became
extremely difficult. But after the fall of Berlin Wall, the situation
stabilized.
In 2010, 65 later after the bombing, the east wing
was reconstructed and now houses
the west collection.
The same year, the decision was made to use Specify for at least part of the
collection, with the mammals leading the way.
In 2019, the global pandemic and successive lockdown isolated
collection staff, forces them to work alone.
This reinforced the use of personal tools like Excel or local database,
making the subsequent adoption of Specify more challenging.
In
October 2023, a cyber attack
brought the MfN at a standstill for nearly a year.
And paradoxically, this event ended the debates and confirmed the decision to
adopt Specify as the museum's sole CMS.
Finally, in 2024, to meet these new needs, our small team
was formed. I oversee biological data management,
while my colleague Franziska Bottger
serves as the internal and external communication and knowledge
coordinator.
Today, we face great challenges in digitizing our collection because
behind every specimen lies centuries of history, expertise, and passion.
To share the metadata linked into this object, we must account for all
existing standards and principles rule established as early as
1867 and refined to this day to ensure
equitable and optimal access for everyone.
We must also preserve the expertise and deep knowledge of those currently
working on the collection, as well as the legacy of the
professionals who have dedicated over 20 years to preserving it.
How do we standardize data that carries centuries of historical events, diverse
perspectives, and unique stories?
Moreover, it is impossible to predict
upfront which information will be
valuable to which user group. Our audiences are incredibly
diverse. Scientists, historians, museum curators, schools,
artists, and local communities seeking to reconnect with objects from their
countries of origin.
This data must be standardized, but we must also consider that vastly different
objects coexist within our collection.
For example, a series of common beetles will not have the same metadata
as a complete skeleton of Dysalotosaurus or as Jacob, the
Alexander von Humboldt beloved pet.
Specify is invaluable for two key reasons.
First, its interface, it's easy for end users to adopt,
and second, and it is what truly sets Specify apart, it is
flexibility. Unlike rigid relational databases, Specify
custom table fields and interconnecting links adapt to any
collection.
This flexibility has allowed us to consolidate all 30 collections
into a single Specify instance, meaning just one database.
It facilitates standardization and homogenization of data while
preserving the unique characteristics of each collection.
For collection staff, this unified structure fosters better understanding
and collaboration. By grouping similar concepts,
they recognize the value of standardization and see that while each
collection has its unique aspects, they all share
commonalities.
This encourages a more cohesive and inclusive approach.
For data managers, this means we can generate annual and monthly
reports, statistics, and graphs for all collections within a single query.
This saves time and effort while enabling efficient monitoring of
processes across all collections at a glance.
For example, here we have the number of entries created per year since the
database was established.
And here we have the percentage of NOID assigned to objects per collection,
allowing us to easily track the progress of this long and laborious process.
For developers, this centralized structure simplifies data sharing on
the data portal, making it easier to integrate and
display information consistently.
Specify's flexibility has been instrumental in the decolonization process at MfN,
allowing us to explore new concepts and immediately put them into practice.
To achieve this, I use a one-to-many table linking collection objects to any number
of historical events. These events can range from
before to after acquisition, from major historical
occurrences like those tied to war or colonialism,
to recent
localized events that we still want to document.
I also set up a prototype collection called Historical
Context. In this exploratory collection, we can link
transcription data, keywords, and taxa to a letter written in
1909 in Tanga, Uro. But most importantly,
it is possible to connect it to the various objects it mentions.
And of course, from any biological object, we can track back to all
archives that reference it.
Even though Specify offers many possibilities, gaps remain.
For example, in managing and standardizing historical events.
The main challenge is that historical events were not designed for a dedicated
table. I had to repurpose another table.
This solution isn't perfect for several reasons, but it's a work in
progress, and I'm confident this gap will improve
over time through collaboration with the Specify communities.
Another gap in Specify is managing localities and geography.
After months of working across collections, I realized
how difficult it is to consistently standardize
geographical data.
Political boundaries, Specify default, have advantages.
ISO 3166 codes ensure global standardization and
interoperability, help document geographic origin
even for historical localities like German colonies, and support
multi-language display.
However, political boundaries may not correspond to biological
collection needs.
There are anomalies in geographical locations,
ambiguous territories, and inconsistent
geographic scales,
which make global standardization difficult.
A major limitation is that administrative boundaries rarely
align with ecological or biogeographic zones.
And a species distribution can span multiple regions,
and these boundaries struggle to capture natural features like ocean-montane
ranges or ecological regions, all vital for
biodiversity research. Assigning a locality solely to
an administrative entity risks losing critical ecological context,
especially for specimens from remote or border areas.
Ecological dimensions are
as essential as administrative ones, capturing both
the geographical and political history of specimens and their
natural distribution. However, it is difficult to have both
representations simultaneously, making cross-collection
searches harder, especially when specimens have both administrative
and marine data.
One possible solution is to add multiple fields to the locality detail table
for different geographic units, like maritime areas,
natural features, or water bodies.
However, this has significantly increased the complexity and the risk of
error in the locality table.
Another idea would be to add a second geographic tree based on natural units.
Existing standards like geoname or MarineRegion could be used,
though
none are universally adopted. But all this still
needs to be tested.
In conclusion, while there is strong desire to share data, the
reality is that it comes with its own set of challenges.
These collections are not static. They are living, evolving entities.
Every day, loan requests are made for new research, and every day new
data must be integrated into what already exists.
This constant evolution adds layers of complexity to our work.
The concepts preserve, standardize, and reconstruct can seem antagonistic,
because how can we standardize something that is still in the process of being
constructed? This is why standardization must remain a response to a
need rather than a solution to a problem.
Even if the data appear chaotic, it reflects a complex history.
Despite these challenges, Specify helps us preserve the richness of
our collections, standardize data for consistency, and
reconstruct the history of specimens and the
knowledge they hold.
Of course, challenges remain, whether they are geographical, historical, or
ethical, but this work is in progress, and researchers, curators, data
managers, and institutions around the world play a crucial
role in overcoming these obstacles.
So the journey continues,
and I'm glad that we can do that together. Thank you.
We might have time for one question.
Oh, we have another.
I think a lot of institutions are a lot more integrated.
I'm with Agriculture Canada, and we have a real gap between
management of our collection and research use of the collection.
And so we're starting small, trying to really,
really stick to collection management requirements.
But when I look at your use of the geography tree, I'm like, "Oh, yeah, I've
spent so much time to standardize, trying to understand
sub-country divisions to try and fill in the tree." But I wonder,
where do you draw that line between serving that
research use case versus the
data management use case of collection material
versus how? Is it your job to
enable that kind of geographical or climate or environment
adaptation for research use?
Yeah. So in my slides, it's really complex, but we are
still on the basis levels. So for now, we
have some trouble to--
for example, the marine collection, they basically
used
ocean and sea
units. And the thing is that if I try to integrate that into the
geography tree that already exists,
we can't do the same research. We lose some
information. So-
So it's how you can use them
is the data they provided to you to integrate-
Yeah. And I try to make everyone happy. And it's not easy.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Okay. Next up is Specify's own Grant Fitzsimmons.
There you go.
All right. Good to know my mic is working.
Well, hello, everybody. Thank you so much for joining today.
Over the last several talks, you've heard a lot about Specify supporting different
collections in different ways, and there's lots of different workflows and
customizability allowed.
But one of the things I'd like to think about during my session is a little bit
about how do we preserve that local flexibility while still making
Specify something that can share data in a way that other aggregators and
downstream destinations can reasonably ingest.
So this slide is a little overwhelming.
A lot of text is how I describe it, but this really gives some context on
Specify as a community infrastructure project that is only
made possible thanks to the many different member institutions that support the
effort.
So we have member institutions in many countries around the world.
We are dependent only on member funding to be going.
We're a nonprofit, and we provide lots of different services.
So Specify as a service, sort of to Kevin's point, both
within the university that we're housed in back in the United States, as well
as to users around the globe in various regions around the world.
We've got, as you can see, millions of records on GBIF that are mobilized
from users of Specify and members of Specify, and we offer a
lot of really interesting services if you'd like to go through all the process of
hosting your data, managing your assets, getting outreach workshops, and
so forth.
But with all of that, the developments we do both to create the platform
that many are using to manage their collections, their data, as well
as the different services we offer, we want to be able to preserve this local
flexibility because I think it is one of the key differentiators between Specify
and other platforms that exist out there.
But I think TDWG is really all about coming up with shared standards that we
all can agree upon so that we don't have this massive gap between what we
do at our various institutions and what people are doing when they're sharing data
in public portals. So every collection shouldn't have to work the same way
day to day, but we need that local flexibility.
Now, this would be repeating what many of you have heard, but for those who haven't
heard about Specify, if you're tuning in now to the live stream or
you're new to this room,
as you can see, it's this collections management system.
It's the system that you can use to enter data into a database that contains
all of your specimen information, manage transactions, and other sorts of
operations with material coming in and out.
You can do batch editing, data quality improvements, bulk
importing, querying, sharing, and so forth.
But we've been working on some powerful tools to make it easier for you to share
your specific customizations in Specify, both within your
single institution, within your building, with your colleagues, but also to be able
to share it publicly with the community.
This means you can export your customizations in one package and share those.
So say, for example, somebody wants to follow the Royal Botanic Gardens Edinburgh,
or they'd like to follow Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria, these things could be
packaged nicely as an export, shared with other people in the community, and you
can share these standards between different Specify users, different databases,
or even multiple disciplines in the same database.
So we're really excited about being able to offer some more standard data
practices,
made possible by sharing schema configurations.
We're also updating the web portal.
This is the portal that you can create a detached copy of the data in your Specify
instance, put it online, and not have that be touching your live
collections information, which is really nice.
This lets you view images, view specimen information, and this is completely
separate from your live database, meaning you can process out and hide all of the
sensitive localities, hide red list species information, those sorts of things,
and still make that data visible, searchable, and
completely separate with your own brand and identity at the top for your
collection.
This is available to all members of the Specify Collections Consortium for free,
and this was contributed in large part by the Florida Museum of Natural History.
So there's some wonderful developers there that, as part of being a consortium
member, felt it was necessary to share this with the wider audience of all.
So we're really lucky to have such a great community of people making it possible
to do what we do.
But that web portal lets you have any fields and visible things that you'd like in
it. You can put anything matching your collection's practices and standards.
But when you are managing things locally, we do need to map that
local configuration to an actual standard that exists on portals and
other data destinations like GBIF.
So what we need to do that is a tool to map Specify to Darwin
Core.
As you can imagine, this took many nights, many days, many weeks
to make sure that we get these right because of just the
pure number of collections and institutions and universities around the world that
are using Specify to manage their collections.
So we've done our best to create a very comprehensive mapping between all of the
fields in Specify that have a matching term in Darwin Core,
and that includes many of the extensions that GBIF supports as well.
But what we want to do is give everybody a big head start so that they can take the
data that's in their customized database and immediately share it with data
aggregators.
So we've built a new mapping tool that is something that is intuitive enough
for a collection manager to be able to see and understand, which
previously tools have been quite difficult to use, if anyone has tested those
mapping interfaces. We wanted to make sure that our tool also supported
not only just Occurrence Core with Darwin Core, but also Event and Taxon
Cores, because we know people are managing these to various levels within their
databases.
We also wanted to make sure we supported every GBIF-registered extension out of the
box, as well as extensions that have not yet been registered, so custom extensions
for other platforms are also supported.
And when I say custom, because you all understand Specify is deeply
customizable, we also made sure that you can have custom cores, terms,
extensions beyond just the ones that I'll be showing in this presentation.
So to give you an idea of what a mapping interface looks like,
anyone who's used the Specify Query Builder is already familiar with this sort of
interface, where you essentially get to pick out of a list all of the terms
or fields that exist within your database.
And on the left-hand side here, you can actually map those to terms.
So at the very top, you have tabs to go between your main
mapping as well as all of your extensions.
You get the full query builder, so all of the filters you do to be able to exclude
certain records based on your criteria or to return certain columns of
data are still available there.
You have the term selector on the left,
and very importantly, if you want to see what the term is defined as in
Darwin Core, you can see that directly from the application itself.
You're not jumping out and back into Specify. You're not searching for terms.
Very fortunately, you can click on the I or hover over it to
see a full textual description of what that term is in that
publishing vocabulary.
When you click the terms list, you can see that they're actually grouped By
category, so you have all of your organism fields together, material entity
fields together, and this sort of thing makes it really trivial to figure out
which concepts exist together when you're mapping your Specify database
to Darwin Core.
And you can see at the very top, that's where you can set any custom term you'd
like. So if there's an IRI for a term that exists in a newer version of Darwin
Core that isn't present in the version of Specify you're using, you don't become
dependent on waiting for an update from the Specify consortium to get those
terms available to you.
When you click on that I, you'll actually see a pop-up that shows you the term,
the vocabulary, the IRI, and description, and that makes it easy for you
to then see examples of how that term is used, what it should look like when
publishing. It's a very nice visual and link-out to be able to
see and use.
The mapping interface is intimidating enough because now you have to think, what
should I map to? What should I use? Which terms do I need to return?
What does GBIF expect and require when I'm publishing data? Those sorts of things.
But fortunately,
you can use an existing query that you've built in your database to be the starting
point. So many people are using Specify queries, exporting them, putting them
into the GBIF IPT, and going through those steps.
But what you can do instead is just start with your query,
and
sort of magically--
If you don't, of course, you have templates which we're providing for both the
primary Darwin Core and all of those extensions, so very nice that you don't have
to go through all that work yourself.
But if you don't currently have those mapped-out terms in
Darwin Core, it actually has a backbone that does that mapping for you,
and I'll talk more about that in a moment.
But as you can see, there's a lot of GBIF registered extensions.
They're all available to add, so when you've done your main mapping, you can click
on a plus and then add every registered
extension that GBIF supports.
So imagine things like your identification history, the GGBN
preparation material sample, and so forth extensions.
You have, of course, audio-visual core and all of the other
primary core extensions.
And this is something that also means you're able to see the descriptions,
names, IRIs, and so forth of all of those terms as well.
So those are all pulled and shown within Specify, too.
But to actually make this a usable system where you have these things connected
together, we're actually connecting the schema configuration, the database schema,
and so forth, with these external terms, so that you can see directly
when you're setting up the database and when you're customizing Specify which
terms exist in external vocabularies and what they are defined as, and
you can see that alongside your internal fields in Specify so you know what the
intention is of that field when setting up the database.
So
I'll go back just a couple slides to show--
Sorry, a few more.
Boop. Okay, here we go.
So when you add any field to your query, the first thing
that will happen is a suggested term will be mapped automatically.
So if you add the catalog number field, it will be mapped one-to-one to catalog
number within Darwin Core. If you add the preparations together,
it'll put that into preparations.
But if you want more depth to that, you can add extensions with material
entity and others, and it will build out that query to be more in-depth, and all of
that data will be preserved. If you choose audiovisual core as an
extension that you're adding to Specify's export mapping,
automatically all of the terms like creator, credit, license, and so forth will be
mapped whenever that is added. So you don't have to go through the laborious
process of deciding what should be included and what shouldn't be.
In another very powerful way, it does tell you if there are missing
terms that are required for publishing for a particular extension on GBIF,
that it makes sure to enforce the minimum field mapping that GBIF expects,
and it gives suggestions to make sure that you're on the right track as you're
working on that mapping.
So I don't know if you can tell, but I'm really excited.
Okay.
All right, so what's next after all the work that I've talked about?
Well, I'd love to demo it for anyone who'd like to see it, so just come grab me
anytime you'd like during the week, and I can show you what that looks like in
practice. But this is all going to be out at least by the
first quarter of next year, though I'm optimistic it will be sooner than that.
We're also a participant in the Darwin Core DAC grant project,
so we'll be working together this weekend a little bit on how we move forward
there. This is not just a Specify effort.
This is a multi-CMS effort, so we'll be working together to figure
out how Darwin Core data package is going to fit into all of this because we' re
really excited about what the future of data publishing looks like.
We'll also be participating, most likely, in a hackathon
in Leiden next year. And everything that we've done, all of the work we've put
together, it's been supported by members and with this grant as well.
That means it's all going to be public on GitHub, so it's shared with all of you.
So
I'm almost out of time, so I'll just say that this isn't possible just thanks to
any one of us, but the entire team makes this happen.
On the left, you can see our full-time and part-time team, and on the right, we're
supported by wonderful undergraduate students at the University of Kansas.
So thank you so much, everybody.
Let me know if you have any questions. I'll be around until the end of the week.
It looks like we don't have any time for questions, but
like I said, Grant will be around for the rest of the week, so will Amy and I.
So
we'll be here to answer questions.
Next up is Dan Baker from CSIRO.
He is online, so he'll be able to answer
questions. But before we start his-
Hello. My name is Dan Baker, and I'm a data manager working with the
Australian National Research Collections at CSIRO.
My talk today is titled "From Data Entry to Distribution:
Streamlining Biodiversity Workflows with Specify at CSIRO."
I would like to begin by acknowledging the Ngunnawal people as the traditional
owners of the land that I'm recording from today, and pay my respects to
the elders, past and present.
This talk will cover a broad range of methods the data management team has
implemented to support biodiversity data standards that are all connected.
But for the purpose of a linear tool, I'll start with our migration efforts
into Specify and then discuss some of the systems we have in place for data
entry, data exporting, and data editing.
I'll cover how we promote the use of our standards to a large user base
and finish with some comparisons between the collections, highlighting the
similarities and differences in processes and outputs, even with the same
consistent ideologies applied to all the data.
Between mid-2021 to the end of 2025, the
National Research Collections of Australia have migrated five of the
six collections into Specify. This effort was part
of a dedicated project that involved collaboration from the data management
team,
our IT services, project managers,
BAs, testers, and subject matter experts from each
collection that were seconded for at least 50% of their time.
Each collection took 12 to 18 months to migrate with a staggered
go-live approach.
The goal was to standardize the way collection data was managed across NRCA,
increase the system reliability and security, and improve
access and discoverability of the collection's data.
As a bonus, a massive data cleanup process also took place
so that we could map fields into Specify correctly in a way that made sense for the
workflows for the curation staff.
But also so that we could have as many curated picklists as
possible and required fields.
Darwin Core terms were used as a framework, which meant some legacy data had to
be split across separate fields or amalgamated together.
We loaded the data into transformation pipelines, checked for errors and data loss,
noted additional cleanup processes, verified workflows in the
Specify front end, and then performed a rinse and repeat until everything was
verified and signed off by the teams.
We now have over two million registered specimens across the five instances
with over 150 registered users.
Once we had gone live with the collections in Specify, the job then switched to
maintaining those biodiversity data standards for new specimens being registered,
and this can be tackled at various levels.
At the individual field level, we have to make sure the data is relevant and clean.
So well-defined fields in Specify with useful descriptions and wherever
possible, a controlled vocabulary picklist help immensely, which is
something the data management team can control and maintain.
Here we have an example from one of our workbench templates, where we've employed
conditional formatting to highlight fields that have formatting restrictions, as
well as fields that are required or fields that should be
conditionally populated, which is something that the Specify workbench validation
does not cover.
We also have copies of our controlled vocabulary picklists to make sure certain
fields contain relevant data.
The next level up is the collection-specific formatting options that we have worked
with the curation staff on. For this example here, we have the collector name
formats. Each collection has a different way they want the data presented on
specimen labels, but we need to keep certain consistent data standards
across NRCA. Our solution has been to encourage the full use of the
agent table to record as much detail as possible in the separate
first name, last name, initial fields, and then create different
aggregated views that reformat their needs.
We have a VBA script within the Excel template so they can split a list of
collector names into the relevant agent fields.
The last level is the holistic full data approach.
From the data management side, we want the complete specimen metadata picture,
which means putting in checks to make sure things like the country has been
selected for a collecting event, or that there are geo-coordinate values
entered alongside uncertainty and precision fields.
A minimum data set ensures that the information is as useful as possible,
knowing how especially time-consuming it can be to fill in the blanks at a later
date, mostly from finding the physical specimen again.
For this, we have a data check tab in our upload template to catch these more
holistic issues.
All of these additional steps work in conjunction with Specify's excellent
workbench data upload feature so that users are able to
register thousands of new specimens in one go.
The ability to share a data mapping file with the curation teams
alongside our template files guarantees data
consistency on top of the checks and balances that Specify
to make sure things like field formatting and required fields are present.
All of this work to maintain clean and standardized data is important
because Specify is the source of truth for the specimen metadata at
CSIRO, and it is not a closed system where that is only
acceptable to the collection staff.
We use the reporting features in Specify and the statistics pages to
curate high-level summaries to management teams.
We use the interaction tables to process specimens being loaned in and out of the
system and track
exchange events as well. The general NRCA activities
include...
Another fantastic new feature Specify has implemented
is the batch edit option, where users can create a query to pull
back multiple data sets with bulk editing processes.
This has been a great tool for us to help the data cleaning
efforts that didn't
make it in before our go-live deadlines, but also allows
us to update the collections as we go.
We've added common names
to all the tax unknowns in
our
fish
collection and also updated their storage details, which is something that
can need to happen on an annual review of the physical specimens.
To find some of these issues that need the attention of the batch edit tool, we
have created more complex data checks via the SQL-based Power
Query editor in Excel to retrieve live data from the database,
with the subject matter experts generally responsible for checking and actioning.
This further helps adhere to biodiversity standards and helps tackle the fact that
even if you have checks in place to ensure new data is uploaded as cleanly as
possible, there is always legacy data to be reviewed or issues that
arise from adding and editing existing specimen data.
A key component in maintaining these biodiversity data standards in NERRCA is to
spread awareness to everyone using the system on the importance of adhering to
best practices and not have it be a topic that only the data managers care about.
With over 150 users interacting with Specify to varying degrees,
we have to make sure we provide enough training to be able to maintain fair
practices across the board.
Whilst much of the training can be repeated for each collection, there are specific
workflows and data considerations that mean we run special sessions for those
teams. For example, the process of registering and connecting tissue
specimens in the wildlife and fish collections, or the placeholder
registration of a specimen in the insect collection so that labels can be
generated as soon as possible.
Everything we do is recorded and made available, and for each go-live event,
we held daily drop-in sessions for the first few weeks to get users
familiar with Specify and everything it can do.
We also remain available for ongoing support, having a central email address
within CSIRO that goes to the team and setting up Microsoft Teams channels
for users to chat to us and ask questions, but also importantly, to
learn from each other as well. We have an internal landing page where you can
access our various instances, and for each collection, we have created standard
queries and a library of workbench templates and mapping files.
Whilst the majority of users
are guests with read-only access to the data, a key benefit of Specify is
the ability to define multiple roles for different permission sets.
And our standardized roles across all collections allow us to increment the power
that each user has, from data entry for some of the digitization team,
all the way up to full edit and limited delete options for the curation
managers.
However, with all this standardization in place, every collection is different, and
a nice example of this are the labels and reports we are asked to set up
in Specify. Whilst the underlying data structure is relatively
consistent across the five instances, we have a wide range of examples
and varying outputs that we build using standardized templates
to adjust as needed.
In the 28 months since the first two collections went live in Specify, we've had a
tremendous uptake in the usage, with over 50,000 new specimens registered in
that time and over 8,000 new taxa recorded.
The average user has made around 25 actions a day, assuming
CSIRO made them work 365 days a year.
With future work on bulk image processing using the AI OCR
tools mentioned, this number will continue to increase.
So what do we want in the future to help Australia's national collections promote
and maintain biodiversity data standards using Specify?
From our experience, it would be helpful to have conditional pick list handling,
meaning that the options available for users to choose from are dependent on other
data fields.
The recent addition for allowing for multiple table aggregation outputs is great,
but sometimes we need to be able to export two different views of a data table in
one file.
An internal tool that scores your specimens on data completeness would be
helpful to make sure all subcomponents of a specimen are recorded.
And finally, many of the collections want a formal way to create a two-way
connection between preparations belonging to separate collection
objects. For example, in the herbarium, we have sheet preparations
against one specimen that were cultivated from the living preparation of another.
Thank you very much for listening to this talk, and thank you to Grant and Teresa
at Specify for their helpful discussions and collaborations.
Okay, Dan is online. We're running over time, but does anyone have any
questions for him really quickly?
No. Okay. That helps with the time. But I do want to put in a plug one more time.
Get your bandana. I want to point out it has the same slogan we've had for
20 years, "Post mortem we sort 'em," right on the bandana,
and we have stickers, lots of stickers you can take home, give to your kids, give
to your team.
Please take them.
So, the final presentation is from Samantha Orellana
from the University of Kansas Entomology.
My name is Samantha Orellana, and I am currently a
postdoc at the Entomology Division of the University of Kansas.
Unfortunately, I couldn't join you in Oslo, but in
name of my colleagues, I will be sharing some updates about
our data mobilization processes using Specify
here at KU.
To give you some context, the KU Entomology Collection
belongs to the University of Kansas Biodiversity Institute and
Natural History Museum.
It's located in Lawrence, Kansas.
As you may know, here is also where the Specify
team and most of the KU collections are located.
However, the Entomology Division is now
in the KU Public Safety building, just a few minutes
away from the main museum.
The KU Entomology Collection, also known as the Snow
Entomological Museum Collection, houses over five
million specimens and hosts a vibrant community of
researchers and students.
In the collection, we use Specify as the main content
management system, and we have digitized about
1.4 million specimens in
approximately two decades.
This represents roughly the 28% of our
holdings. However, this collection
still has the largest insect specimen data set in the
US.
Until recently, only local versions of
Specify were available in the collection, mostly
used by the collection managers and eventual curatorial
assistants.
The last local version used in the collection was
Specify 6,
which was programmed to be decommissioned earlier this year.
So to stay ahead of the change, in 2025,
we plan to migrate to the new Specify 7
online version.
So after updating the mapping for some of the
fields, including the multimedia
fields, the migration process was pretty
straightforward, thanks to the KU Bioinformatics and the
Specify teams.
Now we have access to this online version of our
Specify instance.
Contrary to the local version, the online version allows
access to more users, even outside the collection building,
which has increased the number of students and
researchers using this platform.
Here, we can see the collection object form for data
entry,
which now allows to add new data into
different tables without leaving the form.
For example, if you need to add a new collecting event, you can
do it from the data entry form.
If you need to perform other tasks, for example, a
query, you can also open Specify in multiple
tabs on your browser.
Other advantage compared to Specify 6 is
that the taxon tree can be accessed by multiple users at
the same time.
So instead of finding the tree locked because someone else is
using it, everyone with access can add
and edit names as needed.
Media management was also improved, as we can now add
multiple files directly in the data entry form, where
we can also add controlled vocabulary in the multimedia
metadata fields, including information about
the creator,
which allows us to credit the authors of the
images.
This information can also be edited directly in the attachments
display, which improves the ability to review and improve
data quality.
Both data and images are mapped and packed
into a Darwin Core archive, which is accessible
through an RSS feed with nightly updates.
Through this RSS feed, the data and images are easily
shared and made publicly available in multiple platforms,
such as the Specify online portal.
You can use the QR code to access the portal, which
has all the data and images available from
our Specify instance.
Thanks to the new Specify 7 installation and the
availability of the RSS feed being
constantly updated, we can also update
our GBIF data set constantly, making the
data readily available for research.
Additionally, we can now mobilize the KU Entomology
Collection data directly from Specify to
multiple Symbiota portals, expanding the
information accessibility to different communities of
practice.
These communities include researchers and students
here at the University of Kansas, where we have interns,
undergrads, graduate students, and visitors that
now can not only digitize their specimens
on Specify, but they are also taking advantage of
these new workflows to mobilize the data and
generate additional resources in Symbiota for their
classes or research.
For example, here you can access an
interactive checklist built by one of our students
and also data
and images about type specimens deposited in the KU
collection.
The ability of mobilizing data
more easily using Specify 7 has also been
advantageous to promote international collaborations.
For example, this month, we are starting a new bid
project to mobilize biodiversity information from
Central American species to GBIF.
This
helps us
to share information by following proper biodiversity data
standards and improving the mobilization workflows.
With this, KU will be
able to easily contribute insect data and images from this
region
and increase availability of open biodiversity
information. At the same time, we will be
engaging a global community of biodiversity researchers.
So that's all the time that I have today.
Thank you so much for your attention and thanks to the
Specify team and to the organizers of this symposium for
the time. I'll be available for any questions you may have.
Thank you very much.
Okay. And we are right on time, but Samantha is online,
and she is awake at 3:30 in the morning.
She said everyone's presentations were so great she could stay awake easily.
But if anyone has any questions, she can answer them for you,
or you can email her. Samantha is always up for talking to people.
Sorry to volunteer you, Samantha, but she usually is.
Okay. If there are no questions, then we release you
to tea break. Again, stickers. I
know.
Stickers, bandanas, and could the speakers come up for a picture, please?
And please take the stickers and bandanas. I don't want to take them home.
Great.
Yeah.
She'll
hopefully show up.
Mm-hmm.
She'll hopefully show up.
Oh.
Quick access toolbar.
Okay.
I'm sorry.
Oh, that's too bad.
I know.
I
know.
Tanya?
Yeah, I can try to do a selfie. Yeah.
Shh. Don't tell-
Welcome. Okay, now the mic's hot.
Welcome to Session
25A,
titled "From Mobilizing Data to AI-Ready Knowledge
Infrastructure for Multimodal Biodiversity Data."
It's going to be a really full session.
We have a total of 11 presentations, six prior to
lunch and five more after lunch, and at the end,
we
will gather the speakers here and have a bit of a panel discussion to
wrap things up and
also open things up a little bit to questions from the audience.
So,
this all arose from
a
recently
funded project
funded by the National Science Foundation, and you'll hear a little
bit more about in one of the initial talks.
So I won't dive into that, but briefly,
we live in a world of
abundance in a way, in the sense that biodiversity data
is really plentiful. There's more online than ever before.
What's online is more varied than ever before, and it's also more multimodal,
larger scale than ever.
So these are all tremendously
valuable properties of the state in
which we're in for biodiversity data.
But the data, as I think many people,
and increasingly more are recognizing, biodiversity data often
is really not ready for AI. And so that
comes ... down to a number of things, including
the ones enumerated here. Knowledge remains buried,
data record documentation is inconsistent,
uneven
cross-platform interoperability, ontology integration are huge
issues. Still, data quality fitness for use are really
difficult to assess without
downloading data that used to be straightforward when the data wasn't really
very large, but it's very challenging when it's hundreds of
gigabytes. Provenance, uncertainty, data amendments,
the provenance chain is often broken,
meaning these things are not tracked.
Terms of use and the expectations from providers, how they
actually want to be credited, and what kind of amendments and
augmentations they're willing and able to receive or want to
receive
are usually unclear. And so
trustworthiness is also often an issue because it needs community
aligned standards and government.
So this is just a bit of a highlights of the issues
that have been surfaced in this
NSF-funded project that, as I said, we'll hear a little bit more and that actually
gave rise to
the session here. And so, as I said, we'll have six
presentations in the first half of the session before lunch.
I think I'm just going to keep this short here so we stay
on time.
You'll hear each of these talks in just about a moment as the session
unrolls, and then we'll have five more afterwards.
So hopefully everyone's here, is excited enough by
this first round of presentations to come back after lunch.
I see we have a pretty full room here, which is awesome.
And so, without
further ado,
I want to hand over
both the stage here and hopefully your attention to the first
presentation up.
So I think, Tanja, I want to welcome you over to the stage
here.
And
For my first ADWIG, you guys are making me work really hard
and impersonate a lot of people.
But I'm very happy to impersonate,
in this case,
mostly Eric Sokol, but also a large number of
people who
work through this FAIR for AI Bio project.
I'll tell you a little bit about the project itself, but I do want to acknowledge
Eric Sokol, Kristin Laney,
Elizabeth Campolongo, Matt Thompson, Jenna Klein,
Max Tergen,
Hilmar Lapp, Marty Downs, Greg Maurer, Sydney Record.
You'll see also that there is quite a collection, mostly US, because it's a
US-funded project, so we were required.
So to reiterate the slide that I think I'm showing
in every talk is that we have an
explosion of data
types, data providing devices, data sensors,
and data modalities, scales, resolutions,
and it's rapidly increasing
and changing all the time. As I
said, the most recent are GPS trackers you can put on butterflies
to track individual butterflies.
We can recognize individual monarch butterflies from the images that you can
take and track them through images.
You can
put chemical sensors around a plant to sense the phenology
changes. You can put super high resolution
insect camera traps
in different modalities to replace the traditional things like pitfall
traps, malaise traps, and also pointing to a plant.
So there is
under
soil, under water, so there's an explosion of sensors.
And
different holders of and aggregators of
data hold different data modalities also.
And different projects contribute to different
data platforms. And so the question is,
how do we integrate among these in a
decentralized way, where all of these data sources, data
modalities, data regions can talk to each other without
actually building one database to rule them all?
And we do need to do this because
there is no AI without data. Repeat after me.
There is no AI without data, and also these
biodiversity nature knows no borders,
but policies.
Great.
Hey, what did I say?
But policies do, and so,
policies and licensing and
technology unfortunately knows borders.
And so we
started with this
FAIR for AI
project. So the project was funded by the US
National Science Foundation in the
program called
Findable, Accessible, Interoperable and Reusable Open Science, FAIROS,
to build AI-ready data infrastructure for ecology and biodiversity.
I'm the PI on this project, but it's a fantastic team.
And the way we approached it is not to start top-down,
but to really bring
Across the board, international organizations, you'll recognize
some of the big names here, including
GBIF and Movebank, Smithsonian, NatureServe,
iNaturalist. So there's
big cross-border as well as very US-specific
institutions and organizations
in a series of workshops, starting first before we were
even funded to see what are the needs, what are the
use cases, why should we? Maybe we shouldn't even bother integrating data.
Maybe it is already AI-ready, right?
Maybe
we can do everything we want to do for the
use cases that are there. Clearly not.
So we started with the first workshop in August 2025, and then expanded it with a
series of
increasingly expanding workshops.
And by the way, I'll repeat it many times, if you want to join the effort,
we do have funding to bring you to the next workshop, which is going to be in
February
in 2027,
in the sunny California in February, so it's nice.
Come on over.
Talk to me.
So we started with what do we need?
What do we really, really need, including broader community of what do we
need?
And then at the
first International Conference for Conservation Technology Conference in
Peru and Lima,
we really started to bring in much, much broader
community. This is where the notion of data
sovereignty, data value round-tripping
really came to the fore, where we really realized that that
is the
primary use case. Okay? And so,
we started developing across these workshops the notion
both defining what is AI-ready, and
realizing that there is an intermediate state there, FAIR for AI.
Right? So just like FAIR, but machine
findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable, because AI-ready is very
application specific. And so if you are FAIR for AI, with minimal
human intervention, you can prepare then the
AI-ready data sets. And we
think about it in a way that is this question
data model, QDM,
framework,
and round-tripping across all of this.
No?
Okay. Across all of these...
So this is not really-- It doesn't want to do the laser,
and it blacks out.
So round-tripping a across all of this, so you start with a question, you
need data, you
can have a model to analyze that data, provide value, answer to the
research question, but it also should
provide value all the way
back.
So research questions can declare, and you can do this with
LLMs now, I need this kind of data, this kind of
models. Not specifically, but this kind of, this type of.
Models have now model context protocols and model cards that also say, "I
need this kind of data. I can answer these kinds of questions."
For data, though, we have a lot less.
We have some aspects of,
"I can work with these kinds of
models. I can answer these kinds of questions," but it's much less developed at
this point. And this is where we think the work needs to be done.
So I showed this in the keynote, this effort to
digitize the biological collections of National Ecological Observatory Network.
That produces a lot of data, additional metadata,
right? And so this is a real opportunity for us to figure out
how do we capture that metadata? How do we make this data
set both, what did it take to make it AI-ready, and what
did it take to capture the value of the process
so people do not have to redo it and start building on top of it,
right? And so out of it, we started developing, starting with a
ESIL, which is Ecological Synthesis Center in US,
a FAIR for AI checklist.
And by the way, this notion of data round-tripping is Rob Gralnick, right
there, first brought it up,
and started formalizing. Yeah, I'm going to blame you.
But started to develop this checklist, the categories.
How can we check whether
any given data set independently is AI-ready?
And so there are these four categories of structural, scientific provenance, and
governance, and we expanded it further into
96 categories, and it's still growing.
Very specific, right? And you can see, for example,
it captures things like provenance and structure and
traditional metadata of under what conditions was
it collected, but also
starting to capture
the context of the data structure itself, which are
relevant for the
AI processing, for example,
what kind of record it is.
And so then going from the AI checklist, how do we provide a
score and an informative score, constructive score to any
given data set, right? So we started
to build this into AI
machine-checkable
checklist,
right?
And so where we can report it side by side with
the
traditional FAIR, and built an agent, because 96 categories by
hand, that's not doable. So we both built an agent
with the community. So we built an agent, opened it up to community to
say, "Is this the right thing?" First, the checklist, "Is this the
right thing?" And you can still change it. You can still contribute.
You can still comment and work with us and with the community.
It's not us, us. It's the community.
And also whether the agent actually captures the
checklist intent
as it works. Right?
So
this is an example output of the checklist.
So it not only provides a score, it provides a recommendation of how to improve it
for that specific item and for that specific category.
And,
so it can also does the summary, strengths, and gaps.
So we can then start looking at scores across a
dataset
and
compare one dataset to another. And you can compare traditional FAIR
with AI FAIR.
So,
we ran it. It is sort of focused quite a bit on
NEON, but the reference datasets that
we have are all the NEON datasets on
GBIF, as well as NEON separately published data.
And so you can see the
NEON GBIF scores for regular FAIR versus...
And they generally track. The one example where
really, especially for AI,
most of the datasets, and we've done this also with
other US datasets. Most of the datasets are
really low on care score.
Right? And this is going back to the second keynote that opened up this
conference on Monday.
And it is starting to be
particularly important, I think, as we talk about sovereign data
supply chain, as we talk about putting all of this data now
into AI, which even further breaks the chain of provenance and
value.
Right?
So
you can run this, you can sort of compare, you can look at the score, you can argue
with the score, you can submit comments and we'll still change the score.
You can argue with us directly, come to the workshop,
because we definitely need your input.
What do you think is necessary for
FAIR for AI criteria? Do we capture everything?
Most importantly, really truly
define the bidirectionality of data, so that
because models are built on data aggregates,
on large data sources,
a lot of contributions from primary data collections go in
one direction. How do we enable value
bidirectionality, not only to the aggregators,
but all the way back?
Right? And how do we,
at the very least, the first step, how do we track
the provenance
and origin
from the primary data all the way to the models
that use them?
And how do we track the governance so
that in the words of the
keynote speaker, how do we bring the governance with the
data all the way?
Thank you.
We have time for one question.
Any
one question?
This time I didn't do anything, I promise.
Thank you, Tania.
Let's say I have a new dataset, or I'm prepared to
collect a new dataset.
Is there any way to simulate my methodology
through this AI agent so that I know how I stand and what I can
improve before actually doing it?
What an awesome question. I don't know if everybody could hear it.
Yes? Or no? No. Okay. Some hear it, some no.
If you're starting to create a new dataset, is there a way to
simulate what the dataset might look like to run it against the
agent to see what should be done to make it FAIR for AI?
It's an awesome question. So yes, you
can run the agent against a simulated dataset.
But the question,
it's a great one. Something we didn't think about, and I think it's totally
doable.
Rather than focusing on a simulated dataset, actually check the
methodology against FAIR for AI, which is
awesome addition to the whole thing.
Thank-
Work with us. Let's do it.
Thank you so much. I think we need to move on. Let's give Tania another hand.
And-
Next speaker is Saurabh Goralnik.
For speakers, please make sure before your
talk's up, you are at the back and see the AV
assistant to get mic'd up, okay? Before you come up here. Thank you.
Okay. Hello, everyone.
Before I begin, just to set the record straight on provenance,
I believe the term roundtripping was actually coined by Deb Paul.
But be that as it may, let me move on and start talking about the
topic today I want to cover. And before I begin, I
guess I want to ask all of you,
how many of you know what phenology is? Raise your hand.
Okay. That's not everybody. So I'm going to go ahead and just quickly remind you
that phenology is the timing of cyclical events that happen in nature.
So, for example, if you walk outside this congress
and
look at the trees
today, and have looked at them over the last week, you'll notice they're changing
colors, right? And that's phenology.
So before
I really jump in, one last thing. I want to just
try this out. I'm not much of a comedian, but
phenology joke.
I want to tell you a joke about phenology, but
unfortunately, I'm not sure I can get the timing right.
No? No? Okay. All right. So let's actually move into
the
core of the talk, which is about PhenoBase.
I love this project. I've been working on this for a long time, and it really has
brought home all the challenges of making data and knowledge AI
ready.
PhenoBase is an open access integrated database of global plant phenology, mostly
focused on in situ data.
Not remote sensing. And if you think about where we
are on trying to understand phenology globally, there are a ton
of limitations to our current understanding about phenology and
the compilation of phenology data to address questions about phenology, which are
really important for ecosystem function, for understanding how communities are
responding to climate change, and other kinds of disturbance.
So one of the key limitations is incompatibility
around phenology monitoring and phenology data in general.
So every phenology monitoring program out there has different ways that they
monitor. They've been doing monitoring for often hundreds of years, and they have
their own bespoke
nomenclature and structure, and even ways that they describe the phasing
versus the traits of phenology can be quite different, which makes interoperability
really hard. So over the last few years, we've been developing the Plant Phenology
Ontology. It's like a lingua franca that allows for phenology data to become
more integrated. And Ramona Walls, who was here
and gave a keynote earlier in the week, did a great job on her keynote, briefly
mentioned the Plant Phenology Ontology, which is just basically a hierarchically
organized set of terms that helps us build that
interoperability
integration framework for talking about phenology data across different phenology
programs. So the ontology's organized really simply.
We have basically core higher level fields like plant structure presence, and
underneath that, we might have a breaking leaf bud presence, which is just
defined as a plant phenology trait that is measured by the number of
breaking leaf buds.
It gets an identifier, a URI, and we also can
define logical axioms that link these terms together
and allow for inferencing. So if we know that there's 10
leaf buds present on a plant, we can infer that
we indeed have plant leaf bud presence.
A little more detail on this, just real quickly.
The ontology's organized in a really straightforward manner.
You have basically a phenology observing process.
That observing process has a specified input, in this case, a whole plant.
The output of that observing process might be a measurement datum of 10 to 20,
in this case, unfolded true leaf presences.
Now that we know that, we can also infer that unfolded true leaves are
present on this plant. So super simple, and we can
walk up the
class hierarchy and look at plant structure presence for a plant phenology trait.
When we did this, we actually realized that we really wanted to integrate herbarium
and iNaturalist images into this pipeline.
Mostly people in monitoring observe a whole plant.
And so we had to think hard about how to basically then
work with this idea that in many cases, we're only observing a portion of a plant,
not the whole plant.
And in that case, we might have to make a very different kind of assertion about
what we can say about leaf
absence, because if we don't see
a leaf on a portion of a plant, we can't necessarily infer that the
whole plant didn't have a leaf. And we might actually have to infer something
different about how we look at the upper counts when we have only a portion of a
plant. But with that in place, we can begin to integrate data at scale.
So we've done this with
data from the National Phenology Network, from herbarium specimens, from NEON, from
the Pan-European Phenology dataset. And that's been really fun.
But what we wanted to do
is go bigger. And the problem is that even with those monitoring program
data, we still have mostly gaps in what we know about phenology
globally.
So that's shown here in this map. We don't have data across most of
the globe, and we only have phenology monitoring on
a few species. So how can we scale up, and how can we do it over
time? We're also pulling data about phenology from historical
records as well. So kind of going back and having that longer record to
understand that changing phenology over decades or
centuries.
So how do we overcome those challenges?
The simple answer,
to start, in one way,
is iNaturalist.
This is citizen science at scale. How many of you are iNatters out in the audience?
Raise your hand
high in the air and be proud that you're an iNatter because you're helping us get
phenology data with every observation of a plant.
Last weekend alone, 150,000 observations.
Globally, that's a lot of data coming in per weekend.
110 million angiosperm observations.
That's a lot of data, and each of those images of a
plant has phenology information that we can extract from that if we know how.
So here's a typical iNaturalist record.
Many of you know what this looks like already. I'll go over this really quickly.
You have your metadata up on the top right, where you know who observed the plant,
where it was observed, and when it was observed, and you have some information
about
the uncertainty.
On the top left, we have our digital vouchers, mostly
images. This one has six images taken with the observation.
We have our activity traits on identification.
You identify an F identifier degree.
This will move to Richards Grade if it's a non-cultivated plant, and it has a
couple other attributes.
Importantly, for what I want to talk about are annotations.
This is a way that any user can come in and assert something about what they see in
an image. In this case, I saw, that was me who did the annotation, flower
buds.
I hope you can agree with that. Flowers, I hope you also agree they're flowers on
the plant. And in this case, breaking leaf buds.
So, that information is really rich.
There are about
1.5 to two million annotations on angiosperms
for phenology. That's a lot of data, which is really helpful.
So we took all those annotations, and we downloaded all of those images, which
turns out to be a much bigger hassle than you would ever imagine,
and we were able to build a state-of-the-art machine learning framework for
basically deriving phenology insights from the images.
And I'm not going to go into details.
I'd love to talk more about how we did this, but we used a masked autoencoder,
which is basically a pre-training step that helps us with efficiency and
accuracy for doing this
classification of
flowers and leaves and fruits present or absent on a plant.
We have finer stages than that.
We had a lot of data to train this model for flowers and fruits.
And then we did a lot of threshold tuning and ways to remove equivocal
records that were not
looking like they were scored particularly well.
So we did a
ton of work to basically
use humans in the loop and also look at our outputs carefully
to reduce the noise in these data.
We had great results,
about 98% annotating flowers. We're up to
95% on fruits for present, and then for absent, we're doing
really well,
about as good as a human can do. We looked at human annotation rates of success,
and this is pretty close to what humans do as well.
We did the same thing for herbarium specimens for all of GBIF that had
imaged herbarium specimens available.
I'm not going to go into the details of how we did this.
A slightly different version of a model
using ensembling. But what's really cool, really warms
my heart, is that this actually does really reduce those
gaps. So we're looking at where we had human-annotated data
available and where we mostly have monitoring data
in the blue cells shown on the map.
The burgundy cells are all the new grid cells with new data
globally that we've never had before. That is super exciting to me.
So we're closing those gaps in flowers and fruits.
And then if you look at the bottom one here, we're just looking at the percent of
data that comes from machine-annotated data.
So that's a lot of new data globally coming
directly from that machine labeling of phenology.
And it makes sense. We have about 2% or 3% of the records annotated from humans, so
the rest of the 97% that were annotated come from the machine.
But still, lovely to see that we actually solved the problem
of closing these significant gaps that we have in
phenology data that we can now make available.
So I found that really gratifying and really,
really exciting. So,
good. Great.
What was hard is making PhenoBase AI-ready.
And it's hard for a bunch of reasons.
We had to really think hard about providing AI model
information per record. We really wanted every record that came from PhenoBase to
have basically the model URI and a link to that model on Hugging Face,
where you can go and see what model produced that annotation.
That's super important to have per record.
We also wanted a per-record quality assessment for the AI-generated data.
In this case, we looked at the family-level success rates for annotating those
records based on human input and based on machine scoring of
our whole.data sets. And every record has a quality
assessment score generated with it. Okay?
We really cared about provenance and documentation.
We wanted a clear, traceable
link to the primary data producers that were producing these data, so you could
always go back and decide, "Hey, you know what? I disagree.
The machine got it wrong. I can look at the record and see that." We
wanted clear data dictionaries that travel with the data set because we really
worked hard to make sure that we could clarify what we do when we integrate
monitoring data, which has very different protocols than when we do it with
incidental data coming from iNaturalist. That was super important.
Also, access stewardship and policy were incredibly important for us.
How do we make these data available? We built a portal.
We have a Zenodo deposition.
We thought hard about how we're going to ever update these data.
150,000 records are being generated in a weekend.
We're talking about 75,000 records per day.
That number is growing every year. How are we ever going to keep up?
And how are we going to update these models and make them sustainable?
And then making sure we had really clear data use and data citation policies as an
aggregator. So we're
working as an aggregator, as PhenoBase.
We have to have our own citation policies, but every single other
resource that we draw from needs their own citation policies to be
adhered to. So if you look at a record-level data
on PhenoBase, like this Cornus canadensis on the right here, which is the
image from our iNaturalist observation, there are source and traceability.
You can trace back to the observation ID.
You can link directly back to the record.
You get a lot of the minimum record context that you need.
You get a model, a search in. You get the record-level quality scores.
And again, you get all of that semantic annotation
that makes
sense that when you want to discover something on
PhenoBase, you can discover it and search it at the level that you're interested
in. If you're interested in getting counts, or if you're just interested in flowers
present, you can get that information at the level that you need it, which is, I
think, really, really exciting.
So
bringing it all together,
and how this all works,
we have a single platform. We have one platform, PhenoBase, that can close all
of those gaps using a bunch of different
approaches. And importantly, and what I really want to drive home is
this beautiful synergy between thinking about ontologies and
machine learning to pull that into a framework where
we have AI-ready data and knowledge, I'd argue, and some knowledge
in those data that make it as usable as possible for
machines or for end users who want to do the science.
And that has value not just for the research community, but also for
education, community science, and outreach.
And with that, I'm just going to say a huge thank you to an amazing
team of people who pulled this off.
This is a really, really outstanding group of folks who worked really hard to do
all the hard parts of this. Ramona Walls, who you saw on Monday,
our developer, John Dack, Russell Dittmann, she's a pro at machine learning,
our lead PI, Dai-Jung Li,
wonderful guy. Great team, super fun.
Thank you so much for listening about PhenoBase, and I'm happy to take
any questions that you have.
We do have time for at least one question, possibly two.
Thanks a lot for this great presentation.
So I'm Martin Freiberg. I'm working for Phenops
in Germany. And we found out that,
for example, the first flowering is more important
than the mass flowering and
other stuff like that. So how do you deal with a
photographer's bias towards having a nice picture with lots of
flowers instead of having a picture of a branch
with 20 buds, but only one flower, for example?
Or leaf macrescents. Nobody likes to take pictures of
deadly
brownish kind of leaves.
That's an awesome question, and it gets right at that intersection
between the models and how you model and reduce the bias in the
data,
and the data itself. And so,
I actually do a ton of phenology
research, and there are methods that we use to basically
account for those biases, remove the
challenges of uneven reporting. So,
for example, City Nature Challenge and iNaturalist has this huge spike
in reporting. Actually, if you use the phenology
metrics that we use, that creates a bias.
So we have to kind of floor our data, think hard about bias reduction,
and that gets into where machines and humans will need to collaborate to basically
know what they can inference from the core data they're getting.
And in one way, PhenoBase at heart is mostly producing the best possible
data so that you can do bias correction and inferencing with as
much data as you need to make the right decisions downstream.
But there's still that human
focused activity, and you can begin to
collaborate with agents that talk about how to derive the best insights.
But the insight generation sits a little downstream of where I think PhenoBase
lives. And we definitely recognize there's tons of bias.
There's bias towards cities, there's bias towards
charismatic plants, and all that seems like decision-making that you have to do a
little downstream from where we are at this point.
But I think best practices are super important here.
All right. Let's thank Rob again, and we do need to move on.
So next up is Alexis Jolie.
Yeah. So good morning, everybody.
So I'm a little bit sick, so I hope you
hear me well and until the end, but yeah, let's try.
So I'm a computer scientist at INRIA and co-leader of
the PlantNet platform.
And yeah, I'm going to present you the
human AI curation pipeline that is in production in PlantNet.
So for those who don't know PlantNet, so it's a collaborative
platform that was created 15 years ago now, and
its main feature is an app that allow to photo
ID plants and to share it with the community.
And it's used by about 20 million users per
year, and since the beginning, we collected
1.6 billion raw observations. So that means pictures
taken by the people with the app. Okay?
So what you can see here is a screenshot of the real-time
viewer that we have, where you see the type of queries
people submit to the application.
So it's about 20,000 individual plants every hour.
All right? So of course, there is a lot of
very relevant biodiversity observations, but as you can see, there is
also a lot of diversity of different usage and
diversity of content. People take pictures of potted
plants, of house plants, of gardening plants, so it's
very, very opportunistic. And it's even worse than that.
People want to identify plants on their clothes, on their
tattoos,
in books, in drawings. So it's real usage.
They really want something, but yeah, okay, what to do with that?
And you also have non-plant organisms for a reason we don't
really understand. So mushrooms, they believe it's plants, but for the other one,
maybe they just think the app can do something else.
A lot of human images.
So the typical scenario is a teacher starts a session in the
classroom.
Students install the app, and the first thing they do is to take pictures of each
other.
So you see that in the stream, and it's very frequent.
You have a lot of data like that.
You have non-living things, people just playing with it, or they just install the
app, they test it on what they have, or they want to identify what's on
their pizza, or I don't know why.
And more periodically, there are some sensitive
content, so nudity, some exhibitionists that
try to
post images publicly and trying to do
that.
Drug-related content. People try to identify their cannabis
or whatever they bought. Yeah, things like that
All right. So of course, we have to clean this data, as you
understand. And so this is an overview of the
pipeline.
There are two main branches, so one in the middle
that has human in the loop and one that is fully automatic. Okay?
And the main outputs are the training data for model and the
data that we push in GBIF.
But the very first step is the main AI model. Okay?
Any image submitted to PlopNet first go through the main
AI model.
So this AI model is trained on
22 or 25 now, sorry, my slide is a little bit late.
Twenty-five million of images of PlopNet
that are
human-validated. Okay? And so the
model outputs the species, the genus, the families,
some disease also now it's a new feature in the app, and the reject
classes, okay, to reject all those contents that we are not
interested in.
And interestingly, this is the classifier for which we have the most
problem. It's very difficult to build this classifier because
it's intrinsically difficult task. All right?
Many images are multi-label,
with the plant and something else, even the exhibitionist, so I let you imagine.
And so yeah, you have to
label your training data, and it's more an editorial
choice. So what is the user's intention?
Do we want such pictures with humans
in the app? Do we want to keep it or not?
That's the real choice we have to make when we build this classifier.
All right. So then once it has passed this model,
there is those two
flows, and the first one is when people opt in
to share the observation publicly.
So this is very important. So people say, "Okay, I want this
particular observation to be public." So they opt in to
this provider CC BY-SA license with their name, and
this enters the human curation pipeline. All right?
And so let's see this human cooperation pipeline.
So any observation in the app can be voted, revised by the other
users. So this concerns the species, but also the organ,
whether it's cultivated or not, the quality of the image.
And the
algorithm to aggregate the different votes on an observation is a
weighted
majority voting, which means that each user has a different weight,
and the weight reflects his expertise.
Okay, that's the principle.
And the expertise is estimated through an algorithm that I won't detail
today, but it's an expectation-maximization algorithm,
that try to predict the number of species you are able to
recognize. So it's not your full success rate over all observation because
you could be very good on just common plants.
It's really the number of species that gives
an idea of the expertise.
Yeah, so let's look now at the other branch.
So sorry, maybe just to finish on this branch.
So once those data are validated, they are used
to train the model that I was presenting at the beginning.
So those 22 million observations are the one that are
human-validated. The model is retrained regularly, and then
it is reused to process the new queries and also the old queries.
We reprocess them regularly.
And we have this other stream, which is to still try to make something
useful with the other data that are not shared
with the opt-in principle.
So we don't share the images for these observations, but we can still use the
fact that a species has been observed at a particular location, and
in particular for GBIF. All right?
And so for those data, we only share the occurrence in GBIF,
not the image, because we don't have the opt-in agreement of the people, but we
consider that the species and the location is a common good
that we should use. All right? And so for this pipeline, it's
only automatic, and so we only keep the
AI predictions above a given score.
This score is learned for each version of the model on some
private test set,
to guarantee that we have a very low error rate. Okay?
We only push the one for which there is less than
0.01%
error in the data.
Okay. And then you only have 150 million
observations after this filtering, and we then have other
filters before pushing them in GBIF,
and in particular to remove the cultivated plants and the
potted plants, and this is clearly the most difficult
task ever.
Yeah, so
this is cultivated, this is spontaneous, so if you only use a visual
classifier, so it's very difficult.
Yes, same for this
case. So the one in the pot, so it's spontaneous, but somehow there is
some water that is bring there. So what to
say? And even some forest is cultivated, so the
concept is somehow ambiguous.
So our current approach is more to only estimate the wildness
level of an observation with a vision-based
classifier
that is trained in different ways.
So observations that are far from any human construction,
so we tag them automatically as wild.
Observation with visible anthropized context, so like
birds, house, whatever. So we have in the classifier
a lot of training data about that. And then also we use the
cultivated tag in the app. So we really try to build a visual classifiers
that say, "Okay, this one is really into the wild," and we only push that data
into GBIF.
And then we have additional flora based on WCVP, the
country, and things like that
at the level two.
We keep both native and introduced, but only restricted to the list of
known species in the area.
And then this allows us to publish two data sets in
GBIF, so the one that is human-validated and the one that is just
automatically
computed from the queries.
All right. So all this work is still ongoing,
and we have a new project
starting. See Dimitri here is involved.
So the BIGEL project.
It's led by Aarhus University with all those partners.
And
the goal is really to develop AI-driven workflows,
acquisition of new sensors with participatory
science, and in particular, the subject of
curating the data is clearly one of the central points.
But also we'll try to go further with things that I didn't
present here but are kind of dynamic effects
of negative feedback loops. For instance, if the model starts
to do an error, then people follow the AI, and that
injects some
contamination in the model, and we observe some species
that start to derive 10 years after the start of PlotNet.
So I let you imagine the same kind of effect with the
web and OpenAI and all that kind of stuff, so what could happen in 10 years.
So yeah,
I'm done. Thank you. That was a little bit fast.
We now have time for questions.
Thanks for this great talk.
You drafted this
algorithm for leveling up of users for the
identification. How do you prevent users from
easily leveling up,
using or building upon predictions of the AI or of
others'
identifications, such as this?
Yeah, no, clearly, it's a very good question that we are working a lot on.
People always try to trick some of them.
For instance, they try to just shoot books
with the species names.
But now we more or less well-identify the books captures acquisition, so
it's a way to do it.
Then
if they only follow the AI, we know it, and we don't consider these
followers in the algorithm. So the following
identification doesn't have the
same weight in the algorithm, so clearly it's also a way to do it.
And then you still have an error rate.
Those people that really try to push many data in one way or
another,
they also do some errors on
others.
We also have some animation of curators, people that are really
curating manually the database and that identify such people,
and then we just ghost them or things like that. Yeah.
Hi. Alexis.
Did I understand correctly that the ones that you label as cultivated are not
pushed to GBIF?
Yeah. Sorry, what is not pushed?
The data that are labeled as cultivated.
Oh, yeah.
Exactly.
Okay.
We only push the ones that are really
into the wild. That's the idea. But the classifier is not perfect.
Yeah. But I'm just curious, cultivated plants also have an impact on the
environment. Would it not make sense to publish those to GBIF and label those as
cultivated through the model that you have? There's Darwin Core terms to do that.
I know that iNaturalist is not doing this, but they have an impact on the
environment, and it's very useful data.
Yeah. This was a requirement of GBIF to not publish them, because
at the beginning, we were publishing all data, but in particular, the potted
plants were really not expected by GBIF.
So they asked us to not-- Because as you saw, we
have more probably cultivated data than in the wild.
But somehow we still have some cultivated plants because the classifier is not
perfect, and the reason why we don't push regularly
in us is because of that. This classifier is really
problematic to tune. But that's an open discussion for the community.
If we push them, we should add the tag "cultivated" in GBIF, and that's fine.
But if we have too many of them, then people train SDMs,
and we already see bias in many SDMs because of that, so we try to
push at least as least as possible. Yeah.
Yes, a quick continuation. This might change.
In GBIF, there is a huge interest from agrobiodiversity community to be
represented in GBIF. We're talking
to
the FAO, and so there is a whole layer of
not freely dispersing biodiversity, not only cultivated and agro.
And I have a question about opt-in share-alike.
I make parallels to Flickr and to iNaturalist, where
reuse of the image data
is actually not something that people want to see less.
They want to see more of this, and I think at least iNat changed to more
liberal license than share-alike, which translated to the
growth of publicly accessible and reused records.
And
I think people have more goodwill than we generally think, and
offering them a more liberal license by default might be a good avenue.
SA sounds a bit strict to me.
Yeah, no, we could change or let the user choose.
It's an open discussion. We
think the buy is very important, but the share-alike, we could change.
We can discuss it. Yeah
Thank you. Let's thank our speaker again.
Thank you.
And the next presentation is from Kit Lewers.
Can you guys hear me? Okay, perfect. Hi, everybody.
My name is Kit.
I'm a PhD candidate at the University of Colorado Boulder, and also a NASA
FINES fellow at Goddard Space Flight Center.
And I also work with NEON a good bit because we have some spectrometers that
overlap at NASA and with NEON. But yeah, today I'm going to be talking
about From Spectra to Species: Persistent Biodiversity
Records from Multimodal Remote Sensing, and this has three
main themes running through it. So first,
remote sensing has a longitudinal biodiversity problem.
So
we have a lot of satellites, aircraft, and even just on-the-ground
survey ecological
revisits that happen at NASA, at NEON, a lot of different places.
But most workflows process each of these acquisitions as a separate
image. So just for some thought, let's say that we're
running an airborne campaign that goes over
something like this year after year.
And some campaigns, we're really good about being like, "This
individual has this ID, and this is what it looked like last year, and this is what
it looks like this year." And sometimes we're not so great about that.
But the same organism can appear in 10 datasets sometimes without
accumulating one
connected history, and I think that's really important for trees and things
that exist. But what about when disturbance happens and that doesn't exist
anymore? How are we going to reflect that if we have 10 different
records? So that's where this came from,
this problem and me wanting to look at it, and this is very much a proof of concept
workflow. This is
unfortunately not a part of my PhD, so this is my little passion project on
the side, so I'm definitely looking for some feedback and what people would
be interested in seeing.
So once again, one organism, many disconnected
detections, and we can also see this in GBIF.
So I was talking to Tim Robertson this morning, and I was like, "I know we do fuzzy
matching of organisms in GBIF, but what are the constraints of that?" And he's
like, "Oh, yeah. If you had them a year apart, we probably
wouldn't match those together." And I was like, "Oh, no."
So yeah. So the analytical progression of this
pipeline is simple. So repeat images can become yearly or, depending
on your temporal resolution, weekly, monthly,
whatever you're doing, detections, and then matching connects them
to same physical tree crowns in this.
So what I am using as my test dataset here
is a NEON, National Ecological Observatory Network, site called
SJER, and that's the San Joaquin Experimental Range.
And I chose this because I'm very interested in what it would look
like to use completely off-the-shelf, nothing that I made, to
run this algorithm, and it turns out that it worked okay to validate the
shape of the pipeline I was making, but didn't work super well in
actually getting the results that I would want to publish
to a data aggregator. So,
at TadWig last year, if you were at my talk, I proposed
using coincident structure, so LIDAR
metrics with spectra. So
I'm a big nerd about spectroscopy.
So basically, everything on Earth reflects a certain
energy signature, and I think that that is amazing because if you could get
to the point where you could be
confident that the spectra that you're seeing are the ones that are actually coming
off of the object, you could potentially identify all matter on Earth
from an airplane and maybe even a satellite one day, and that would be super cool
for biodiversity if we could do that.
So that's why spectra is included, because it can help you identify
taxa,
along with other chemistry. And then also using red,
green, blue, and near-infrared imagery because it's extremely
high resolution. The stuff that we were just looking at on the last slide,
I believe, is one centimeter resolution, and then I work with
another instrument that can sometimes get sub-centimeter resolution, and if you're
using drones, you could definitely get even higher resolution.
But yeah, so the goal of this is towards
detecting vegetation crowns and then adding a persistent identifier to
that so we can connect records across time and
space.
So
that was my presentation last year.
This year, I finally had some time to start breaking it.
So
I wanted to know, okay, this is a cool idea, but can I actually
do it? I don't know.
So I decided to create a quick prototype, like I said, that would constrain
identification with field records.
So NEON is an amazing organization.
I absolutely love working with them, and I believe that they have over 150 data
products associated with 80 field sites, which used to be 81,
but we did just lose one.
But yeah, so
I wanted to constrain that only to vegetation
records that had been taken from survey data.
I do understand the implication that that would leave out the ability to detect
potentially invasive species at this point, but it is a proof of concept, and
I am planning on making sure that that is a part of another pipeline as
I do plan to continue working on this.
And then I also chose something called Deep Forest, which is an algorithm made by
Ben Weinstein, which can go through very densely forested
areas and is very good at selecting out individual tree crowns,
so we would actually be able to segment and then identify.
I chose the San Joaquin
Experimental Range because it is very much outside of the use case of
Deep Forest. This is an oak savanna with a whole bunch of
bare grass and rock and-
Big tree crowns that sometimes look like little tiny tree crowns within them.
So,
the NEON field records provided a defensible local species that I
could compare to, and the sparse oak savanna was a really good
test of that. And then Deep Forest is that other
off-the-shelf AI that I wanted to use, and I did.
So, my first pipeline was super simple.
Once again, just trying to validate the shape of the data pipeline that I wanted to
make, not necessarily get perfect results.
And what I wanted to do for this specifically was acquire the
high-resolution red, green, blue imagery,
delineate independent tree crowns, constrain candidate
species with NEON records, which I did pull from GBIF using the PyGBIF
API, and export
persistent provenance-rich observations.
And the provenance is important. I'll talk more about this in a second, but
there is a lot of places that uncertainty can be introduced into
this pipeline. So, I wanted to make sure that the uncertainty at each
step was included, so you didn't just get this end metric where it's like, "Oh,
the AI that
identified the species must've been super uncertain," where it could've actually
been something further up in the pipeline that was producing that
uncertainty. So,
what did I actually do?
So, this is two years,
2023 and 2024. And in year
of '23, I only detected 222 crowns,
and in 2024, I was already detecting 232 crowns,
and I was like, "I don't think oaks grow in a year." I'm not a plant
person, but
I think that's a little crazy. And what I did from there was
do an IOU, or an intersection of union, to see
if I could place where trees were overlapping really well.
I'm so sorry that this is not the colorblind-friendly
version. I thought that I put that in there, but there are green boxes, which are
the overlaps, and then blue is from 2024, and
we're only seeing it in 2024, and red is if we
only saw it in 2023.
And it did
okay. It saw trees. It saw a lot of rocks, and what was
also interesting is it saw a lot of shadows that it thought was trees, and those
persisted from year to year. And what I decided to do, because I was a little
short for time, is I wanted to do just the central part
because the way that cameras are, the further you get away from the
center of the image, the more distorted things become.
So I was like, "Well, I'll just go in the center." And even in the very center, I
can see two years in a row. I don't know if you can see that tiny yellow box
inside of a bigger yellow box on the
right side of the image. I do not know my left from right. I'm so sorry.
But on the right side of the image. And yeah.
So, there were a lot of things that are already happening, but it did
pretty well. I let it segment. I was like, "Let's see where we go from here."
So, I wanted to see what would change when each
observation contributed to one organism history.
So, the observation remains distinct, but a shared organism
identifier is what was connecting them over time, which is why I was looking for
those overlaps.
And
yeah. So, the identification that I decided to use, I just used an
off-the-shelf cloud model, which performed pretty poorly, I'm not going to lie.
It just gave me one type of tree, and they were a bunch of different trees.
But
yeah. So,
the biodiversity infrastructure that helped constrain the AI also
hurt it when it was a very general model.
But it
did okay. But this was just my way of showing that you could
actually go from a airborne platform segment
and then identify something to actually create a GBIF record.
So, the useful failure that I saw was the weak performance showed
me that we couldn't really just throw some spaghetti at the wall and see if it
would stick.
You will get results, but you won't get great ones.
And it also showed why model versioning, training, ecology,
operating domain, and segmentation confidence must travel at each
part of the record that is going either to GBIF or wherever you would
aggregate it. So, the model provenance is a
biodiversity data provenance because uncertainty can enter before
identification, during preprocessing, during
segmentation, or even during that temporal match, which we saw in
that.
But yeah. So, what ended up happening at the end is after I did
the
identification is I had it create Darwin
Core occurrence records, and I mainly just used occurrence ID, organism ID, because
that was the axis that I wanted everything to revolve around.
Scientific name. Oh,
sorry, my formatting's a little higgledy-piggledy.
Identification remarks, and then the identified by, which I put as
AI.
I'm interested in people's thoughts
for the identified by. Oh, sorry, did you have a question?
Okay. And then basis of record, which was a machine
observation. So,
this created a bidirectional relationship where we were using data that we already
had
to create new data. So, the data that we already had was the trees that already
existed in that area, and the new data was actually being able to
look at it from the sky and
actually identify it.
So, this is the part that actually makes me really excited about
this. So,
if you can start identifying individuals and getting a
place where they are and have point- This is data from Panama.
You can start tying other observations to that
individual. So here we see an airborne where you can see the tree
crowns pretty well. This is a mangrove forest. Oh, and that also got cut off.
But this is a Landsat
tile from the wet season or the rainy
season in Panama, and then if you look over, you can see that we also
have an emit
pixel, which gives you hyperspectral imagery.
And
if you can find a way to bring that data in,
you can monitor what is happening in the spatial context
of a species throughout the year, and potentially all the way back to
1972,
which is when Landsat first started.
And I'm running out of time, so I'm going to go through this really fast.
So that was my first pass, but now I'm actually using Goddard's
G-LiHT, which is the Goddard LIDAR, Hyperspectral, and Thermal
instrument that flies on the bottom of a plane.
We have nine different sensors all integrated into one
platform, so everything is running concurrently, and we have a 15-year
archive that we're working on,
going through, and this would be a great way to get millions, maybe even
billions, once again, not good at math, tree records, and
hopefully get those into GBIF. So the coincident LIDAR
and imaging spectroscopy and repeat flights can help us
measure that in a longitudinal way.
And also what I said earlier is we are
working on three different distinct
climes that we have, so Puerto Rico tropical forest, the
Smithsonian Research Forest we'll also be looking at,
which is temperate mixed hardwood, and then we'll be looking at Arctic boreal
forest structure and possibly making specific models for each so that we
can identify those with a great confidence.
And the future biodiversity record can potentially show how an
organism changes through time while preserving exactly how we know it.
So sorry for being a little rushed, and thank you so much for your attention, and I
would love to talk to you guys about this.
Thank you
for this pitch for individual ID of trees and
plants, and there's a great precedent.
So in '24,
a large group came together and wrote introducing
unique animal ID and digital life history museum for wildlife metadata.
It is incorporated in GBIF. It's incorporated in many different--
So there are two parts to it.
Adding the individual organism ID
directly extendable from animal ID.
That gives you across many different datasets.
The other part to it is who's going to hold the registry, and that's the
Digital Life History Museum. In animal case, that's the
Movebank
Digital
History Museum. So the Movebank is German
funded,
holds all the movement data for-- Somebody movement, I think? Yeah.
Oh, no. I was pointing at Peter.
Oh, sorry. Yeah.
So the question is then,
with instantly extendable to plants, trees
specifically probably, who's going to hold the
registry?
Yeah. So this is actually something I've been thinking about because it is
going to be a harder thing to do. I've been thinking maybe
a collaboration of different
agencies that work on remote sensing,
or even just looking at the GBIF model
where we have our institutions that do these campaigns, and
they're the ones who hold onto the data and then push it to GBIF.
But also, I think there's a lot of opportunities for
not making something new, but making something collaborative because I think this
is also a great step towards ecological intelligence, where you can
make dashboards and pull in a lot of different data points.
Did that answer your question at all? It did not. Let me think about it.
Yeah, maybe, that conversation can be continued-
Yeah
... afterwards, and there's lunch also following, and
there's actually an innovation out of the Image-Omics Institute
that might be quite applicable to one of the problems you're facing, too.
And maybe, Antonio or myself can talk
more about that. So next up is Jack Hollister.
Yeah.
It's a double act. We're going to go a bit local.
So let's just kick it off because I'm going to do the intro.
We're talking about
local stuff, but let me introduce ourselves first.
So we've got Jack here, who is senior robotics engineer at Natural History
Museum, working with Disco UK currently, and then myself, an IT project manager
who is building a collections management system for the Natural History Museum.
We
have a friendship which revolves around tinkering and building cool stuff.
That's essentially it. And part of that is a more fundamental idea
which we had, which was around presenting some of the talks that we're doing here,
which is bringing the AI onto a hardware,
and not sending it to the cloud, processing it, and building an environment
where researchers can actually prototype and build and test a lot of the
things. So there's three talks around that here. Cleaning the data is this one.
I'll be talking tomorrow about some literature, and then those who missed
it, Jack talked yesterday about some morphology
extraction
from images, which was really, really cool.
But what are we doing?
Well, we needed some hardware. We have some good friends.
We got to borrow two of these little beasts here, so the Dell GB10s,
which
together you can cluster them, and you can actually run some pretty good
models, up to 400 billion parameters, which is really cool.
And what we wanted to do is we wanted to check whether we could
use these to clean data. So building a
collections management system, migrating huge amounts of data, normalizing
that, bringing that all together. Maybe we could use this.
But it also proved another thing, because when we did go to the museum and said,
"Look, we're going to be installing some agents, we're going to be running some
crazy stuff," our IT went, "No. That's not what you're going to do."
So we did run a lot of it at home, but we did end up
actually having the museum build an infrastructure that is
a step towards building an infrastructure that's safe
for researchers to plug into local hardware, use their
machine learning or their proofs of concepts, and
then not going onto the internal
infrastructure and changing people's accounts or doing stuff that they shouldn't.
So it's a good step in that way. And I thought that was a good outcome of that, and
something that we are exploring with the institution at the moment.
Before I hand over to Jack, I just wanted to go through the three examples that we
did. So what we decided to do is we would run a
24-hour
test on these machines, trying to clean up three specific types of
data. So we did a full data load of sites, which is geography, a
full data load of the bibliography, and a full data load of the GPS coordinates,
and the aim was to clean those up. Now, what were we actually doing?
So
sites,
700,000 records there, 58 columns in that one record, trying
to bring back country. So trying to look at the
empty records for country, looking across those fields, seeing if
we could extract that country name, so we could put it in, so we can
start cleaning up that data. We did, in most cases.
Jack will come into that. Bibliography, again, just titles.
The amazing thing is we have thousands and thousands and thousands of records that
just don't have a title, because researchers are used to just putting in the
abbreviation. They understand that. That's been practiced for a long time.
So doing that, again, would bring back a lot of data.
So searching across 113 fields and trying to fix about
59,000 or 60,000 records.
And then the big one.
Sorry, that's still that one. Yeah.
So bringing back that, and here's an example of it doing correct.
I want to hand over to Jack because that's the interesting stuff.
And then GPS.
With about 6.2 million records,
and what does it say? 4.4 that just don't have usable
GPS records. And that's historic.
That's not because people have been bad with their data. That's just historic.
It's there. But again, an opportunity to fix
that and quite a good number of columns, including names
of places, et cetera, as an example is here, where something is missing.
But actually, when you look across it, you've got HB Kent UK, and you
can actually find the GPS for that, narrow it down, and you can use
that as an attempt. Now, I will say
that this talk is not about whether the data was correct.
This talk is about whether we can use local AI and local models to start
looking at that. There's a huge question, well, there's a slide at the end that
will talk about that. But with that, I believe
I'm safe, and I can hand over to you.
Excellent.
Hello, everyone. So coming back to the main question, we wanted to ask,
can we actually run local large language models on this
hardware and use it to process these large data sets in a reasonable amount of
time? So for each experiment, we gave it up to 24 hours and
recorded how much data it would process, how many tokens it used,
and what equivalent commercial API cost, what it might cost, rather.
Importantly, around 10% of the data we were examining, we
put as test data. So we removed the known answers and then fed this
back to the machine so we could see if it was right or wrong.
So before running the main experiments, we tested quite a number of different
local models on this GP10 cluster.
So there was lots of Qwen models. We tried a lot of the GPT local models.
But the one we went for was from NVIDIA.
So they have a nice local large language model called
Nemotron, and particularly the Nemotron Super.
Cool. But you cannot simply just
download a
large language model, a local one, and get it to run.
You actually have to give it both a prompt and design a harness for it.
So for the prompt, the prompt defines the task, and it tells it what evidence the
model is allowed to use. But the harness is like the
software, and it actually prepares the data.
It sends it to the model, checks if it was correct, and then
sends it to the next one. So the large language model is only a small
part of what the actual overall system does.
So for the results. For the first experiment was recovering missing
country data. So in 24 hours, the system was able to process
over 4,000 records. On the test data set, it
recovered about 80% correctly, exactly
as
was there.
It rejected ones that were ambiguous.
So these were ones that were spelt slightly differently.
But if we wanted to process this full data set on this cluster, it would take
46 days. So
it's a reasonable amount of time.
With the bibliography experiment, it was a bit more difficult.
So in the 24 hours, we were able to
examine 2,300 records. There were 66 duplicates that
we could easily move over, but we only managed to recover
125 records from the internet, and that's because the internet is
quite clued up on sending large language models when you want to scrape data.
So most of them are rejected. But I think it's good to point this sort of
data out to people, or this sort of problem.
And then the locality experiment.
So in 24 hours, we were able to process about
6,500 records. Every record was
Processed, and we had the mean
medium accuracy of about 5.3 kilometers from
the actual location. So not exactly where it was, but it's
fairly close, and we think that's quite good. But what about if...
Oh, wrong way.
What about if you want to do this at scale?
What about if we want to do our full data set?
So
DISCO has just started, which I'm a part of, and when I was looking at
all the data it has across GBIF and everything, it has about
6.4 million records that
have this vibitamin string but don't have modern
coordinates.
If we wanted to run this on the GB10 cluster, it would take over 1,000 days to
get all the data. So that's not a
usable time, really.
Wrong way again. So we went back to our friends at Dell and
NVIDIA, and they gave us access to this computer that wasn't released at the time.
It's called GB300. I won't go over all the details,
but it's a desktop, but it's very powerful, and it does cost
£100,000, so it's not an easy investment for people to get.
But
with this, you can
run multiple models at a time. So you can run 100 concurrent
Nematron models.
So it's built to really power through some of this data.
And this meant that we can
run 22,000 records per hour, and then this
is half a million records a day,
and these are the results for that.
Oh, no. And
then when I was looking at the data set, we realized that there was
2.7 million records with both coordinates and the
vibitamin string. So we were actually going to use this as our test data set.
So that means we actually had to process 9.1 million records.
But when I was looking through it, I realized that a lot of the records had
duplicates, so this brought down the total volume down to 4.2
million records, and this meant we could run it over 9.1 days
continuously. And the medium accuracy did go
up to about 12 kilometers, but I think that's still pretty good.
And I won't go over the exact values, but this is estimated
cost of how much it would
be to run this on commercial APIs.
Oh, yeah. Cool. So
it was fun, actually,
bringing that data down and trying to analyze it.
It does open quite a few questions, of course.
One is,
yes, I think there's huge potential in having an infrastructure where
researchers
and data managers can test and try and use without incurring
token costs. There's an upfront cost to that, of course.
We, of course, only looked at a small portion, but one of the things I think is the
third point there is we haven't talked about validation here, right?
I am meant to feed that data back into the collections
management system, and there is no way that we can validate
4.4 million GPS coordinates. So there needs to be a
way of presenting that in the system.
Now,
there's a talk later today that I do about the system that we're building.
I don't directly come into that, but part of it is presenting the data alongside
with the real data and having it,
over time, be part of the enrichment of the data.
But because it still lives in the system, you can still search on it, and you can
still bring it back. So it lives side by side, and it doesn't really
influence the real data, at least for now.
If we get really good validation mechanisms, then hey, we can just pop it
in and flag it, of course.
And then, yes, locally, AI does offer a different
token economics.
You can
establish an infrastructure
over time at an initial cost
and allow people to bring their data in safely,
work with it, and then take it back home, and it won't
go where it doesn't need to go. This is mainly CMS
data, collections management data. There's a lot of sensitive stuff.
So maybe not entirely
equal to a lot of the data that we've been talking about, but it is really relevant
to us.
I think we've got loads of time for questions now because I think we're actually
done.
So thank you very much for listening and for a lot of
people who were involved and helped.
Well done.
That's really exciting to see.
I
will say,
using a flagship
commercial model might not be the best solution, period, for anything we
want to do at scale. We do a lot of work with the
mini or nano models that are
a lot less costly. But I love that you're using a local language model.
I wanted to say one quick thing. I think it's great to be doing these experiments.
We're doing the same thing at our institution at the Florida Museum.
I've been working hard to really benchmark.
I think benchmarking is super important here.
I just want to encourage that to be the core of what you think about as how to get
those benchmarks that you can compare how well an AI does versus what a human would
do
to geo-reference a record or produce geographical coordinates or
whatever the task.
The core thing I wanted to say is I really do think that it's probably not the best
idea to rely on a large language model to produce geospatial data.
I think you need a double-layer approach.
I think you need to use the language model for the semantic part of finding and
interpreting localities, and then you need a geospatial part.
The one thing that I've found that large language models don't do very well with is
math.
Surprisingly, right? You would think that would be something they're really good
at. But I do worry that you want to
maybe best practice that a little further about how to operationalize that as you
move it into production.
Yeah.
We did consider bringing other tools in, but we wanted to almost make this
the experiment that just does it with the local models.
But yeah, there's so many different tools we can bring in to help
validate or even do the job and then have the large language model
be the validation.
Quick question. I think there's one more question. I completely agree.
The talk that I'm doing tomorrow, I think, is not on the GB10s,
it's actually on a laptop. And there's
a lot of optimization to get the model just to deal with what it's good
at.
So we do need to move on, unfortunately.
We're a little bit behind time, and I'm sure everybody here
is starting to get hungry, and I don't want
to cut too much into lunchtime. But,
I do think the next talk's going to be worth staying here.
So please,
if you can just contain your hunger for a little bit longer,
and for Lars Vogt's presentation.
No, that's mine.
Thank you, Hilma.
And I'm happy to be here. We have the 10-minute
slot, so I really try to be fast.
What we want to present is basically ideas that we developed in the
EcoWeaver initiative for our core model,
for semantic framework for ecological knowledge synthesis.
And
this is, for now, purely conceptual.
We're currently developing a paper draft for that, and there's no
running
implementation of that yet.
Okay, this is an older version. Sorry for that.
So the running example that we will follow is
Darwin's naturalization conundrum, where we have
phylogenetic relatedness as the cause
variable, and then establishment success as the effect,
and involving two populations, a non-native and a
resident
population. And
the thing is that the same cause can
result in a positive or a negative effect.
And ecologists often explain these phenomena
in reference to context dependence.
And we apply a convention here. So, causal
relationships we want to model as maybe sets or
individual binary relations between two processes of
change of a quality or disposition and their bearer.
So we see immediately how the
simple
graph that I showed you before splits up into these two paths:
the pre-adaptation path and the limiting similarity path.
But we still have inconsistencies here because the same
cause cannot result in two contradictory effects.
And the representation is not
fair and not clear.
So,
we introduced three requirements for representing usable
causal knowledge. The first one is really about
intervention
operations, where causal relationships, of course, play a certain
role. I will not go into detail here in this talk, but that
refers to the triple-A principle of actionable knowledge that we've
developed, and you can read about it here.
The second one is that representations have to distinguish general claims
from the particular cases.
And then, since our variables are change
processes, we have to represent the change process
itself as well, and the methods for quantifying the change
of the qualities, because some qualities are unobservable, like
phylogenetic relatedness, and we have to apply certain methods.
And depending on the methods, the
values can be different.
So, these are representational requirements, and
for fair and clear representation, we have to be able to
represent very different types of statements in
the database.
And many of them are not supported by OWL-based formal
semantics.
And that's why we want to use the semantic units framework, and in
very short, the idea is you have some semantic content that is
semantically meaningful for a human user.
So it might be one triple, it might be many triples.
And we have one identifier that represents, in the graph, this
semantic content that then instantiates a class, so it's
classified. The approach is technology-agnostic.
So you see up here one statement as a graphical
representation in OWL, and the same content as a tabular
representation.
And it's clear compliant because we map for
each type of statement
everything to a, we call it dynamic label or a dynamic
graph, a graphical representation that is then rendered
in the interface, so it's human interpretable, although the
structure itself is machine actionable.
So the data becomes cognitively interoperable.
The approach also allows us to negate statements in the A
box without having to resort on complex class
axioms.
And if you want to hear more about that, on Friday is another talk where
we go into more detail. So with that, we can
now specify universal causal statements as universal
causal statement units. We have our proposition.
We have the one identifier, the resource that represents it.
We have metadata that we can link to that
provenance. If the cause of claim comes
from the literature, we could also include bibliographic reference
there and the extraction method that has been applied.
And we can also distinguish between
propositions that are asserted to be true and those that are not
asserted to be true in that framework.
So, two contradicting claims can coexist without causing
logical inconsistency.
So we would have resolved that problem,
and then we can build causal networks
based on these binary relations, and we define rules
when that can be done, under which conditions.
And the framework also allows to have collections of
statements giving their own identifier.
And so you see here the conundrum, the two
pathways, and all the individual binary
relations. And to each of these, the two pathways and the
entire network, we can provide identifiers
for them and add metadata to that, and they form a semantic grid.
And that can be like a map service, like OpenStreetMaps.
We have for all, for the path, for the networks, for each
individual binary relationship, we have addresses with
our IDs. And now we can pin diverse
content to these specific addresses.
Also, we could supply any information that is
necessary for simulation-ready causal models,
where causal models can basically import the data,
run the causal experiment, the simulation, and feed back the
results to the graph.
So we merge basically a human interpretable content with
machine interpretable structure.
And what we can pin is evidence layer.
We can pin conditions if we want to do,
for instance,
intervention operations and when can they be applied and when
not, the methods for the variables, and the
formal readings for the causal models.
And here's an example how we can pin these different
types of information. So up here we have the causal, basically
the rule, the claim as a universal causal statement
unit. And now we can pin the cases as assertional
causal statement units to that general rule using
the satisfies property, which is a statement in its own right.
And because of that, we can also negate that statement
and indicate failures where the case doesn't
have the effect that the claim has predicted.
And
querying these
failures is straightforward then in the graph.
And we can add measurements and observations, so provide empirical
evidence,
and that is linked to the case. So the context is really
a property of the case.
And of course, all the units are versioned, so they
are citable in synthesis.
Looking at the causal variables, you see here we have decrease in
establishment success. That's an unobservable property.
So we need some method or proxy how to be able
to
quantify that, and above-ground dry biomass is one
of these, but then it must be documented how that works.
And here we have in red the variable itself,
but it's in the same time also the identifier of this
larger compound of statements. So you can basically
focus in that information and get the entire picture.
We can also define causal perspective.
So we identify a cause and effect as focus
in our network, and we identify the possible causal
path between these two variables and
give them an identifier, again, a causal perspective.
And then we can automatically identify the
chains, the forks, and the collider junctions in the paths
and give them a unit, so an identifier and address again,
and pin all the information that is relevant here.
So conclusion is with this approach, we want to
accumulate instead of accrue results.
So ecology, we know, produces causal knowledge faster than it can
consolidate it, and we hope that by making all the
different types of information as first-class
objects in the graph, we can link them and
hopefully help to get with the
consolidation
become faster. So our manuscript points to many
more ideas, but with 10 minutes, there's no time to
describe that. We distinguish between reflective and formative
indicators for unobservables. We look at family of causal
hypotheses by dissecting the context space into
applicability spaces and failure spaces.
We look at context dependence as a result
of underspecified causal variables in taxonomic and partinomic
ways, and so on. So if you have questions for that, please come.
I'm happy to discuss that.
And that's it.
And thank you for your attention.
Any maybe quick question for Lars before
we head out for lunch?
Everyone is hungry.
I think everybody's hungry. So you've seen these talks
span a wide arc, but that is also because the
topic itself for this symposium does, AI-ready
data and knowledge, right? So please come back after lunch to
see the second part of this arc, and
looking forward to that.
I'll call this session to order in about two minutes, and then
I'll go ahead and
introduce the talk,
Gerwin, and just give the title and then turn it over to you.
When we get to five minutes, you'll
get a little signal from me in two minutes, and then we can't go over.
So at zero minutes, you're done and then for questions, if you agree we have time
for one or two. Perfect.
I think it will be 10 to 15 minutes.
Oh, great. Okay, perfect. That's excellent. Were you supposed to be 15 or 10?
Do you remember whether-
I think it was 10 minutes.
minutes.
What?
Would you sit over there?
I can sit over there.
Move my stuff over there.
Thank you.
Hello, everybody.
We
are going to start on time,
so that we can stay on schedule.
If you don't know where you are,
which could be true for all those still on jet lag,
this is the Mobilizing Data to AI-Ready Knowledge: Infrastructure
for Multimodal Biodiversity. This is session two, so
hopefully many of you were at session one. If not, great session.
Not to make you feel bad about it,
but we're really excited about having a slate of talks.
For this session, I'm going to introduce our first speaker coming up here, and
Gerwin Kasparek will be talking about mobilizing and integrating extracted
information from the literature. Is that right?
Into a
biodiversity data ecosystem, the BioFID approach. Take it away, Gerwin.
Okay.
Oh, you were my time.
Great.
Hello. Good afternoon, everyone.
I think the mic's working fine.
Okay.
Oh, sorry. Let me move you over to-
One more thing.
Do I need this?
Okay.
All right.
Ready when you are.
Okay.
So good afternoon.
Today, as a librarian and biologist, I
talk about mobilizing and integrating data from
biodiversity literature,
and the approach that our Project BioFID has chosen to tackle
this challenge.
Let's start by looking at some sources of biodiversity data
and why literature is so valuable.
Okay.
I want to compare three major sources of biodiversity data.
First, collection metadata from museums or herbaria.
These span centuries, are of very high quality, but are
limited in volume. Then citizen science data.
Here we got large quantities of observation, but only from
recent years.
Only literature data combines historical depth
and high volume.
Yet it's the hardest to access because it's locked in
unstructured text.
So literature is our focus and a huge opportunity for
mobilization.
Continue.
Extracting data from the literature isn't straightforward, and here's
why. The data is buried in natural language,
often unstructured.
It's frequently in non-English languages like German, Latin,
Hungarian, and so on.
The literature is full of abbreviations that are only
understandable to insiders.
The content is often following peculiar,
subject-specific conventions, such as indented
keys.
And sometimes the physical condition of the paper or the
printing is poor.
Initiatives like the DeZentes roadmap,
discussed in a parallel symposium regrettably,
stress the need for action.
Without mobilizing this data, we're missing decades and
centuries of critical biodiversity knowledge.
Now, what do we mean by mobilization?
The term emerged in the 2000s, originally tied
to specimen metadata from collections, and in the
2010s, it expanded to literature data.
For us, mobilization means taking analog,
unstructured information, including
printed natural language texts, and converting it
into fair digital formats. Findable,
accessible, interoperable, and reusable.
This isn't just digitization. It's making data
actionable for research and conservation.
So let's take a concrete example, a text from the 18th
century, which was later prepared by Spielger.
The original German passage describes occurrences
and traits of an orchid species in the region of my
hometown, Frankfurt.
From this single sentence, we could extract numerous
pieces of structured data, and we could link them to
resources such as GBIF, Wikidata, to ontologies,
to trade databases, and so on.
To just take two examples, an occurrence record.
Coeloglossum viride observed near Eschenheimer Tor in Frankfurt
in May 1729
in a meadow habitat. Or we could extract a trait record
from this.
The species has leaves in which the trait leaf width can
have two values, narrow or broad.
This shows the richness of literature data,
but automating this extraction is still a challenge.
Fully automated extraction is not yet reliable,
although some people are very optimistic about that.
So can
AI help here? On top, you see the correct
occurrence record from the example.
Now, here's what a current large language model extracted from the
text.
It got the taxon and habitat right, but it hallucinated the
references. Wrong GBIF ID, wrong Wikidata
ID.
Regarding the name, GBIF currently considers Coeloglossum
viride to be the accepted name, while World Flora
Online states that Dactylorhiza viridis is correct.
Important, the GBIF ID returned by the LLM has
nothing to do with either name.
Even with an improved prompt,
which explicitly requests careful check of the ID,
the LLM still replied with an incorrect GBIF ID.
The repeated requests
have unsettled the LLM so much that it no longer dares to
provide an ID for the toponym.
This tells us AI can extract structure,
but verification against authoritative sources is
essential. We can't trust raw LLM outputs
alone.
This is where BioFit comes in.
Our specialized information service has three core aims:
to mobilize data from Central European biodiversity
literature,
to provide software tools for text mining, and to
digitize literature with a focus on the 20th century,
where we have enormous gaps.
We are a collaboration between the Senckenberg Nature
Research, the text technology of Goethe University Frankfurt,
and the Senckenberg Library, where I come from.
And BioFit is funded by the German Research Foundation, DFG.
How are we doing this?
We are building a large corpus of biodiversity texts from Central Europe,
including some in-copyright works for which we were
able to get the necessary rights.
We apply generic natural language processing tools,
NLP, and adapt them for biodiversity.
We also develop domain-specific resources like ontologies
to standardize data elements,
and we're exploring AI, such as LLMs, as far as
this offers added value.
So where do we stand?
There will soon be a large corpus with semantic annotations.
The corpus is searchable via our Unified Corpus
Explorer, UCE,
and we're carrying out experiments with
information extraction from the annotated text.
Looking ahead, we plan to do the following.
Expand the corpus further.
Optimize NLP pipelines, for example, improving
co-reference resolution to link entities across larger
documents.
Then move information extraction from research to
production
to combine data from text tables and images.
The keyword here is multimodal information extraction.
And then to structure extracted data in graph-suitable and
machine-actionable formats like RDF or
OWL. Our overarching goal is to contribute to
a biodiversity knowledge graph ecosystem, which is a
powerful way to link and query complex data.
To make our data
interoperable, we rely on standards.
These are some generic standards like
UIMA for NLP pipelines,
OWL for ontologies, or RDF/SPARQL for graph
data.
The choice of UIMA as a standard that is not widely
used is motivated by the fact that UIMA also
enables highly complex annotations and that
well-structured pipelines can be built.
And then there are domain-specific standards like
Darwin Core for occurrence data, of course, or taxonomic backbone
from GBIF or the Catalog of Life.
These standards will ensure our outputs are usable
and reusable by the community.
Our key reusable components include the
DUI, the Docker Unified UIMA Interface, an
advanced interface for natural language processing and annotation.
Then the UCE, the Unified Corpus Explorer for semantic search.
There are the ontologies like, among others, the
Chilopoda or anatomy ontology, or some
EnvO extensions and translations.
And mobilized data for a biodiversity knowledge graph.
All of these are open source and are available for reuse,
or in the case of the knowledge graph, will be freely available
once they have reached the necessary maturity.
So to wrap up, biodiversity literature is a goldmine of
data, but the data is locked in unstructured text.
BioFit mobilizes this data using NLP, AI,
and standards to create fair, actionable knowledge.
We've built tools and resources to support this, and we're scaling up
to contribute to the knowledge graph universe.
You can learn more at the BioFit website or contact us directly.
Thank you very much. Now we're happy to take your questions.
Don't let me scare you.
Any questions?
Melissa.
Ah, you win the prize.
Yeah, this sounds really interesting.
I've been doing some similar work at Q, looking at
extracting
data on medicinal plants and phytochemistry from
open text corpora. But, so I was wondering what kind of traits
you're looking at extracting, because I think
some of the questions or approaches you were talking about depend on
specifically what you're trying to extract along with the taxon.
The most important kind of data we try to
extract, which is in the focus
of most of our researchers in the target group, is
occurrence data.
But of course, we also want to extend this to other data, and trait data
is somehow the second most important
area of data.
And we will have to involve ontologies,
like plant ontology and so on,
to extract
these trait data. But we are not
that far in our studies that we can say, "Oh, we
will have
a large number of leaf width trait data for
10,000 species or so." This is an
evolving
project, so we cannot say at the moment what will be the end
product.
Oh, did you have a question, Hilmar?
Oh, did Hilmar ask?
Yeah.
Okay. If I
may.
You may.
I didn't see the mic.
Just please hold it closer to your mouth so people online can hear.
Okay. So, you showed an example
comparing the ground truth to what the LLM
creates from information in the
record.
I guess I'm curious, what are your plans
for building a labeled training data set?
We have generated a first training set in the
last project phase, and we'll extend this further in the
next time.
But
I
cannot say that this will be a corpus of this
size or so. I think we will have a
step-by-step approach, see if
some training corpus is large enough to give
good results, or if we need more training, a larger corpus,
to get results which are sufficient.
Great.
Thank you.
Thank you, Gerwin.
Wonderful.
Our next speaker will be Karolina Kurczewska. I hope I got that close to right.
You'll correct me.
I'll take my microphone.
Yeah, great. We're talking about Camera Trap DB, right?
That's true.
Great. Awesome. Take it away.
Let me help you out here getting the presentation up.
Yeah.
Yeah. You bet.
Do we have a pointer, or?
We do, yeah. It's right here. And it's this little button.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, great.
Very well.
Oh, hi. Hello.
That's on.
Is that right?
Yes.
Take it away.
Thank you. Okay. Hello, everyone.
My name is Karolina Kurczewska.
I'm a data manager at the Polish node of GBIF.
I work at Open Science Conservation Fund, where we develop Trapper open source
software for camera trapping data, and I am also part of the team that
maintains Camera Trap DB data standard.
And today, I would like to tell you about a little bit of what's coming in the
future of the Camera Trap DB standard.
So, just a short introduction. Camera Trap DB standard is a
standard for exchange of camera trapping data in accordance with the FAIR
principles.
It was first introduced in a paper published in 2023.
This QR code will take you to the paper if you're not yet familiar with it.
And just as a short background for those of you who are maybe not very familiar
with the standard, the Camera Trap data package contains
four files. One of them, data package JSON, contains metadata, and
that's both package metadata, which means description of the package structure
itself, and the project metadata, so project name, description,
identifiers, list of all the contributors, and so on.
And then there are three data files.
Deployments table contains all of the deployments, meaning the
placement of a camera trap in the field in a particular location for a defined
period of time. Then there's the media table.
It contains all the media, meaning photographs and videos that
were created as part of this project, and every media object is connected to its
deployment. And then there's observations table, and that contains
consensus observations for information about what was
observed in every media and in every event that was identified with this project.
And every observation links to its media and to its deployment.
CamtrapDP standard has been adopted by the global camera trapping community.
For some time now, it's possible to publish CamtrapDP packages
directly into GBIF without the need to map them to Darwin Core.
And to browse these datasets, you can go to our GBIF hosted portal,
WildAlbum. That's the code that will take you there. That's the address.
And as for a couple of days ago when I was making this presentation, there were
25 datasets together comprising almost a million animal
occurrences, and this number keep growing.
So I would like to focus on a couple of aspects of CamtrapDP.
First, it is based on frictionless data framework, which means that it's easily
extendable. If you have some information that you want to express in your data
package, but there are no fields for it, you can easily add a new table.
All it takes is you need to provide a schema, and then if that schema is valid,
your data package will be valid. So that's a good thing because
it allows everyone to include all the information they want in a data package.
But it also creates a little bit of a problem because if everybody starts just
extending the data package the way they want to, then we lose the interoperability
of the entire thing.
Observation table already contains some fields that allow us to
inform about AI-generated results.
So there's a field called classification method, which can
be either human or machine, and there's a field called classified by, which
can contain the name of a human that classified the resource or
a name of the AI model that classified the resource.
However, in the last couple of years, the scope in which we use AI
in the analysis of this data has changed a lot.
So it's possible that those two fields are no longer enough to
actually
express this information.
And CamtrapDP was designed for traditional camera trap research, by which I mean
using store-bought camera traps to monitor medium and large mammals.
But there are other kinds of research as well that have similar structure that
could also benefit from the standard like this.
And I would like to tell you about a couple of projects that reevaluated CamtrapDP
standard for the needs of their own data.
First is the Safe and Sound project.
It was published by Wild Labs in something that is charmingly called Boring
Fund, and the project produced a report that you can read in full under
this code. And the purpose of this project was to, as I said, to
evaluate whether CamtrapDP is suitable for sharing
bioacoustic data.
And here are some of the conclusions.
The main idea is that, yes, CamtrapDP standard can be used to
express bioacoustic data as well because the structure of data is
quite similar, but there are some changes that would be required for it to be a
good fit for this data. So we would have to add some terms in the
deployments table to describe acoustic sensors.
Right now we have fields like camera model or camera height, so those fields
would have to be renamed to device model, device height, so it can accommodate
acoustic sensors as well as cameras. Does this work? Yes. Okay.
We would need to also add way to describe
recording schedules. There can
be diverse recording schedules in traditional camera trapping as well, but
typically it's all motion activated.
Something moves in front of the camera, then it takes a picture.
With acoustic recording, there are some more diverse recording
schedules. So the standard needs a way to describe that in detail.
There are some fields that would be required to add to the media table, because
right now the media table has been designed to describe, as I said, images and
videos. So fields like maybe frequency range or something that are typical
for audio data would have to be added as well.
And another proposition from the Safe and Sound project was that we should add
assertions table that would enable adding different kinds of measurements to this
data package. So this assertions table is an analog to
measurement or fact extension from Darwin Core Archive or from assertions table
from
Darwin Core data package. So that was the proposition to include it in
CamtrapDP as well.
And the other group that reevaluated CamtrapDP for their purposes
is InsectAI. InsectAI is a cost action. It's a big project.
It's over 500 participants.
And within this InsectAI, there is working group three.
And among the tasks of this group is to devise a standard for sharing data and
metadata from automated insect monitoring.
This code will take you to the website of InsectAI, so we can find out more
about this fantastic project.
And as I said, they also reevaluated the value of CamtrapDP
for the data for visual insect monitoring.
And the results were the following. It is a good fit.
However, some changes to the standard are necessary.
I hope you're starting to see a pattern here.
So we would need to extend some vocabularies and add some fields to better
accommodate insect data. For example, in deployments table, we have a
field called bait use because we often use some kind of bait in traditional camera
trapping. But in insect monitoring, it's often light or pheromones that are used
to attract insects. So we would have to rename this field attractant use to cover a
wider array of possibilities there.
more robust hardware description would be required to cover insect monitoring,
because in traditional camera trapping, you have those store-bought cameras, fairly
simple models. But in insect monitoring, there are often some custom-made
hardwares that are very interesting, so it would require a little bit more
fields to describe them properly.
A way to describe more diverse recording schedule would
also be helpful for the insect monitoring community.
And another
suggestion was that we should be able to express all classifications that are made
for the resource, not just what we currently have in the standard, a table with
consensus for every resource and event.
That was part of the monitoring project.
And the last piece of input from this...
That's a summary. So the last thing I wanted to tell you about is that the
suggestion was to add a table for models, because currently there's
only a way to have a
name of the model, and with the amount of models we use these
days, it's just not enough. So there was a suggestion to add a models table that
would enable us to describe used AI models in more detail.
Okay. And the traditional camera trapping community has also been giving some
feedback to the standard. For a couple of years, they have been using it now, and
this mostly comes from my experience of developing Trapper and talking to Trapper
users. So there are two points that this feedback converges onto.
First is that there is a need to share all identifications made for a resource,
like I mentioned before. When we have a single picture or video, we don't
run just one model on it. There is often a pipeline of different AI models that
look at the same resource and come to similar or different conclusions.
A way is needed to express all of those observations, all of those results,
not just the final consensus one.
And also more detail for describing the models, more than just a name is
necessary.
All right. So,
to sum this up,
CamtrapDB has been adopted by the community.
It has proven to be a good way of sharing camera trap data in a way that
is according to FAIR principles. There's a growing number of tools to
visualize this data, to analyze it, to share and publish this data so other
communities, not only traditional camera trapping community, could benefit from
a standard like this and from this whole suite of tools.
Feedback from different thematic communities highlights similar needs.
All this feedback highlights basically the changes that happened in the
data analysis pipelines in the last couple of years.
So the direction in which we need to change the standard is really
clear if we take all of those feedbacks into account.
CamtrapDB is a good fit, not just for traditional camera traps, but
for any data that comes from stationary sensors.
So it could be
rigs for monitoring insects or audio recorders or camera traps.
The structure of this data is very similar, so they can all benefit from the same
standard. And also, there's a lot of multimodal monitoring these days when you have
both camera traps and audio recorders.
So having this shared standard for all this data would also be beneficial to enable
sharing these multimodal datasets as one
entity.
So we will continue these works. The Safer and Sounder project that
was funded by NLBIF will start December this year, and the purpose of this
project is to incorporate feedback from the Safe and Sound project into the
standard. So that's something I'll be working on.
Insect AI is also still happening, so we'll be now working on
incorporating this feedback into the standard.
CamtrapDB is developed under Tadwik.
There's a website, and it's all happening on GitHub.
So if you want to stay on top of it, if you want to be a part of the discussion,
I encourage you all to visit our GitHub, see the issues, and take part in the
discussion as well.
Thank you.
Questions.
Rob has a question.
I'll be
mercifully concise so we have time for more questions.
Okay.
So, CamtrapDB,
does that have a direct
way to interchange back to the Darwin Core?
You could do it through a Humboldt extension, right?
Yes. There is.
Has a mapping been achieved?
Yeah. I have it.
Okay, good. Yeah.
So among those tools that I mentioned for standard, there is an R
library, and one of its
functions is to direct to translate CamtrapDB datasets into
Darwin Core. That's also what happens when they are published to GBIF, because
when we publish CamtrapDB datasets to GBIF, all the animal
observations from CamtrapDB are translated into Darwin Core
occurrences. So there is a way to do that.
There's a direct mapping, and it's available for everyone in this R library.
Very well.
Good on you.
Anybody else?
Is anybody using CamtrapDB?
Oh.
It's not enough of you.
Thank you.
Hello.
Since the CamtrapDB, all the terms
are more complicated than the original one or traditional ones you
use as core and extension thing. Do you have any
workflow or method to train the field workers or
transcribers to
get used to use these terms or to learn all about the
CamtrapDB thing?
So I think the general idea is not necessarily that the field workers will
construct the packages with all the four files themselves.
There are different softwares for managing camera trap data, and the idea is that
the softwares are compatible with CamtrapDB.
So field workers and people who do the data analysis input data into their
software, and then the software generates CamtrapDB. That's the general idea.
And there is a growing number of softwares. Trapper supports that.
Agouti supports CamtrapDB as well.
So if you're looking for a software for camera trap, it's worth to have a look if
it supports CamtrapDB or not. And other softwares are
incorporating that as well. So I think the idea is that the software does it for
you. Also, many of the terms in CamTrap-DP are either related or
directly taken from Darwin Core, so we're trying to keep it as compatible as
possible. CamTrap-DP can be thought of as just a special case of
Darwin Core specifically for describing camera trap methodology.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Very well.
Good talk.
Thanks a lot. That was great.
We are now going to have a virtual presentation by Jenna Kline.
Also, will the 2:45 speaker who's talking on causal
Bayesian schemas, come see one of the symposium organizers so we can get you
mic'd up.
Tim.
Great, Tim. Awesome. Yeah. Head back to the room here at this
point, and they'll get you mic'd up for your presentation. Wonderful.
Great talks.
Really appreciate the talk from
Karolina, and let's go on to our one virtual
presentation in our whole symposium, I think.
We had thought that it was possible that Tanya Berger-Wolf would give five
presentations in our
session, but it turns out that she is not giving this talk, and this is a virtual.
We'll see how it goes. It's taking a little while to open up here.
And we could've tried opening this before we came in here.
Oh.
Hi, everyone. My name is Jenna Kline.
I am a postdoc at MIT, and today I'll be
presenting FAIR Square Drones: An AI-Ready Standard for
Cross-Domain Wildlife Drone Datasets.
Ecological data is increasingly multimodal and
multiscalar, drawing from fields of ecology, AI,
robotics, remote sensing, and computer systems.
And realizing the potential of AI to infer insight from these
very heterogeneous data sources has historically
required close collaboration between ecology
and computer science,
and now systems and robotics. In line
with the theme of the conference, Robot-Ready Biodiversity Data
Standards,
I propose extending this framing beyond
AI plus ecology to robotics and computer
systems.
We need expertise from all of these fields to design the
infrastructure to collect, possess, process,
coordinate, and act on ecological observations.
Fieldwork is a team sport, and ecological datasets are
collective achievements.
I think this photograph illustrates that point particularly well.
This is a photo from the 2025 Wild Drone
Hackathon in Kenya. This is me over here.
This hackathon brought together ecologists who understood the
species and the ecological research questions,
local experts and partners who deeply understand the
landscape and animal interactions,
drone pilots and roboticists who operate the system, build custom
platforms, and computer scientists who process
and annotate the data.
After collecting all of our data in the field, we wanted to be
able to reuse each other's data to build
on each other's tools and developments.
But the students quickly realized that having access to the
files was not really the same as being able to use them across
disciplines.
These datasets embody an enormous collective
investment of expertise, building relationships, time,
and resources.
So preserving enough context for that investment to support
more than one
particular paper, computer vision task, or
discipline is vital.
One of the challenges is that each discipline has
slightly different metadata requirements for reuse.
For ecology, that includes what was observed, where was it
observed, when, and under what data collection protocol.
For robotics, we would want to know what was the drone platform used,
what trajectory was flown, what was the control mode and sensor configuration.
In computer vision, what labels exist and how were they
produced?
The data is often the same, but as this image shows,
what constitutes sufficient documentation for
reuse means something different in each research community.
So to solve this challenge, we as a group proposed coming
up with what would be a metadata standard to allow computer
scientists, ecologists, and roboticists all working in the field
be able to reuse each other's datasets.
But we didn't want to fall into a typical trap, which I
think this
comic illustrates particularly well.
We're not proposing a replacement for existing standards
these research communities already use.
We propose an integration layer connecting
existing ecological and AI-ready standards,
which then fill the gaps needed to describe drone sensing
systems.
So a couple of the community standards that we extend and build
on is the
FAIR
and AI-ready principles
Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable,
as well as the
Darwin Core and Humboldt Extension.
We draw on all of these to define a cross-domain standard
for drone-based wildlife datasets.
And the standard encodes the platform, the mission,
the sensor, the annotation, and the provenance metadata
in a machine-readable dataset card.
So this is a
high-level example of what the dataset card looks like.
The event captures
each mission
details, what observations were made, what the habitat was like,
what permits were used, what the drone platform was, and the mission plan.
And then the occurrence captures the frame-level
telemetry, as well as what images were collected at
each time.
And so together, this makes the data
usable across multiple domains.
The FAIR Drones dataset card schema has nine main
components,
and this provides a checklist covering all the relevant metadata
to make it useful across disciplines.
For example, an ecologist may not think to
capture the sensor and calibration, or a roboticist
may not think to capture the class balance and difficulty.
So this provides a tool to ensure that the
data that you have access to is captured in a way
to make it useful for people across disciplines
who may want to use it.
We provide a worked example from the CABR,
the Kenyan Animal Behavior Recognition dataset, that is
FAIR Drones compliant, and you can access this on Hugging Face
at this link.
We also provide a Drone Dataset Card Quick
Start Guide
to help make the process a bit easier to implement,
including instructions for what is the minimally
viable data that's needed to be included, all the way down
to very detailed checklists.
In addition to the CABR dataset study, we also provide
five more case studies that are FAIR Square Drone compliant,
spanning multi-view drone swarms, 3D
construction, lion behaviors,
and humpback whale tracks combining RGB and thermal
imagery. We intentionally selected case
studies that would span a wide variety of
ecological, computer vision, and
robotics challenges, and used this to stress test
the standard to make sure that we weren't missing anything,
and making sure that this was flexible enough to meet
the multitude of different
datasets that drones are used to collect.
But we can expand on this. Drones aren't the only sensors
that we would like to use to study animals in their natural
habitats. But how can we leverage all
of the data streams available to us?
Drones are one piece of the puzzle.
Monitoring at scale requires cross-modal
coordination.
AI-driven animal ecology closes the control loop to
enable adaptive sampling. First focused on
drone,
and in other smart sensors.
But we can also apply the same tools
to unlock new capabilities to coordinate across sensors.
However, to leverage this, we need to make sure that the
data is usable and cross-referenceable across these
heterogeneous sensors.
To start to explore some of these ideas, we've extended the FAIR
Square Drones dataset standard to support
multi and cross-modal sensor deployments and datasets, which
we have used to publish the Smart Wilds
dataset.
The FAIR Square Drone schema was used to record all of the
sensor settings, the field notes, all the way through
annotation,
noting which was manually annotated versus what was
AI-generated. And critically, with the metadata to synchronize
the observations both temporally and spatially.
So in summary, FAIR Square Drones enables
reusable observations, coordinated sensors, adaptive
collection, and promotes the interdisciplinary
collaboration and innovation for animal
ecology studies.
Thank you very much for your attention today.
We would love your feedback
on the proposed dataset standard.
You can find the documentation and preprint at these links,
and don't hesitate to reach out if you have any questions or comments.
Thank you.
Hi, everyone.
Okay, you guys.
Let's see.
We have a couple minutes.
Yeah, we have a couple minutes. I'm supposed to speak into the mic.
And that's good news. We wanted to just give you guys a couple
of-
... thoughts about how we're going to wrap up this session.
We're going to invite all the speakers up to the front of the stage,
and we will basically have a couple of
questions that we've come up with as the symposium organizers that we'll lead
off the discussion session with. And then at
that point, we're going to turn it over to you guys to help
ask questions to any of the speakers about any of the topics that touch on this
symposium theme. We really hope that you guys were the ones to take over
asking questions. We actually came up with 11 questions.
We
trimmed it down to nine. So if you don't
develop your own questions, you'll have to bear with the questions that we came up
with. So we'd love to hear your thoughts and input.
We really want it to be an engaging session where you guys can talk to
us and share your thoughts. It could be a question, it could be a comment, it could
be a blue sky idea. We want to hear it.
We want to make sure that you have a chance to interact more fully with all of the
speakers. And if you would like, I think Omar and I talked about if any one
speaker or audience wants to come grab a drink with the organizers, we'd
love to hang out and talk more after the day winds down.
So I think I'll leave it there and maybe just turn it back over
to David. Dave, anything to add?
So we have a couple of minutes, and the reason we have a couple of minutes is we're
trying to keep all the speakers on the same schedule so that people moving from
room to room don't come in in the middle of a conversation that they wanted to be
in at the beginning.
So just
how many folks, other than this session, how many of you attended an
AI-focused session so far?
Okay. As expected.
What are your frustrations so far?
Or are you finding solutions that were interesting
and before now
you hadn't thought of? Or what is missing from this conversation, either in
the room so far, or just generally with
the use of AI
and
AI-ready data?
Tiny question for you. You should all have something on the tip of your tongue.
Any thoughts?
Hi.
I've really been looking for solutions about how can we
persuade the data providers to believe
if we provide our data to the system
and it was used by AI agents,
our
contributes are still acknowledged properly.
And I don't really feel like we've seen a lot of
mentions on this idea and a lot of suggestions, but I'm
not sure. I haven't really seen a strong,
valid
solution till now, but would glad to hear
other thoughts.
Yeah. So citations,
acknowledgement.
Does anybody else have a similar concern, or are these thoughts relevant to
what you're doing?
Nobody else is worried about getting credit if your data comes through an
AI?
Sure. But you're French. You go, "Eh."
And it--
Yeah.
Absolutely.
It's a great way to sort of start.
Perfect. All right. Thank you.
Over to you, Tim.
Yeah. Mic check.
Yeah. Oh, mic check.
Is there a time person?
No. You're timing. Okay, I'll look to you.
Hello, everyone.
So I'm Tim Almen. The
sound of my voice has been all over the place while I'm up here.
I work out of Carleton University in Canada.
I'm going to be telling a story from America, but I am a Canadian who works
with the associate members of the EU, so
that's great.
Thanks. The work that I'm going to be talking about today emerges from a
collaboration between Canada and Germany.
We've been collaborating for about three years.
There are four names on this slide, including my own, Robert Fuchtstuckl,
Filiz Aleri, and Lars Voet, but the larger collaboration
includes more than 50 people from
across the world, really.
So today I'm going to be talking to you about representing causality using a
data schema. There's a GitHub repo if you want to follow along.
There's a super messy example using the schema, and also links to the
schema itself.
So I want to start with a story. I told you I was going to talk about America.
This is the Bandon Marsh in Oregon,
and it doesn't look like a marsh right now.
It's a farm because at one point, this marsh was drained to make a
farm. The US Fish & Wildlife Service owns all of this land,
and they engaged in a restoration project for this patch of land.
And if anyone knows something about restoration,
if you're going to make a farm, you want to get the water away from it.
And if you're going to restore a wetland, you want to introduce water back to it.
So they dammed up the drainage channels, and water came back to the
Bandon Marsh. It looked like this beautiful brown patch of
wetland.
Everything was hunky-dory. The marsh was flooding again, which
is great for biodiversity. It's especially great for
specific types of biodiversity. It is great for the salt marsh
mosquito.
The people who were restoring this land knew that it would promote
mosquito habitat. They knew this guy would be coming back in swarms.
They didn't quite know how much it would become a
mosquito habitat.
So there was a public health advisory.
A local golf course had to close because there were swarms and swarms of
mosquitoes flooding the golf course.
The US Fish and Wildlife Service had to sample all of the ponds of standing water
to figure out how many mosquito larvae there were. There were lots.
They had to call in excavators again
To revise the drainage of this area.
Essentially, they had gotten a little bit too ambitious.
The tides were flowing in, but they weren't flowing out again.
So the area was staying wet with standing water the whole time.
This illustrates a problem in restoration and conservation,
and that problem is something that others have talked about.
We work in silos, and so there is a large amount of
restoration ecology, especially wetland restoration.
There's a large amount of knowledge on mosquito ecology, but the two do not
communicate. They are not interoperable.
These knowledges are locked
in the literature, and they remain disconnected from one another.
So the challenge that EcoWeaver has been trying to solve is how do we connect
this,
and how do we share it with practitioners, people on the ground, in a way that is
meaningful and useful to them?
Part of this quest has been thinking about different ways to approach structured
data. This way is something that I came up with while I was
on parental leave with my kid and thought, "Hey, this would be a great
book to read." It's based on a book by Phyllis Illari and Federico
Russo called "Causality," and what they propose in this
is an idea in the philosophy of science that causality is not
one arrow from one thing to another.
There are a mosaic of ways of understanding causality, and
all of those are at play in some way.
At the same time, I also discovered LinkML, and I started talking a lot more with
Chris Mungall and the group at the Lawrence Berkeley National Lab.
And that led to the creation of the Causal Mosaic Schema, which is the icon on
the far side there.
And the schema is a labeled property graph schema, which
I don't think I need to define for this audience, but the idea of a labeled
property graph is that the nodes and the edges can have
properties assigned to them. So a relationship
between ditch plugging process, which is a
name for the process when you plug the ditches on a farm to restore the wetland,
that is associated with an increased abundance of the salt marsh
mosquito.
And what that looks like in JSON is something like this.
You can have the entity term grounded in an ontology.
In this case, it's an ontology of ecological management terms that we
have also created and been working on.
So the ditch plugging process is the plain language and then a curie
associated with it, and the edge can also have
an ecosystem context. In this case, it was the marsh
ecosystem type,
and they can be connected to a node.
So this is just a brief illustration.
So if we go back to our mosquito example, we can find in 1995, Kramer
et al. had a paper that talked about how to
alleviate the production of
the salt marsh mosquito in a restored area,
and that's by tidal enhancement. So you increase the amount of tidal
turnover, the capacity of the tide to flood and drain from the land.
What we could do is annotate this claim
with the Causal Mosaic, and that would lead to a series of nodes and edges.
Some pretty straightforward stuff, but it gets to be powerful when you expand
it to thousands of studies. So the restoration of full tidal action
increases tidal circulation, which is a property of the marsh,
that could be measured, sometimes we call that hydroperiod,
which causes a decreased abundance.
The increasing the circulation causes the larvae to decrease,
and that
decreased frequency of herbicide application is something that the Kramer paper was
concerned with. Not really relevant to our current example, but nonetheless appears
in the graph.
So the Causal Mosaic has rich detail on its nodes.
Like I mentioned before, we have an ontology-grounded entity type, a
measured attribute which applies to a taxa that might be
documented here because, as Lars likes to remind me,
you're not actually talking about the taxa, you're talking about the abundance of
the taxa or some property of it in this particular area.
So we concentrate on three main properties
for the causal nodes: the entity type,
which could be limited to a taxa, an environmental variable, a
management process, or an environmental process,
and then an entity term connected to that, and a state or change qualifier.
The important thing here is that the nodes are not
a thing in and of themselves. The nodes describe a change, change
in something.
Sometimes that change is everything staying the same, but we can get to that
later. That's a little bit of complexity in there.
But the key idea is that causality is a relationship
between a change in one thing and a change, or a staying the same, in another
thing.
The measured attribute, again, describes taxa, and applied to is
for the target scope of a given process or a variable.
The edges are much richer.
We have a
bunch of details. 11 different causal predicates can be used on an
edge.
I think there are 67 fields in total, and
they describe 16 different causal features and eight philosophical accounts
in three families. You're not meant to read this.
It's just meant to
convey that there's a lot of information.
That breaks down into four discrete layers.
So the first layer is claim strength and the linguistic expression, and what this
is designed for is we are not evaluating the claims that
authors make, we are transcribing them into the Causal Mosaic.
So it's not up to this schema to say whether or not the claim is justified.
It's the claim was made in a peer-reviewed study.
The second layer is that philosophical account classification, which generally
breaks down into mechanistic classifications or difference-making
accounts
And then the causal features are 16 different features that a given
causal claim can have. These range from strength to
context specificity.
And then the evidential basis is where we talk about what type of study
led to this finding.
We also, of course, include full provenance information metadata on the
article and the annotator.
I should say too, and I'll talk about this in more detail, because of the scope of
our project, this necessitates LLM assistance in annotation because there
are simply too many papers. Right now, we have a graduate student who's working on
papers. She has gotten through two in the last two months, so this
is very intense work.
If we do the mosquito example alone, we end up with a
hairball of 14 articles, 238 nodes.
This is small potatoes compared to doing a corpus of thousands of
articles.
So it's nice to look at, and we love making hairballs as graph people,
but how can this be useful? And this is where we turn to the output
side. I come to this work as a practitioner
first. My PhD was on community practice of
restoration, and I'm really more comfortable in the mud than I am in rooms
like this. So I wanted to make something that would be useful to
practitioners who are making decisions on the ground.
So we imagine four outputs from the Causal Mosaic.
The first is an evidence gap map,
and this is a typical type of map of the evidence
that the conservation sector has borrowed from healthcare, where
it shows the strength of evidence.
On the x-axis could be a particular
technique
or a particular aspect of the ecosystem, and on the y-axis could be
another thing.
A better example is you could have the restoration technique along the x-axis and
then the ecosystem where it's applied along the y, and it would show you the
strength of evidence and illustrate where the gaps might be.
The second is a more direct decision support tool. Thanks.
This is a fuzzy cognitive map, and this was first proposed by
Bart Kosko way back in the '70s.
And it has been extended and expanded since, but it is a very basic
decision-making model,
where the relative proportion of the edges are what's important, not
necessarily the values themselves.
But the Causal Mosaic can translate fairly directly into a
map like this, so you could specify what different components of your
ecosystem you're interested in and create a fuzzy cognitive map, and then you could
run some tests to see what happens when you change certain
parameters, what happens to other parameters.
We can get a little bit more detailed
and create a Bayesian belief network out of parts of the Causal Mosaic.
And for this, the Causal Mosaic is helpful in forming the metal model for the
Bayesian belief network. So that means the structure, what the different
parameters are, and also for providing some information for the
priors in that network. So some idea of the range of
variation that's been documented in the studies that could help you
inform priors. It's not a direct one-to-one.
You couldn't programmatically make a Bayesian belief network.
It does require some intervention, but
it nonetheless gets you halfway there.
The fourth output that we envision
is a retrieval-augmented generation type
approach, where you pair an LLM with the hairball, and
the LLM has the capability to construct searches and
provide a meaningful output to a practitioner who asks a
natural language query.
Lots of limitations because it's a big, ambitious project.
So this is a meta-model, not the parameters.
We aren't really pulling in all of that granular data.
You'll notice we're not talking about effect size.
We're not talking about P values. We're not talking
about the statistical tests that these papers contain.
So that means it can't really provide a fully parameterized
model. That's a direction we hope to grow into.
This focuses on the Western academic science tradition,
especially in discussing what experiment types led to a particular causal
link.
So that's a big gap. We are working on that.
We're having a gathering in Jena, Germany next week, where we have a lot of
people coming to talk about traditional ecological knowledge and how that might
factor into causality.
And importantly, it focuses on peer-reviewed literature.
Within conservation and restoration, there's a lot of information contained in
management reports, which often don't use the same kind of experimental
structure that we see in the literature.
So we haven't included those yet, and part of the reason is that the
literature is comparatively easy to search and easy to
download depending on how you do it.
So it's easier for us to pilot this model,
change it in ways that might make it a little better, more effective.
And the final one is that this relies on LLM annotation.
I could do a whole separate presentation on that pipeline and the question of
what have you seen that's kind of sticking with you.
We have seen a lot of examples of LLM annotation.
I will just say briefly that I would love to talk to people who are struggling with
that because I have found some ways that do work effectively to ground
answers in ontologies and to avoid hallucinating identifiers.
So we can definitely talk about that after.
But those are the limitations. That's the repo. That's my email.
Really interested in collaborating and talking more about this. Thank you.
Great talk. That was awesome.
Great.
Thanks a lot for that talk. Hey, Dave, I'm going to pass this over to you for
questions.
Oh,
I have two questions.
The first one is, it's only the causality relation.
You don't have any subtypes of causality.
What do you mean by that?
You can have necessary causation.
So, a cause might be present for the effect to happen, but it does not trigger the
effect on its own.
Yep.
Or you can have the necessary sufficient causation, or you can have
the type of causation versus what's called token causation-
Yeah
... which is the difference between type and individual.
Yeah.
Right? So that's why I'm just asking, there's only the one
causation link in the model?
No, there are 11 different labels for the predicate
type, and then there are the eight philosophical
causation
explanations, and those include things like the INUS condition.
Those include things like necessity or sufficiency.
So all of that will be detailed.
The way that we display graphs is with one line and one word
above it, and that's unfortunate, but we couldn't possibly
display 60 lines of text on each edge.
But each edge will contain rich information on the nature of causality
that is described in the article.
Okay.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, but that means that there's no sub-properties which
are different types of causation.
You don't have-
Yes, there are sub-properties that are different types-
Okay
... of causations, and there can be multiple edges between nodes.
So
as different studies-
Yeah, that's true
... look at different aspects of causation, those edges could add up.
Okay.
The second question is,
do you see a need
to package up these
causality graphs into specific
sub-graphs?
Do you want to be able to
have
a graph where you follow this A causes B, B
causes C, C causes D, and package that up as one thing because
it's a meaningful unit?
Yes, absolutely.
Okay.
Those are my two questions.
The answer is yes.
Thank you.
If you didn't get a question answered as clearly and completely as you want, please
stick around for the discussion. Find speakers afterwards.
Come hang out with the symposium organizers, grab a drink.
I am really, really pleased to have Brigitte and Martin presenting the last
talk of our session before our panel on LifeGate.
And let me get your slides up, and then you can take it away.
So that's to the right.
When we get
the talk up, we should be all set.
Actually, is it going?
All right. Hello, everybody. So,
this talk is probably a little bit different from the other ones because
I'm not talking about AI yet, because
that's what
we would like to do in the future. So it's about LifeGate.
So LifeGate
is a mind map representing all
species. So what do we have? We have a map,
a mind map,
containing all 2.6 million species
described so far. So we have data about all of them and
about five million synonyms. We
also included
all published phylogenies since about year 2000.
Very, very few cladistic analysis are included as
well, but most of them are
genetic phylogenies.
I won't have the time on explaining how this map was
constructed, but just approach us during the break
and I will explain. So what do we have?
You can zoom in from the phylum level,
class level, order level, to the species level.
We have the source of all the phylogenies.
We have the
synonyms. We have the number of species.
We have lots of pictures you can choose from.
And of course, you ask yourself what it is useful
for. I only have a tiny fraction of
examples of showing you.
Many of us talked about and heard about GBIF,
so here's a visualization of GBIF data.
So each orange point represents one
species
in the data set, so at least it is mentioned
once in GBIF. So basically, that means that
blue, there's nothing. So we have big gaps here
in the Coleoptera,
here in the algae, even in mosses.
And well, you can have a look on that because
everything's in there. You see what's missing.
This is another view of the IUCN Red Data
List.
Now, this inlet here is a picture of
amphibia, and here on the right, you see the mammals,
and it's on top of the
arthropods, but the arthropods are basically zero.
We don't know anything about
their
status. So what we are going on to do
is using this map and trying
to get as many attributes and
traits about them, trying to fix them
together onto the map,
and then
trying to
Finally produce a faceted search on
this so that you can say, "Please
give me all species of plants
that have leaves that are at least 15 centimeters long,
that
have hairs,
yellow corolla, that's living in Australia." And the more
input you put into the system, the less
output you have, and finally, you might end up with just
one or two species. And that's
why we are actually here, to
find information of what others
were doing in this respect.
All right. So we have many use cases.
We have scientists, we have museums, collections, citizen
science. Of course, you can just put your
natural history museum data in there and see what's missing
or where we are good and
where we are not good, or national parks or whatever.
And,
this is
what we are doing, and
I'm
exactly five minutes, so now my colleague is
going on.
Yeah. Thanks a lot. So while Martin spoke
mostly about what is there already, what he has been developing over the last,
I don't know, 15 years or so,
what I'm focusing on now is where do we want to go?
And where do we want to go is part of
what we are working on in a just started
DfG-funded project that brings together biological
expertise from Martin and others, and computer
science. And picking up again this
faceted search example.
So what we envision, what we dream of, is
we have somewhere original descriptions and
diagnosis, observation, and so on about certain
species.
And the idea is that the
biologists, the ecologists in the project,
figure out
what are the traits that are needed to identify species, for instance, and
what are traits that appear in certain classes of families of
a species. So they will define based on these
definitions, the relevant traits, of course, also looking at the
existing trait ontologies and so on.
And then we hope that the computer scientists, together
with some AI support,
will be able to automatically extract those
attributes from the literature. Yeah, so here we will produce
manually annotated ground truth and we'll then use that to train systems to
hopefully have an at least semiautomatic
further steps
that can then be fed into a user
interface that will support this faceted search.
And of course, this needs to go back to people with
biological expertise to quality control
and verify this.
It needs to go out to a community, needs to be
linked to,
yeah, the world at large and other initiatives,
and hopefully, then will also feed back
to the different further steps. And
if with this faceted search, someone finds out, well,
what I have here doesn't exist yet, it's not there in the
literature, then this new species that has been detected,
of course, should flow back here and then
become part of the systems. So the idea is to have some
self-sustainability here in the end.
So where are we? What's our ongoing work?
What are next steps? So you've seen the
LifeGate website. You can also already explore there with
what is there already. You can play with this,
use it for whatever you want. We have a large code base
for the computation of this visualization, and
also supporting the manual extraction of information
from papers. We have a large collection of papers and
photos,
about 25 million from around 500,000 species.
We have all published phylogenies, recent and extinct species,
divergent time.
The key gap is, from our perspective, that so far this
is largely a standalone application and is
not yet too well integrated into the overall
ecosystem. So what we envision with the new project and
why we are here is to transition from this individual
application to something connected
to others,
exposing APIs, sharing ontologies, knowledge
graphs,
also sharing information extraction, reusing information
extraction that others develop, reusing ontologies that
are existing elsewhere. So we want to integrate with
Checklist Plant, Catalogue of Life.
We want to connect and contribute to existing ontologies and
knowledge graphs, of course. We want to leverage information extraction
pipelines that other people develop or have developed.
And on the other hand, we would like to make these visualization
and interaction capabilities available to other
projects. Martin already mentioned some things.
If you have a database of species that are available in your
collection, for instance
You could use LifeGate to visualize where in this
map of life your collection are, where there are
gaps maybe, also where they go in this overall
picture, which is quite a nice way also to interact with the public, for
instance.
So we would like to connect, to exchange, to
open up what we have, and
for LifeGate to become an integral part of this
biodiversity knowledge ecosystem, not another
standalone platform. And we've already talked to many people
here, but would like to talk to more.
So if you are interested, if you see some way of coming together,
working together, please get in touch.
And this is the team behind LifeGate from
ecology and computer science.
So thanks for your attention and thanks to
DFG for funding us.
10:14.
We have time for one question,
if it's the right one.
Any questions?
Okay. Can I tell you, you guys are all champs.
I know this is the point in the week where you're all like, "I
could just use one more hour of sleep,"
but you're all doing great.
Any questions about this?
Well, thanks.
All right.
Okay, so we are going to move on to our panel.
And to begin, we're going to ask all of our speakers, both
from the session before lunch and after lunch, to come up here.
Unfortunately, we're not able to
offer you plushy chairs. You're going to have to stand.
But the panel's not an hour long, so hopefully that will be okay.
So if you could please all come up.
We're also going to have to do a little bit of juggling with the mics because we
only have one roving mic. I'll be going around
being able to hand the mic to people in the audience.
So I think we're going to, up here, have to
repurpose at least or maybe two of the
overhead mics as roving mics. Okay?
So maybe if you can unstrap them from yourself, so that you can
just pass them around. Hope that works.
And so I'm going to just start us off here with a question,
but I really would encourage you all to
think about questions you want to ask and don't be shy about
asking. We really don't want this to become a session where
we only ask some pre-prepared questions and that's going to
be it. Okay? So I'll start us off, give you maybe a minute or two
while a few people answer here, to think about your
own questions and formulate them.
Try to be concise, okay?
That leaves time for more interaction and for more answers.
All right? So I'm going to start us off here with
one question.
And
maybe I'm going to leave it to
you to choose
who
wants to answer, and if nobody wants to, then Rob's
just going to pick somebody.
Is AI ready
a property of only a dataset, or does it also depend on the
scientific question and task?
Who wants to start? Okay. All right.
So can you hear me?
Yes.
So I think data is always a model that you build of the world, and
a model is always an abstraction that is purpose-driven.
So what you take from the world is driven by the purpose, and
because of that,
AI ready
depends also on the purpose of the data, how you want to use
it. So you cannot have a dataset that is AI ready
just by itself without the application.
Okay.
I would add to that, maybe I think it's similar to data quality, which is
also defined as fitness for use, so it's not an
objective intrinsic property of the dataset, but
always has to be seen in the context of how you want to use it.
I rather like this distinction between AI fair and
AI readiness, which I think is exactly this distinction.
I'm going to play a bit of devil's advocacy.
I think that's probably right to a degree.
But when you start working with aggregation and pulling
complex datasets from multiple sources together, those
purposes become mixed, and that creates
complexity, and then the reuse of those data might be completely different
from the intended
construction of those datasets. Right?
And so there's still AI readiness in, say, an
aggregator's large-scale dataset.
But I think that becomes more a matter of each individual researcher
defining their fitness for purpose and use
using this aggregated data. And that becomes quite complex.
I don't think it's as easy as a simple answer there. So that's just my take.
Did you want to...
Maybe one more take, and then we'll open it up to the
audience here
for the next question.
So yeah, I fully agree that it's task-dependent, so yeah, completely.
But
I think it's also very important to have some snapshots ...
datasets that are, yes, for a particular task, but that
everybody, all researchers can share and work on, and
this has always been a
very strong motivation for research.
So yeah, we need such data, AI-ready datasets,
cleaned and ready.
Okay.
Our panelists are ready.
All right.
Who wants to ask a question? We'll open it up to the audience here. All right.
I want to pick up a topic that you, Tania, raised up in
the end of your slide, this triangle between
AI readiness, data provision, and so on.
And we always look now when we speak of AI readiness in
a unidirectional way. So what about the bidirectional way?
So the feedback back to the data providers,
how do they benefit from what we call
AI readiness?
Great question. And so I want to be pedantic about it.
We talk about FAIR for AI, not AI readiness.
AI readiness is very model task-specific.
We separate this, but FAIR for AI. There
are two aspects of bidirectional, and I don't know, I had a brain blip when I was
giving the talk. One of the biggest recommendations and what makes
one direction of it a lot better
is adding recipes, skill sets on the
dataset
side that essentially tell
agents and models of here's how you use this
dataset.
So this is in addition to data schema, so this is the next level of
data schema that helps agents
do this. The other part of
bidirectionality
is starting to be thought in a couple of projects.
One of them is CyVerse, which is a US
data fabric, part of it came out of data fabric initiative for all of
scientific data infrastructure.
But
there are a couple of things there.
One is having the
DOI or other identifiers that come from the very
one unit, like smallest unit of data, and propagate all the way back,
and then
every aggregation pings all the entire chain of
DOIs or object identifiers that constitute
that collection.
And so this way,
you can propagate the value, you propagate citations, you can propagate
the use in any model, the attribution.
It
also allows, for example, where in the other panel I just came from,
this discussion that in some cases, in some regions, we're starting to have so
much data that we can't store it.
But what we're seeing also is there's tons of duplication, and
so you have one image, and then somebody just has a crop of that image,
and they store that crop. And then we spend a lot of time on
de-duplicating data. So whereas you shouldn't do this, you should have that one
image stored once, one location, that's it.
Everybody else store the coordinates, store the link to it, store the
link with modifications that you made. Not the link, but the reference.
Not link, reference.
So that, I think this kind of provides the back and forth.
And the other thing that the CyVerse project is starting to do, and we're
piloting it with the NEON, National Ecological Observatory data,
the metadata version, is where the dataset also contains
this kind of
expanded permissions
set. Like we used to have the individual group
public of read, write, execute. So in this case, it
starts having, okay, you essentially operationalize the
data use and licensing agreement, and you can tell for these models, for
this use case, for these kinds of model, for this use case.
And then every time it is used,
the model registers its use with the dataset, which
propagates all the way back to the original.
So that starts giving you this bidirectionality, both of
attribution and of value. So if I ran this model
or trained this model on this dataset, it means that
everything in this dataset contributed and should have that,
not just attribution, but valuation, because we're starting to talk
about nature valuation, biodiversity markets,
the whole economic systems being built on the value of data.
Any other take on the question from
anyone else on the panel?
It's okay if not. The question was directed at Tania, after all.
Next question from the audience.
Thanks, Hilmar. And thanks to all of you for your talks.
It was a very exciting day, and the question I was going
to ask is maybe partly answered by what's up on the screen here.
I was going to ask,
especially those of you who've been around for a while, who've been trying to do
this for a long time.
Some things remain challenging, some things are a lot easier.
I would love to know, especially for those of you who've been hammering away at
this for years and years,
well, let's not focus on the easy stuff, let's focus on the difficult stuff.
AI seems like magic. Lots of things get easier.
Some of these things, I think,
can be addressed with AI, but not everything can.
So what's the hardest part now for you?
And it could be funding, it could be people, but
technically, whatever you want.
So in our practice, what becomes more challenging with
AI is convincing people to open up their data.
So I have a lot of colleagues that say, "As long as these tech
giants just harvest the data, regardless of whether it's allowed or not, I will
not make my data open anymore. I will not make it available
anymore." And I think we have a real problem there.
Any other take? There got to be more takes on this. Come on.
I'm going to "yes, and" to that, and we're seeing it
especially in
Latin America and Africa.
Very strong push
against open data and this notion that open data is a very Western and
colonial concept, and the doctrine of digital
discovery, where the Global North comes to the Global
South to discover things
now digitally, has
a very strong pushback, and hence the data sovereignty.
And we're seeing it now going all the way to UN and the Convention on Biological
Diversity. Two years ago, this was the digital sequence
information, where a discussion, if you're
not in the world of policy, that
the conversation is about who
owns, who benefits,
and who gets
direct money value from the
biodiversity genomic
and other digital sequence information.
One of the examples was corals in Puerto Rico, that the sequence
from there is used by pharmaceutical industry
to produce sunscreen and other beauty products that they, of course, benefit, but
the corals are dying and being bleached.
And
so then
there is a whole
discussion on the
whole chain of provenance and value for digital sequence information
that was discussed two years ago at COP16.
What is absolutely clear that the sequence part is
going to be dropped, and is going to be biodiversity
digital information, and it's going to be the same kinds of conversation.
Who benefits? How do you attribute value?
If it's used for product development or for discovery or
for decision-making,
how does the
monetary value directly go back to the original
source of that digital information?
And so then, therefore, the pushback,
more than 90% of biodiversity data in the
world comes from
private, indigenous, and
local community-held land.
And so that's where the strongest pushback is, "Not my
data, not for you, not
for AI."
Yeah.
Oh, do you want to go?
Yeah, why don't you go?
I'll be fast.
Sure.
It can be quick, yeah. Another key challenge is
data heterogeneity, I think. What we have learned
from training models at European scale, whether for
identification or SDMs, is that you have different protocols.
All the bias of your AI comes from this heterogeneity.
Even the image resolutions of things like that, when you look at in a model
like PlantNet, sometimes you say, "Okay, why this species is not well-recognized?"
It's because the training set was smaller resolution, different
compression, really technical things that you don't imagine at the beginning.
And it's also the case, I think, for protocols, all that kind of stuff.
And so we really need to synchronize the data that is collected.
For me, that's all the bias from AI come from the data, of course.
Yeah, I-
So I want to just step in here and offer a moment
for a different perspective.
I just wanted to push back a little bit against Tanja's quote there.
So we recently ran our BID program this year,
and we had over 1,000 applications
asking for 48 million euros
of projects from Latin America, Africa, and the Pacific Islands.
We could fund
less than 5% of those.
The
prerequisite for that program is open share data.
So there is a great demand there for sharing open data.
And we also work with a
task force at the secretariat that we run with a indigenous data task
force. The indigenous communities are willing to share
and use data as long as it's done properly and we work with them.
So that's
very important. So
there are the bad stories, but there are good movements as well.
And there is that demand, I think, still globally for open
data.
Hey, Joe, thanks for that perspective. That's really important.
Where you went was very broad in terms of challenges, but I think a lot of this
boils down to trust as well, and that's a frontier
area for AI. How do you trust AI outputs?
And I think
a lot of these
challenges are also opportunities, right?
So building better mechanisms to instill trust about what an AI is
delivering as an output,
thinking hard about whether AIs can actually deliver causal thinking, which I think
is a really cool thing about our session, where people really
focused on causality and how causal mapping ontologies are so important
as co-training with these
less deterministic and less causal approaches.
I know there's causal AI and people are working on this, but I think there's a lot
of issues around trust, causality.
And really, I'll just lay down one more thing and then turn it back to Hilmar.
I want a world of empathy. I'm not sure AI will deliver that.
So-
Can I say yes and to-
No, you can't. Let's move on.
So I don't think we disagree, by the way.
I think, yes, sharing data, but with very strong governance, and I think this is
the body that can, at least to a large extent, deliver on the
governance
of data sharing so that it actually protects,
enables all the broader conversation of trust.
So to round out the panel here, because we're about to come up to the
end of our time, I want to maybe draw
back to
the one peak of hype with AI
and machine learning that came, I don't know how many years ago,
where
it became apparent that you can learn a lot from the
data themselves. You didn't have to have much
preconceived notion of models. And so that led to the
notion that we can really
ignore and drop everything we've accumulated in
knowledge over a very long time. And it seems
like
integrating knowledge into AI is really making a bit of a comeback, and the
recognition that ontologies that capture knowledge in a
computable and standardized form are making a bit of a
comeback. And so I'm really interested to know,
because it's also been a subject near and dear to my heart for a very long time,
what
do you think about what exactly is the role
or importance of ontologies in this space, if there is any?
Maybe you think, "No, we don't need ontologies."
Oh, I don't know.
No, I consider myself a relative newcomer to ontologies.
I think three years ago, I really started going down a rabbit hole, and I
think it is helpful to have a backbone of some sort of
certainty.
I don't think it's controversial to say, though, that ontology world has a
governance problem, and I
did want to answer the last question about what remains to be hard, and I
think it's messy human stuff. And you can't separate messy
human stuff from ontologies. There are some
people, like Niko's doing some really good work.
Niko Matsalouglou? Did my best there,
on governance of ontologies and thinking about the softer
science stuff. How do we collectively make decisions that
can impact people's lives, that concern real
things on the ground for communities?
We need to have some kind of
an approach that is
inclusive and transparent and all of those things
that the social science world has been really working hard on.
I think bringing those to ontologies is really important, especially in the AI era.
And part of the appeal, too, of ontologies is it kind of de-black boxes
LLMs in a way. The actual transformer
model is still a black box. It's still billions of parameters that you could
never feasibly evaluate.
But if it's rooting its decision in an ontology, you can maybe trace
that somewhat, and that's at least why I'm a fan of the structured
data and ontology world is because it provides some layer of
explainability.
Yeah. Thanks.
Thank you. I could add to that. So I would extend it to also include
knowledge graphs, not only ontologies.
And the good thing here is, we cannot all develop
our own LLMs, right? So we use the LLMs.
We have no control on the data that they have been fed,
but we have control over the ontologies and the knowledge
graphs that we use in combination with that LLM.
So we get a little bit control back if we do that.
That's maybe a great place for- Yeah, I think that's a great place
to close. Did you want to close it out, Rob? No, go for it.
Okay, so we're closing it out here. Thanks everyone for attending.
It's been really well attended.
I'm sure you found the presentations really
informative, as much as I did. Thanks to all our
speakers. Let's give them another hand.
And we're going into the coffee break here, but we'll also have a little bit of a
social
at the
Politikern, which is just across from the street here in this
big plaza. If you stay in the big plaza that's right outside of the conference
center and turn 360, you're going to see it, I
promise. It's going to be towards the
tall building on one end, and we'll have a bit of a
drink there and
I guess get us ready for the Torchlight festival. 5:30.
5:30. That's right. 5:30. And thanks to Hilmar.
And Rob. And- And everybody else on the committee.
Okay. Thank you, everyone.
No, wait.
A group photo? Tanya wants a group photo.
Group photo. Rob!
Rob, can you come up?
Can somebody with the
camera?
This isn't working either.
Okay.
All right, now we're getting somewhere.
It's still stalled on the--
Let's just cancel that. It's just... All right.
Okay. This computer's had a day. All right. That's fine.
I have
to download them one by one, because I
can't open them on-- And all the ones on
my--
It's
okay.
I
got the first two. We'll get the others later.
All right, let's get this show on the road.
End of the day,
let's get moving.
Hold on.
From the beginning. What do we got?
No, we still don't have everything.
All right, let's get this show going. All right. Hi, my name is Ben Norton.
I'm at Yale University. I'm your moderator today, and do you want to introduce
yourself as the co-moderator?
Andre.
Andre. He's the co-moderator. Right. All right.
So quick word,
digital tools for data discovery, resolution, and exchange. Is this good?
Last talk of the day.
Thank you to our sponsors. I think you've probably heard that today, so this is
good. And
yeah, I think we all know this by now. All right, let's get going.
Ben.
There we go. All right. There we go. All right.
First talk
is Patrick.
You got one?
I got it.
We're going to make technology work today.
Fantastic. All right, great.
Very much, Ben.
Hi, everyone.
So
I'm going to talk about
literature services,
and in particular, I will try to
demonstrate how data standards can support
applications such as question answering.
So question answering is what you usually do when you talk to a
chatbot, actually.
So some words before to set the stage, before going
into the question answering part.
So
the back-end services that I will use are based on the
SIB literature services. So that we maintain in
Switzerland,
and we maintain different front-end.
There are many of them,
those that were in the previous session
on the Libroscope. I've seen, for instance, what we developed with Triage.
But now I'm going to focus on Biodiversity PMC,
and in particular, the interaction with Biodiversity PMC
with question answering. Okay?
So this is Biodiversity PMC landing page.
So you arrive and you have all these collections.
So
Medline,
PubMed Central Extended. So
in addition to the regular PubMed Central, we also have many
journals that are not in PubMed, like all the Pensoft journal,
the SetUp journals, and many others that are not deposited
into PubMed that we harvest. Then there is a supplementary
data index. It's about
a lot of files, like Excel spreadsheets and
virtually anything, like PowerPoint or CSV or stuff
like that. And also
about 24 million images, and all images
have been OCRized. So if you want to search for the content of
images and the same for the content of the spreadsheets, you
can search with this index, which is something you cannot do into
PubMed or in most of the-- Not even in Open Alex.
So Open Alex will not index the content of the image.
And then we also have Plazi, which is important for
taxonomic treatments.
We are talking about biodiversity. And then we have Zenodo.
Today, Zenodo is a relatively
compact collection. But what we will soon call grey literature is going to
inflate. So by the end of the year, we probably will have more than one
billion
content coming from Zenodo and some other repositories.
Okay, so
this is for the Biodiversity PMC. It's large, not as large as
Open Alex, but much more focused on biodiversity.
And if I try to compare, let's say, the content of
Biodiversity PMC compared to PubMed or Europe PMC,
so we have a superset of them. So
PubMed is focused on medical stuff, and we have all the medical
stuff about parasites and,
I don't know, ticks and
bone disorders or vector-borne disorders and so on.
But on top of this, we have a lot of agriculture and anything related
to ecology or environmental sciences, we try to also get this.
So it's a superset of PubMed. But we still focus on life
science as opposed to, let's say, Google Scholar or
OpenAlex or Unpaywall. Okay? And we also provide access
to supplementary data. Okay. So now this is the landing page.
Imagine that you are interested in Collembola. Okay?
Collembola trophic guilds. You would get this type of results.
So starting with Medline,
43,000. PMC+,
116,000, and then supplementary data, PLOS, and so on.
Okay? That's the way to search the content.
What is specific here is that
the content of this paper has been pre-annotated.
So
we have about 50 terminologies for a total of
about close to nine million concepts, and
each of these concepts have been pre-annotated as they
occur within the paper. So
for instance, if you are interested in Collembola or any taxon,
then you can start with browsing the different terminologies that
we have. So Collembola, you see that Collembola is available in
NCBI. It's available in Catalogue of Life.
It's available in Agrovoc. Okay? So many terminologies would
provide some taxonomy or
taxon names related to Collembola.
And then, of course, you get a concept, and you can click on them, and
it will take you to the literatures.
But
of course, that's not the best way to search.
What is important is that
all the papers
have been annotated. So for instance, here you see that we have an
annotation. So the terminology that we annotated is
Open Tree of Life. Okay? Then you have a version of the ontology,
and then you have a concept ID, and then you have the preferred name.
Okay? So this is Nyctereutes
procyonoides, and the
one that we found in the text is the vernacular name, which
is raccoon dog. Okay? So because we
handle all the synonyms, we normalize with a unique
identifier, but if there are dozens of synonyms, then we still
can find the
match. Okay. This is a distribution of the different terminologies.
We do not have 50 here. It's about 25.
But you see that you have a lot of things about taxonomy.
Okay? That's not a surprise. It's something that
is sizable. Okay?
Okay. Now moving to question answering.
So what we did with the question answering, we normalized all
this collection of the literatures.
It has been normalized with concept. Okay?
You can even get the concept individually.
And then we need to do exactly the same thing at the query level, so we
will normalize the query. Okay? You have a query. We will normalize it.
Okay? Raccoon dog will be normalized with an ID.
And then you can query the indexes with all the collection.
I don't want to detail them all. It's going to fetch some document, and
then we will apply to some
factoric extraction or generative extraction on top of this. Okay?
So
this is very similar to a chatbot, but you see that I will show you that it
behaves a bit differently. So
if you want to do the first model that we have, the
default one is that we will extract only
fact out of the paper. So you are not going to get a page
of answers like in your favorite Gemini or
whatever is your model, but you will really get the answer.
And we made, of course, evaluation of this answer.
So in this particular question, this is a good answer, by the way. Okay?
So borreliosis is one of the relevant one.
And you can look at the other one. They will be very similar to your
favorite bot, but it's extracted from the paper.
It's not like an interpretation of the bot.
So this is what you would get with your favorite
chatbot. This is not wrong. It's not wrong,
but of course,
it's a little bit verbose. Okay? So you have things about common sign and
symptoms. That's not your question, but you will get this for free with your
chatbot. Okay? So this is what we separate between
factoried question answering and let's say, talkative
question answering. Okay. Now some of the results.
So
we tested on a benchmark, which is called SQuAD. I think SQuAD is very large.
It's like 100,000 questions and answers.
And we did quite well. So the important one here is
F1 here. Okay? So we are above 70%
precision for the top return answer, and it doesn't mean that the
next one is not good, but sometimes the
best is in position three. You see?
So this is the way you measure this F1. Okay?
So this is with the extractive, and of course, I'm sure you want to know how it
would work with the generative.
Generative is a bit more tricky because it's very verbose.
So either you think that any match that is relevant
there is relevant, you count it as positive, or you also
try to limit the top here and say only the top here has to be positive.
So that's why it's difficult to compare extractive and
generative. Okay? That's intrinsically difficult.
Nevertheless,
I can show you what it
looks like if you choose the generative model.
Still, it will be a bit different from your chatbot.
So of course, we will use pre-trained model.
Of course, we will do retrieval-augmented generation, and we will use biodiversity
PTC in the back end.
Then we will
specialize the model where we do all the fine-tuning, and we try to keep
a low
compute cost.
So if you come with a question like what trophic guilds are
associated with Collembola,
you will get only two document that match your answer,
and that will be the type of text that will be generated.
So Based on the provided document, Collembola are primarily
associated with detritivore. And actually, Collembola
as first and mostly detritivorous species.
Okay, that's it. And of course, this is to be compared with
what you get with your favorite chatbot, where you will get all
the possible scenarios for
Collembola. They can be fungivores, they can be bacterivores, they
can do swelling, they can be anything.
The good one you would expect is that one.
You see it's clearly not in position one.
So actually,
this is what I think we can provide as an alternative to the
verbose chatbot, because
we only provide two, three, or four documents, and the
synthetic answer that you have here is really more relevant than
what you get with a chatbot. This is what I wanted to
demonstrate.
Of course,
that one is publicly available, so you can
already query it biodiversity PMC now.
And that one,
let's say, the generative one, should become public in October.
So I hope you will test it as soon as it is available.
Thank you very much.
And we have one minute for questions.
Questions, anybody?
Thank you.
Coffee.
All right. Fantastic. Thank you.
Perfect. That's great.
And next up is Christian.
Christian Langer, is that how you pronounce it?
This way. All right, cool.
All right.
Do I switch it? Okay, it's working.
What's that?
It's working.
Okay.
This is where I transmit my internal dialogue to the entire audience. It's good.
All right. Yours is... This has been a bit confusing.
I see.
Okay.
I had them.
Awesome. There you go.
Okay, perfect.
Hello, everyone. I changed the title of my
presentation a little bit, so don't be confused.
I will still talk about the same thing. So I'm Christian.
I'm a programmer at iDiv, and this is my team at iDiv.
iDiv is a German center for biodiversity research in Leipzig, Germany,
and my team is pushing biodiversity data cubes forward.
So,
how do you...
Exactly. So,
the question that we all have is how can we describe the
entire biodiversity? So in the GeoBon community developed
years ago, the concept of EBVs.
EBVs are Essential Biodiversity Variables,
and these are
a set of measurements to describe biodiversity
across time, space, and entity.
So it's the gap between raw biodiversity data and
indicators.
So we have eight EBV classes and
with
22 variables. For instance, one EBV class would be species
population
with a variable species distribution.
And EBVs can have the potential to serve as a foundation for
biodiversity monitoring programs.
So think about EBVs as a middleware between raw data
and the indicators. So raw data, for instance, would be in situ data,
remote sensing.
So
GBIF data, so the typical presence-absence,
specimens data would be then--
So GBIF data would be the raw data.
But of course, a GBIF has not only occurrence data, it has also abundance data with
the Event Core, but this would also be raw data.
And indicators would be
the changes in biodiversity, so aggregated trends.
There you can see actually the trend of
biodiversity.
And think about EBVs as modeled data sets.
And exactly for these data sets, we developed a format,
a schema to describe the biodiversity.
And this schema we are calling EBV cube.
This cube is in GitHub. You can check it out.
I'm not going so much into detail now.
You can check it out by yourself.
It's actually a raster format. So we are using NetCDF for all
biodiversity variables. So as I said before, it's not only species
data, it's data about traits, habitats,
DNA, phenology, pollination.
For instance, one data set is about chlorophyll content
of a country.
So
we are not a competitor to Darwin Core,
which handles only species specimen data.
So we are describing the complete biodiversity.
So this NetCDF contains metadata, which is in
ACD/MCF
... groups in a data cube which has four
dimensions. So the x and y, the time, and the
entity.
And all these cubes are categorized and visualized in our
EBV data portal.
It's EBV portal, you can check it out. It's portal.geobon.org.
It's a portal for GeoBon,
and it's an open access platform to categorize and visualize
EBV cubes.
So on the right side, you can see our metadata catalog.
So there you can search and filter by metadata.
It has an API, it has an automatic DOI assignment,
a version control system, and so on.
The visualizer
is used, of course, to visualize the cubes,
but we are using the WMS, but not the
normal OGC
standard. It's
an extension from the WMS. It's called NCWMS.
It's like an entire API specifically
designed for NetCDF data.
So here you can see an example.
I choose also an example
based on species data, which we produced from the GBIF
occurrence cubes.
Then we check out
the entities. You can see here also complete taxonomic backbone from GBIF.
Of course, when you search a data set about habitats, you can see then
the entities would be habitat, not species, and you can see the complete
taxonomic backbone from this habitat.
When you check Show on Map,
we will guide it to the browser, and you can
browse the cube by entity.
You can select, for instance, this
species.
You can select scenarios and metric.
You can change the time. And a really cool thing is,
basically, you can search any region in the world, any area of
interest, for instance, any national park in Norway,
and you can calculate the trend of it.
So how do we do it? So, as I said before, we are using the
NCWMS,
and here is a little figure with the help of ChatGPT,
how we do it. So, on the left side, you can see all the
data that we are using. For instance, genetic, species
population, species traits, ecosystem functioning, structure.
We have a cube of all this data.
We are using THREDDS,
which produce the NCWMS.
We have also
the API
from our portal,
and we have built a really simple JavaScript web GIS,
a web app,
to display or to send the request to
THREDDS and to get some responses.
So here's the magic.
This is the NCWMS, and
it produce some requests.
I
will not go into detail in all of this, but
here you can see the different requests
and
the responses the request produce.
So, for instance, get time series, we get it JSON or CSV
to calculate the trend over time.
And get map, for instance, for the tiles.
And I can show you how the get map is working to produce the tiles.
So, for instance, here's the normal URL.
You can see
the first, we pass the name for the request. It's the get map.
It produce a tile. It's a flat image.
The metric one is the habitat suitability in this case.
The entity one, we have to pass an integer, but in this case, it's
also a species name, and here in this case, it's gorilla, gorilla.
We can specify the tile size,
the coordinate reference system, the time, and the spatial extent
as a bounding box. And what we get is the API response
is the PNG file showing the bounding box
512 pixel times 512 pixel for the species on
January 1st, 1990, in as Web Mercator in
Viridis color. So if you want to
display a different time, we just have to change the parameter in the URL,
and we get a new tile.
So this is basically it, but of course, it has pros and cons
from our software architecture.
So first of all, it's super lightweight.
It is open source and easy to set up.
So we don't use a complicated JavaScript framework.
So it's just vanilla JavaScript.
It's super fast for almost all data sets we are using for all
cubes,
and THREDDS is designed specifically for NetCDF.
And a real cool thing is it allows DAP 4 for
NetCDF-4, so the open DAP standard.
So we can get the binary data
or the real data array from the
different chunks of this data. So we don't need to download
the whole NetCDF. We can
send specific chunk request to get
parts of the data.
So the cons,
it is super fast, but for high-resolution maps, so
let's say 10-meter global data sets
Our server will definitely reach the limit.
So we have to downscale it by a factor of 10.
So the data sets we are visualizing,
10 meter would result in 100 meter.
And SWATS is not designed for cloud-based environments, for instance,
S3 bucket,
and also NetCDF.
So we have to switch to another format, which is then Zarr or
Currant.
And
NC WMS is not directly an OGC WMS
standard. It is just OGC compliant,
and this will maybe
produce some problems in future. But
nevertheless, for most of the data sets we have, it's super
sufficient.
And yes, so
that's basically it. This is our team, and thank you.
So we have a couple minutes for questions.
No?
Thank you. Guillaume Body from the
French Biodiversity Agency.
So your technology provide very quick
results
based on raster only. I have two question, actually.
Can you handle information which is not
point-based but
shape file based? For instance, if I know the
abundance in France
for some birds, can you handle that without a map behind it?
And secondly, when you're downscaling, when you provide
results,
how can you guarantee the reliability of the
information you provide?
Because showing a result is something, showing a result that mean
something for the users
is a little bit more complicated. And for instance,
you show a graphic of
the number of occurrences
in some areas.
I don't know how to use
a number of occurrences as it does not represent the
abundance nor the distribution.
Okay, so there are three questions, I think.
So the first question, yes, it's a good one.
No, we can't.
So the format is raster based,
means NetCDF.
So we have some requests to
provide also this format as a vector,
in a vector format.
Shape file, okay, maybe not shape file.
But,
so the short answer, right now, we can't.
So we have to produce a raster.
But in future, maybe...
In my opinion, I see
maybe the schema
a bit
independently from the format.
The format right now is NetCDF.
Maybe in future it can be vector also,
but the schema is maybe more independent.
It can be applied for all formats. So I
see it like this in the future.
But
right now, we don't have this possibility.
Yes, for the downscaling,
this is just for visualizing. The real data, you get full
resoluted.
So if you have 10 meters global data, you can
download the data.
But for visualizing, for a really huge data set,
it's downscaled. But which is not a big problem because it's
just for visualizing.
And, be aware,
here you can see a nice scale on the bottom.
Most of the maps
which are out there and publicly available have the highest
resolution, I think it's 30 meter.
So if you have a map which is 10 meters,
you have to visualize this map on a 30-meter scale.
So you can't even zoom in.
Maybe NASA and the military has higher, it has up to three meters,
but the most publicly available maps from ESRI, from NASA-- not NASA,
from
OpenStreetMap have the highest 30 meters.
So you can't even
zoom more in than 30 meters.
And the third question?
What-
How do you interpret this map, for instance?
What can you say about biodiversity with this map that you're showing?
So you don't see here--
So it's based on GBIF data,
but each map
has a different metric.
Okay? And this metric is,
for instance, the total number of occurrences.
It's a really, really simple model,
not really like a super statistical model, but it's a really simple one,
this case.
But each
data set is different.
So, for instance,
I can't tell you now all the different metrics, but when you check the portal,
so there are
Dutzends of different metrics. So in this case, you can see the
total number of species occurrence,
which is calculated by the different GeoBon community.
So for instance, you can...
And you check the general information, you scroll down, you can see
the methods, and you can see exactly how the dataset is produced.
And you can see also the provenance and
we have all these in our metadata schema.
So the-
What's that?
I know. Yeah, it's not.
I know.
All
right.
Next up.
There's no presentation. Who's our next speaker?
Ines?
Not here.
There's no...
Yeah. There's no video. All right.
Well-
It's virtual video.
If there's no video, there's a problem
in the folder.
All right.
One second.
It's the end of the day.
There's just not-- There are only three in the folder, and the intro.
I'd hate to...
Let me try to find.
It's Dmitri. It's a recorded, and we'll start playing that, and I'm going to
go see if I can find the other one while we're at it. All right.
Hold on one second.
Here at TADWIG, we try to be on the ball with stuff and
usually works out pretty well.
All right.
Open the file.
Now we're talking. All right. Fantastic.
Hello, everybody. My name is Dima Mazarin,
and I want to talk today how to use
local scientific name resolution and reconciliation
with Gen vérifier.
So what is Gen vérifier?
It is a scientific name reconciliation program.
It uses advanced algorithms that allow to do
partial and fuzzy matching,
also authorship matching.
It has a massive scale. We have pre-indexed more than
80 million records across more than 100 popular
biodiversity datasets.
It has a high throughput.
We have
a system that allows to run more than
2,000 names per second.
And now it has a local or remote support,
which means Gen vérifier can either run locally
or you can use centralized service at
vérifierglobalnames.org.
So why would somebody want to use Gen vérifier locally
if it is available as a service on the web?
The first reason,
there might be no particular dataset that you
need.
It can be that a dataset is proprietary, it can
be institutional,
or it can be specialized dataset that only you use.
When Gen vérifier runs locally, you do not need
network, you don't need internet,
and that can be useful if you are traveling or
if you are in the field.
It is also possible to update particular
dataset of interest
as many times as you want.
And for example,
you want to
update a particular dataset, but in
a centralized service, it will only be updated in a few
months.
Also,
for local Gen vérifier, you don't need the same
datasets as a centralized service.
You can only put datasets that you need
for your particular purposes,
and that will make application run faster.
The main thing about Gen vérifier
is to import data.
It has to be done regularly.
The way we did it before,
we used
datasets from everywhere,
and we had diverse or non-standard formats.
The parsing of these datasets could be complex,
and digestion can be not easy.
If there are minor errors, we might spend
half a day to fix a particular error.
For example,
there can be encoding problems
or metadata
is not
written correctly in XML file in Darwin Core
It can be that
field delimiter has problems in a file,
or it can be that a CSV file, comma-separated file,
does not have consistent number of fields,
and we have to figure out
how to do ingestion correctly.
The way we do it now, we use an application called GNDB.
This application
is part of SF WORK
program that we developed at Species File Group.
GNDB uses unified standard, which means
it can be highly automated how we ingest files.
It has a much higher performance than previous system.
For example, we are able to ingest catalog of life in a matter
of minutes instead of hours, as it was before.
We have a consistent workflow.
So if we have a system
on a
centralized or if you
use it locally,
the workflow is exactly the same. There is no any difference.
We have flexible sources.
We can ingest file from local hard drive, or
we can ingest file from the web.
The system allows to convert with
ease Darwin Core files, ColDP files,
tab and comma-separated files, and so on.
So
let us explain
what GNDB is and what SF WORK
project is.
SF WORK is an active approach to a data
standard.
At the core of SF WORK, there is a
SFGA format.
And the difference between SFGA format and other
biodiversity formats
or standards
is that
we can use SFGA as soon as we downloaded
it.
It doesn't require additional step of converting it
into a database.
And there are all kind of functionality, all kind of
applications that can use this file directly.
In our case, with GNDB,
we do aggregation. So GNDB is an
aggregator of several SFGA files
into one database.
How does it work?
At first, we have several
databases, several datasets in a
variety of formats. It can be just a
text, or it can be tab-separated file,
comma-separated file, ColDP, or Darwin Core
file.
We have program called SF, and we have program Harvester.
We use both of them to
convert all this variety of formats into
SFGA format.
And when we have all the SFGA files that we need,
we run GNDB
to use these files and populate
GN Verifier database, which is currently Postgres.
As soon as database is ready, we can run GN Verifier
directly.
And when we do that, we will have a web interface
to name reconciliation,
command line interface, and also API.
So you can write scripts that will use this local
service.
So what do we do
to add metadata to
these
newly ingested
datasets, which are not in the
official GN Verifier?
To make sense of these datasets,
you would need to enter metadata information
in a YAML file.
As soon as this metadata is created,
GNDB will be able to understand it and
add it to the GN Verifier database.
All the datasets that are
not official should be with ID
1,000 or larger
to avoid conflict.
So here are example commands.
First command, SF command,
takes a Darwin Core file and converts it into
SFGA file,
zipped version. We zip it for
just making it smaller.
The next command, GNDB populate, uses ID
of that new dataset
and sends
its data into
GN Verifier database.
After all the datasets are
imported into
database, we have to run GNDB optimize.
It creates several additional tables, and it
also creates a view which denormalizes the
data.
Denormalization is important for speed
After that, we run
GN Verifier service. It is called Gnames.
And when GN Verifier API service is running,
we can start GN Verifier as a web service
using command gn-verify -p
with the name of the port where it will run, or we can use
GN Verifier directly as a command line system.
Both work the same.
We are
ready to support this new functionality.
It is new,
and we understand it
can be
hard to start using it. So we are happy
to help people to set up GNDB locally.
We are
happy to help.
And as I said before, the system on a local
machine and the system to run Verifier
globalnames.org are exactly the same.
We are still doing active development, and your feedback will
help us to support more dataset formats,
and it will help us to understand how to
streamline the pipeline better.
And this is all. Thank you for listening.
So
the third presentation is not located anywhere on Google Drive.
It's completely missing.
Even the letters Y-A-D are not there.
All right. So I think that's it for today, guys.
Can we go there? Oops.
Where's the mouse go?
Perfect. That's it. Thanks for coming.
And
15 minutes back there today. It's good. So round of applause for our speakers.
Any questions about anything?
Thoughts,
concerns about the world, Earth, Tadwig?
All right, good. That's it, guys.